OK, this is linear algebra
lecture nine.
And this is a key lecture,
this is where we get these
ideas of linear independence,
when a bunch of vectors are
independent -- or dependent,
that's the opposite.
The space they span.
A basis for a subspace or a
basis for a vector space,
that's a central idea.
And then the dimension of that
subspace.
So this is the day that those
words get assigned clear
meanings.
And emphasize that we talk
about a bunch of vectors being
independent.
Wouldn't talk about a matrix
being independent.
A bunch of vectors being
independent.
A bunch of vectors spanning a
space.
A bunch of vectors being a
basis.
And the dimension is some
number.
OK, so what are the
definitions?
Can I begin with a fact,
a highly important fact,
that, I didn't call directly
attention to earlier.
Suppose I have a matrix and I
look at Ax equals zero.
Suppose the matrix has a lot of
columns, so that n is bigger
than m.
So I'm looking at n equations
-- I mean, sorry,
m equations,
a small number of equations m,
and more unknowns.
I have more unknowns than
equations.
Let me write that down.
More unknowns than equations.
More unknown x-s than
equations.
Then the conclusion is that
there's something in the null
space of A, other than just the
zero vector.
The conclusion is there are
some non-zero x-s such that Ax
is zero.
There are some special
solutions.
And why?
We know why.
I mean, it sort of like seems
like a reasonable thing,
more unknowns than equations,
then it seems reasonable that
we can solve them.
But we have a,
a clear algorithm which starts
with a system and does
elimination, gets the thing into
an echelon form with some pivots
and pivot columns,
and possibly some free columns
that don't have pivots.
And the point is here there
will be some free columns.
The reason, so the reason is
there must -- there will be free
variables, at least one.
That's the reason.
That we now have this --
a complete, algorithm,
a complete systematic way to
say, OK, we take the system Ax
equals zero, we row reduce,
we identify the free variables,
and, since there are n
variables and at most m pivots,
there will be some free
variables, at least one,
at least n-m in fact,
left over.
And those variables I can
assign non-zero values to.
I don't have to set those to
zero.
I can take them to be one or
whatever I like,
and then I can solve for the
pivot variables.
So then it gives me a solution
to Ax equals zero.
And it's a solution that isn't
all zeros.
So, that's an important point
that we'll use now in this
lecture.
So now I want to say what does
it mean for a bunch of vectors
to be independent.
OK.
So this is like the background
that we know.
Now I want to speak about
independence.
OK.
Let's see.
I can give you the abstract
definition, and I will,
but I would also like to give
you the direct meaning.
So the question is,
when vectors x1,
x2 up to --
Suppose I have n vectors are
independent if.
Now I have to give you -- or
linearly independent -- I'll
often just say and write
independent for short.
OK.
I'll give you the full
definition.
These are just vectors in some
vector space.
I can take combinations of
them.
The question is,
do any combinations give zero?
If some combination of those
vectors gives the zero vector,
other than the combination of
all zeros, then they're
dependent.
They're independent if no
combination gives the zero
vector -- and then I have,
I'll have to put in an except
the zero combination.
So what do I mean by that?
No combination gives the zero
vector.
Any combination c1 x1+c2 x2
plus, plus cn xn is not zero
except for the zero combination.
This is when all the c-s,
all the c-s are zero.
Then of course.
That combination -- I know I'll
get zero.
But the question is,
does any other combination give
zero?
If not, then the vectors are
independent.
If some other combination does
give zero, the vectors are
dependent.
OK.
Let's just take examples.
Suppose I'm in,
say, in two dimensional space.
OK.
I give you -- I'd like to first
take an example -- let me take
an example where I have a vector
and twice that vector.
So that's two vectors,
V and 2V.
Are those dependent or
independent?
Those are dependent for sure,
right, because there's one
vector is twice the other.
One vector is twice as long as
the other, so if the word
dependent means anything,
these should be dependent.
And they are.
And in fact,
I would take two of the first
-- so here's,
here is a vector V and the
other guy is a vector 2V,
that's my -- so there's a
vector V1 and my next vector V2
is 2V1.
Of course those are dependent,
because two of these first
vectors minus the second vector
is zero.
That's a combination of these
two vectors that gives the zero
vector.
OK, that was clear.
Suppose, suppose I have a
vector -- here's another
example.
It's easy example.
Suppose I have a vector and the
other guy is the zero vector.
Suppose I have a vector V1 and
V2 is the zero vector.
Then are those vectors
dependent or independent?
They're dependent again.
You could say,
well, this guy is zero times
that one.
This one is some combination of
those.
But let me write it the other
way.
Let me say --
what combination,
how many V1s and how many V2s
shall I take to get the zero
vector?
If, if V1 is like the vector
two one and V2 is the zero
vector, zero zero,
then I would like to show that
some combination of those gives
the zero vector.
What shall I take?
How many V1s shall I take?
Zero of them.
Yeah, no, take no V1s.
But how many V2s?
Six.
OK.
Or five.
Then -- in other words,
the point is if the zero
vector's in there,
if the zero --
if one of these vectors is the
zero vector, independence is
dead, right?
If one of those vectors is the
zero vector then I could always
take -- include that one and
none of the others,
and I would get the zero
answer, and I would show
dependence.
OK.
Now, let me,
let me finally draw an example
where they will be independent.
Suppose that's V1 and that's
V2.
Those are surely independent,
right?
Any combination of V1 and V2,
will not be zero except,
the zero combination.
So those would be independent.
But now let me,
let me stick in a third vector,
V3.
Independent or dependent now,
those three vectors?
So now n is three here.
I'm in two dimensional space,
whatever, I'm in the plane.
I have three vectors that I
didn't draw so carefully.
I didn't even tell you what
exactly they were.
But what's this answer on
dependent or independent?
Dependent.
How do I know those are
dependent?
How do I know that some
combination of V1,
V2, and V3 gives me the zero
vector?
I know because of that.
That's the key fact that tells
me that three vectors in the
plane have to be dependent.
Why's that?
What's the connection between
the dependence of these three
vectors and that fact?
OK.
So here's the connection.
I take the matrix A that has V1
in its first column,
V2 in its second column,
V3 in its third column.
So it's got three columns.
And V1 -- I don't know,
that looks like about two one
to me.
V2 looks like it might be one
two.
V3 looks like it might be maybe
two, maybe two and a half,
minus one.
OK.
Those are my three vectors,
and I put them in the columns
of A.
Now that matrix A is two by
three.
It fits this pattern,
that where we know we've got
extra variables,
we know we have some free
variables, we know that there's
some combination --
and let me instead of x-s,
let me call them c1,
c2, and c3 -- that gives the
zero vector.
Sorry that my little bit of art
got in the way.
Do you see the point?
When I have a matrix,
I'm interested in whether its
columns are dependent or
independent.
The columns are dependent if
there is something in the null
space.
The columns are dependent
because this,
this thing in the null space
says that c1 of that plus c2 of
that plus c3 of this is zero.
So in other words,
I can go out some V1,
out some more V2,
back on V3, and end up zero.
OK.
So let -- here I've give the
general, abstract definition,
but let me repeat that
definition -- this is like
repeat -- let me call them Vs
now.
V1 up to Vn are the columns of
a matrix A.
In other words,
this is telling me that if I'm
in m dimensional space,
like two dimensional space in
the example, I can answer the
dependence-independence question
directly by putting those
vectors in the columns of a
matrix.
They are independent if the
null space of A,
of A, is what?
If I have a bunch of columns in
a matrix, I'm looking at their
combinations,
but that's just A times the
vector of c-s.
And these columns will be
independent if the null space of
A is the zero vector.
They are dependent if there's
something else in there.
If there's something else in
the null space,
if A times c gives the zero
vector for some non-zero vector
c in the null space.
Then they're dependent,
because that's telling me a
combination of the columns gives
the zero column.
I think you're with be,
because we've seen,
like, lecture after lecture,
we're looking at the
combinations of the columns and
asking, do we get zero or don't
we?
And now we're giving the
official name,
dependent if we do,
independent if we don't.
So I could express this in
other words now.
I could say the rank -- what's
the rank in this independent
case?
The rank r of the,
of the matrix,
in the case of independent
columns, is?
So the columns are independent.
So how many pivot columns have
I got.
All n.
All the columns would be pivot
columns, because free columns
are telling me that they're a
combination of earlier columns.
So this would be the case where
the rank is n.
This would be the case where
the rank is smaller than n.
So in this case the rank is n
and the null space of A is only
the zero vector.
And no free variables.
No free variables.
And this is the case yes free
variables.
If you'll allow me to stretch
the English language that far.
That's the case where we have,
a combination that gives the
zero column.
I'm often interested in the
case when my vectors are popped
into a matrix.
So the, the definition over
there of independence didn't
talk about any matrix.
The vectors didn't have to be
vectors in N dimensional space.
And I want to give you some
examples of vectors that aren't
what you think of immediately as
vectors.
But most of the time,
this is -- the vectors we think
of are columns.
And we can put them in a
matrix.
And then independence or
dependence comes back to the
null space.
OK.
So that's the idea of
independence.
Can I just, yeah,
let me go on to spanning a
space.
What does it mean for a bunch
of vectors to span a space?
Well, actually,
we've seen it already.
You remember,
if we had a columns in a
matrix, we took all their
combinations and that gave us
the column space.
Those vectors that we started
with span that column space.
So spanning a space means -- so
let me move that important stuff
right up.
OK.
So vectors -- let me call them,
say, V1 up to -- call you some
different letter,
say Vl -- span a space,
a subspace, or just a vector
space I could say,
span a space means,
means the space consists of all
combinations of those vectors.
That's exactly what we did with
the column space.
So now I could say in shorthand
the columns of a matrix span the
column space.
So you remember it's a bunch of
vectors that have this property
that they span a space,
and actually if I give you a
bunch of vectors and say --
OK, let S be the space that
they span, in other words let S
contain all their combinations,
that space S will be the
smallest space with those
vectors in it,
right?
Because any space with those
vectors in it must have all the
combinations of those vectors in
it.
And if I stop there,
then I've got the smallest
space, and that's the space that
they span.
OK.
So I'm just -- rather than,
needing to say,
take all linear combinations
and put them in a space,
I'm compressing that into the
word span.
Straightforward.
OK.
So if I think of a,
of the column space of a
matrix.
I've got their -- so I start
with the columns.
I take all their combinations.
That gives me the columns
space.
They span the column space.
Now are they independent?
Maybe yes, maybe no.
It depends on the particular
columns that went into that
matrix.
But obviously I'm highly
interested in a set of vectors
that spans a space and is
independent.
That's, that means like I've
got the right number of vectors.
If I didn't have all of them,
I wouldn't have my whole space.
If I had more than that,
they probably wouldn't --
they wouldn't be independent.
So, like, basis -- and that's
the word that's coming -- is
just right.
So here let me put what that
word means.
A basis for a vector space is,
is a, is a sequence of vectors
--
shall I call them V1,
V2, up to let me say Vd now,
I'll stop with that letters --
that has two properties.
I've got enough vectors and not
too many.
It's a natural idea of a basis.
So a basis is a bunch of
vectors in the space and it's a
so it's a sequence of vectors
with two properties,
with two properties.
One, they are independent.
And two -- you know what's
coming?
-- they span the space.
OK.
Let me take -- so time for
examples, of course.
So I'm asking you now to put
definition one,
the definition of independence,
together with definition two,
and let's look at examples,
because this is -- this
combination means the set I've
-- of vectors I have is just
right, and the -- so that this
idea of a basis will be central.
I'll always be asking you now
for a basis.
Whenever I look at a subspace,
if I ask you for -- if you give
me a basis for that subspace,
you've told me what it is.
You've told me everything I
need to know about that
subspace.
Those -- I take their
combinations and I know that I
need all the combinations.
OK.
Examples.
OK, so examples of a basis.
Let me start with two
dimensional space.
Suppose the space -- say
example.
The space is,
oh, let's make it R^3.
Real three dimensional space.
Give me one basis.
One basis is?
So I want some vectors,
because if I ask you for a
basis, I'm asking you for
vectors, a little list of
vectors.
And it should be just right.
So what would be a basis for
three dimensional space?
Well, the first basis that
comes to mind,
why don't we write that down.
The first basis that comes to
mind is this vector,
this vector,
and this vector.
OK.
That's one basis.
Not the only basis,
that's going to be my point.
But let's just see -- yes,
that's a basis.
Are, are those vectors
independent?
So that's the like the x,
y, z axes, so if those are not
independent, we're in trouble.
Certainly, they are.
Take a combination c1 of this
vector plus c2 of this vector
plus c3 of that vector and try
to make it give the zero vector.
What are the c-s?
If c1 of that plus c2 of that
plus c3 of that gives me 0 0 0,
then the c-s are all -- 0,
right.
So that's the test for
independence.
In the language of matrices,
which was under that board,
I could make those the columns
of a matrix.
Well, it would be the identity
matrix.
Then I would ask,
what's the null space of the
identity matrix?
And you would say it's only the
zero vector.
And I would say,
fine, then the columns are
independent.
The only thing -- the identity
times a vector giving zero,
the only vector that does that
is zero.
OK.
Now that's not the only basis.
Far from it.
Tell me another basis,
a second basis,
another basis.
So, give me -- well,
I'll just start it out.
One one two.
Two two five.
Suppose I stopped there.
Has that little bunch of
vectors got the properties that
I'm asking for in a basis for
R^3?
We're looking for a basis for
R^3.
Are they independent,
those two column vectors?
Yes.
Do they span R^3?
No.
Our feeling is no.
Our feeling is that there're
some vectors in R3 that are not
combinations of those.
OK.
So suppose I add in -- I need
another vector then,
because these two don't span
the space.
OK.
Now it would be foolish for me
to put in three three seven,
right, as the third vector.
That would be a goof.
Because that,
if I put in three three seven,
those vectors would be
dependent, right?
If I put in three three seven,
it would be the sum of those
two, it would lie in the same
plane as those.
It wouldn't be independent.
My attempt to create a basis
would be dead.
But if I take -- so what vector
can I take?
I can take any vector that's
not in that plane.
Let me try -- I hope that 3 3 8
would do it.
At least it's not the sum of
those two vectors.
But I believe that's a basis.
And what's the test then,
for that to be a basis?
Because I just picked those
numbers, and if I had picked,
5 7 -14 how would we know do we
have a basis or don't we?
You would put them in the
columns of a matrix,
and you would do elimination,
row reduction --
and you would see do you get
any free variables or are all
the columns pivot columns.
Well now actually we have a
square -- the matrix would be
three by three.
So, what's the test on the
matrix then?
The matrix -- so in this case,
when my space is R^3 and I have
three vectors,
my matrix is square and what I
asking about that matrix in
order for those columns to be a
basis?
So in this -- for R^n,
if I have -- n vectors give a
basis if the n by n matrix with
those columns,
with those columns,
is what?
What's the requirement on that
matrix?
Invertible, right,
right.
The matrix should be
invertible.
For a square matrix,
that's the, that's the perfect
answer.
Is invertible.
So that's when,
that's when the space is the
whole space R^n.
Let me, let me be sure you're
with me here.
Let me remove that.
Are those two vectors a basis
for any space at all?
Is there a vector space that
those really are a basis for,
those, that pair of vectors,
this guy and this 1,
1 1 2 and 2 2 5?
Is there a space for which
that's a basis?
Sure.
They're independent,
so they satisfy the first
requirement, so what space shall
I take for them to be a basis
of?
What spaces will they be a
basis for?
The one they span.
Their combinations.
It's a plane,
right?
It'll be a plane inside R^3.
So if I take this vector 1 1 2,
say it goes there,
and this vector 2 2 5,
those are a basis for --
because they span a plane.
And they're a basis for the
plane, because they're
independent.
If I stick in some third guy,
like 3 3 7, which is in the
plane -- suppose I put in,
try to put in 3 3 7,
then the three vectors would
still span the plane,
but they wouldn't be a basis
anymore because they're not
independent anymore.
OK.
So, we're looking at the
question of -- again,
the case with independent
columns is the case where the
column vectors span the column
space.
They're independent,
so they're a basis for the
column space.
OK.
So now there's one bit of
intuition.
Let me go back to all of R^n.
So I -- where I put 3 3 8.
OK.
The first message is that the
basis is not unique,
right.
There's zillions of bases.
I take any invertible three by
three matrix,
its columns are a basis for
R^3.
The column space is R^3,
and if those,
if that matrix is invertible,
those columns are independent,
I've got a basis for R^3.
So there're many,
many bases.
But there is something in
common for all those bases.
There's something that this
basis shares with that basis and
every other basis for R^3.
And what's that?
Well, you saw it coming,
because when I stopped here and
asked if that was a basis for
R^3, you said no.
And I know that you said no
because you knew there weren't
enough vectors there.
And the great fact is that
there're many,
many bases, but -- let me put
in somebody else,
just for variety.
There are many,
many bases, but they all have
the same number of vectors.
If we're talking about the
space R^3, then that number of
vectors is three.
If we're talking about the
space R^n, then that number of
vectors is n.
If we're talking about some
other space, the column space of
some matrix, or the null space
of some matrix,
or some other space that we
haven't even thought of,
then that still is true that
every basis -- that there're
lots of bases but every basis
has the same number of vectors.
Let me write that great fact
down.
Every basis -- we're given a
space.
Given a space.
R^3 or R^n or some other column
space of a matrix or the null
space of a matrix or some other
vector space.
Then the great fact is that
every basis for this,
for the space has the same
number of vectors.
If one basis has six vectors,
then every other basis has six
vectors.
So that number six is telling
me like it's telling me how big
is the space.
It's telling me how many
vectors do I have to have to
have a basis.
And of course we're seeing it
this way.
That number six,
if we had seven vectors,
then we've got too many.
If we have five vectors we
haven't got enough.
Sixes are like just right for
whatever space that is.
And what do we call that
number?
That number is -- now I'm ready
for the last definition today.
It's the dimension of that
space.
So every basis for a space has
the same number of vectors in
it.
Not the same vectors,
all sorts of bases --
but the same number of vectors
is always the same,
and that number is the
dimension.
This is definitional.
This number is the dimension of
the space.
OK.
Let's do some examples.
Because now we've got
definitions.
Let me repeat the four things,
the four words that have now
got defined.
Independence,
that looks at combinations not
being zero.
Spanning, that looks at all the
combinations.
Basis, that's the one that
combines independence and
spanning.
And now we've got the idea of
the dimension of a space.
It's the number of vectors in
any basis, because all bases
have the same number.
OK.
Let's take examples.
Suppose I take,
my space is -- examples now --
space is the,
say, the column space of this
matrix.
Let me write down a matrix.
1 1 1, 2 1 2,
and I'll -- just to make it
clear, I'll take the sum there,
3 2 3, and let me take the sum
of all -- oh,
let me put in one -- yeah,
I'll put in one one one again.
OK.
So that's four vectors.
OK, do they span the column
space of that matrix?
Let me repeat,
do they span the column space
of that matrix?
Yes.
By definition,
that's what the column space --
where it comes from.
Are they a basis for the column
space?
Are they independent?
No, they're not independent.
There's something in that null
space.
Maybe we can -- so let's look
at the null space of the matrix.
Tell me a vector that's in the
null space of that matrix.
So I'm looking for some vector
that combines those columns and
produces the zero column.
Or in other words,
I'm looking for solutions to A
X equals zero.
So tell me a vector in the null
space.
Maybe -- well,
this was, this column was that
one plus that one,
so maybe if I have one of those
and minus one of those that
would be a vector in the null
space.
So, you've already told me now,
are those vectors independent,
the answer is -- those column
vectors, the answer is -- no.
Right?
They're not independent.
Because -- you knew they
weren't independent.
Anyway, minus one of this minus
one of this plus one of this
zero of that is the zero vector.
OK.
OK, so they're not independent.
They span, but they're not
independent.
Tell me a basis for that column
space.
What's a basis for the column
space?
These are all the questions
that the homework asks,
the quizzes ask,
the final exam will ask.
Find a basis for the column
space of this matrix.
OK.
Now there's many answers,
but give me the most natural
answer.
Columns one and two.
That's the natural answer.
Those are the pivot columns,
because, I mean,
we s- we begin systematically.
We look at the first column,
it's OK.
We can put that in the basis.
We look at the second column,
it's OK.
We can put that in the basis.
The third column we can't put
in the basis.
The fourth column we can't,
again.
So the rank of the matrix is --
what's the rank of our matrix?
Two.
And, and now that rank is also
-- we also have another word.
We, we have a great theorem
here.
The rank of A,
that rank r,
is the number of pivot columns
and it's also -- well,
so now please use my new word.
This, it's the number two,
of course, two is the rank of
my matrix,
it's the number of pivot
columns, those pivot columns
form a basis,
of course, so what's two?
It's the dimension.
The rank of A,
the number of pivot columns,
is the dimension of the column
space.
Of course, you say.
It had to be.
Right.
But just watch,
look for one moment at the,
the language,
the way the English words get
involved here.
I take the rank of a matrix,
the rank of a matrix.
It's a number of columns and
it's the dimension of -- not the
dimension of the matrix,
that's what I want to say.
It's the dimension of a space,
a subspace, the column space.
Do you see, I don't take the
dimension of A.
That's not what I want.
I'm looking for the dimension
of the column space of A.
If you use those words right,
it shows you've got the idea
right.
Similarly here.
I don't talk about the rank of
a subspace.
It's a matrix that has a rank.
I talk about the rank of a
matrix.
And the beauty is that these
definitions just merge so that
the rank of a matrix is the
dimension of its column space.
And in this example it's two.
And then the further question
is, what's a basis?
And the first two columns are a
basis.
Tell me another basis.
Another basis for the columns
space.
You see I just keep hammering
away.
I apologize,
but it's, I have to be sure you
have the idea of basis.
Tell me another basis for the
column space.
Well, you could take columns
one and three.
That would be a basis for the
column space.
Or columns two and three would
be a basis.
Or columns two and four.
Or tell me another basis that's
not made out of those columns at
all?
So -- I guess I'm giving you
infinitely many possibilities,
so I can't expect a unanimous
answer here.
I'll tell you -- but let's look
at another basis,
though.
I'll just -- because it's only
one out of zillions,
I'm going to put it down and
I'm going to erase it.
Another basis for the column
space would be -- let's see.
I'll put in some things that
are not there.
Say, oh well,
just to make it -- my life
easy, 2 2 2.
That's in the column space.
And, that was sort of obvious.
Let me take the sum of those,
say 6 4 6.
Or the sum of all of the
columns, 7 5 7,
why not.
That's in the column space.
Those are independent and I've
got the number right,
I've got two.
Actually, this is a key point.
If you know the dimension of
the space you're working with,
and we know that this column --
we know that the dimension,
DIM, the dimension of the
column space is two.
If you know the dimension,
then -- and we have a couple of
vectors that are independent,
they'll automatically be a
basis.
If we've got the number of
vectors right,
two vectors in this case,
then if they're independent,
they can't help but span the
space.
Because if they didn't span the
space, there'd be a third guy to
help span the space,
but it couldn't be independent.
So, it just has to be
independent if we've got the
numbers right.
And they span.
OK.
Very good.
So you got the dimension of a
space.
So this was another basis that
I just invented.
OK.
Now, now I get to ask about the
null space.
What's the dimension of the
null space?
So we, we got a great fact
there, the dimension of the
column space is the rank.
Now I want to ask you about the
null space.
That's the other part of the
lecture, and it'll go on to the
next lecture.
OK.
So we know the dimension of the
column space is two,
the rank.
What about the null space?
This is a vector in the null
space.
Are there other vectors in the
null space?
Yes or no?
Yes.
So this isn't a basis because
it's doesn't span,
right?
There's more in the null space
than we've got so far.
I need another vector at least.
So tell me another vector in
the null space.
Well, the natural choice,
the choice you naturally think
of is I'm going on to the fourth
column, I'm letting that free
variable be a one,
and that free variable be a
zero, and I'm asking is that
fourth column a combination of
my pivot columns?
Yes, it is.
And it's -- that will do.
So what I've written there are
actually the two special
solutions, right?
I took the two free variables,
free and free.
I gave them the values 1 0 or 0
I figured out the rest.
So do you see,
let me just say it in words.
This vector,
these vectors in the null space
are telling me,
they're telling me the
combinations of the columns that
give zero.
They're telling me in what way
the, the columns are dependent.
That's what the null space is
doing.
Have I got enough now?
And what's the null space now?
We have to think about the null
space.
These are two vectors in the
null space.
They're independent.
Are they a basis for the null
space?
What's the dimension of the
null space?
You see that those questions
just keep coming up all the
time.
Are they a basis for the null
space?
You can tell me the answer even
though we haven't written out a
proof of that.
Can you?
Yes or no?
Do these two special solutions
form a basis for the null space?
In other words,
does the null space consist of
all combinations of those two
guys?
Yes or no?
Yes.
The null space is two
dimensional.
The null space,
the dimension of the null
space, is the number of free
variables.
So the dimension of the null
space is the number of free
variables.
And at the last second,
give me the formula.
This is then the key formula
that we know.
How many free variables are
there in terms of R,
the rank, m --
the number of rows,
n, the number of columns?
What do we get?
We have n columns,
r of them are pivot columns,
so n-r is the number of free
columns, free variables.
And now it's the dimension of
the null space.
OK.
That's great.
That's the key spaces,
their bases,
and their dimensions.
Thanks.