-- and lift-off on differential
equations.
So, this section is about how
to solve a system of first
order, first derivative,
constant coefficient linear
equations.
And if we do it right,
it turns directly into linear
algebra.
The key idea is the solutions
to constant coefficient linear
equations are exponentials.
So if you look for an
exponential, then all you have
to find is what's up there in
the exponent and what multiplies
the exponential and that's the
linear algebra.
So -- and the result -- one
thing we will fine --
it's completely parallel to
powers of a matrix.
So the last lecture was about
how would you compute A to the K
or A to the 100?
How do you compute high powers
of a matrix?
Now it's not powers anymore,
but it's exponentials.
That's the natural thing for
differential equation.
Okay.
But can I begin with an
example?
And I'll just go through the
mechanics.
How would I solve the
differential -- two differential
equations?
So I'm going to make it -- I'll
have a two by two matrix and the
coefficients are minus one two,
one minus two and I'd better
give you some initial condition.
So suppose it starts u at times
zero -- this is u1,
u2 -- let it -- let it --
suppose everything is in u1 at
times zero.
So -- at -- at the start,
it's all in u1.
But what happens as time goes
on,
du2/dt will -- will be
positive, because of that u1
term, so flow will move into the
u2 component and it will go out
of the u1 component.
So we'll just follow that
movement as time goes forward by
looking at the eigenvalues and
eigenvectors of that matrix.
That's a first job.
Before you do anything else,
find the -- find the matrix and
its eigenvalues and
eigenvectors.
So let me do that.
Okay.
So here's our matrix.
Maybe you can tell me right
away what -- what are the
eigenvalues and -- eigenvalues
anyway.
And then we can check.
But can you spot any of the
eigenvalues of that matrix?
We're looking for two
eigenvalues.
Do you see -- I mean,
if I just wrote that matrix
down, what -- what do you notice
about it?
It's singular,
right.
That -- that's a singular
matrix.
That tells me right away that
one of the eigenvalues is lambda
equals zero.
I can -- that's a singular
matrix, the second column is
minus two times the first
column, the determinant is zero,
it's -- it's singular,
so zero is an eigenvalue and
the other eigenvalue will
be -- from the trace.
I look at the trace,
the sum down the diagonal is
minus three.
That has to agree with the sum
of the eigenvalue,
so that second eigenvalue
better be minus three.
I could, of course -- I could
compute -- why don't I over
here -- compute the determinant
of A minus lambda I,
the determinant of this minus
one minus lambda two one minus
two minus lambda matrix.
But we know what's coming.
When I do that multiplication,
I get a lambda squared.
I get a two lambda and a one
lambda,
that's a three lambda.
And then -- now I'm going to
get the determinant,
which is two minus two which is
zero.
So there's my characteristic
polynomial, this determinant.
And of course I factor that
into lambda times lambda plus
three and I get the two
eigenvalues
that we saw coming.
What else do I need?
The eigenvectors.
So before I even think about
the differential equation or
what -- how to solve it,
let me find the eigenvectors
for this matrix.
Okay.
So take lambda equals zero --
so that -- that's the first
eigenvalue.
Lambda one equals zero and the
second eigenvalue will be lambda
two equals minus three.
By the way, I -- I already know
something important about this.
The eigenvalues are telling me
something.
You'll see how it comes out,
but let me point to -- these
numbers are -- this eigenvalue,
a negative eigenvalue,
is going to disappear.
There's going to be an e to the
minus three t in the answer.
That e to the minus three t as
times goes on is going to be
very, very small.
The other part of the answer
will
involve an e to the zero t.
But e to the zero t is one and
that's a constant.
So I'm expecting that this
solution'll have two parts,
an e to the zero t part and an
e to the minus three t part,
and that -- and as time goes
on, the second part'll disappear
and the
first part will be a steady
state.
It won't move.
It will be -- at the end of --
as t approaches infinity,
this part disappears and this
is the -- the e to the zero t
part is what I get.
And I'm very interested in
these steady states,
so that's -- I get a steady
state when I have a zero
eigenvalue.
Okay.
What about those eigenvectors?
So what's the eigenvector that
goes with eigenvalue zero?
Okay.
The matrix is singular as it
is, the eigenvector is -- is the
guy in the null space,
so what vector is in the null
space
of that matrix?
Let's see.
I guess I probably give the
free variable the value one and
I realize that if I want to get
zero I need a two up here.
Okay?
So Ax1 is zero x1.
A x1 is zero x1.
Fine.
Okay.
What about the other
eigenvalue?
Lambda two is minus three.
Okay.
How do I get the other
eigenvalue, then?
For the moment -- can I
mentally do it?
I subtract minus three along
the diagonal,
which means I add three -- can
I -- I'll just do it with an
erase -- erase for the moment.
So I'm going to add three
to the diagonal.
So this minus one will become a
two and -- I'll make it in big
loopy letters -- and when I add
three to this guy,
the minus two becomes -- well,
I can't make one very loopy,
but how's that?
Okay.
Now that's A minus three I -- A
plus three I,
sorry.
That's A plus three I.
It's supposed to be singular,
right?
I-- if things -- if I did it
right, this matrix should be
singular and the x2,
the eigenvector should be in
its null space.
Okay.
What do I get for
the null space of this?
Maybe minus one one,
or one minus one.
Doesn't matter.
Those are both perfectly good.
Right?
Because that's in the null
space of this.
Now I'll -- because A times
that vector is three times that
vector.
Ax2 is minus three
x2.
Good.
Okay.
Can I get A again so we see
that correctly?
That was a minus one and that
was a minus two.
Good.
Okay.
That -- that's the first job.
eigenvalues and eigenvectors.
And already the eigenvalues are
telling me the most important
information about the answer.
But now, what is the answer?
The answer is -- the solution
will be U of T -- okay.
Now, wh- now I use those
eigenvalues and eigenvectors.
The solution is some -- there
are two eigenvalues.
So I -- it -- so there're going
to be two special
solutions here.
Two pure exponential solutions.
The first one is going to be
either the lambda one tx1 and
the -- so that solves the
equation, and so does this one.
They both are solutions to the
differential equation.
That's the general solution.
The general solution is a
combination of that pure
exponential solution and that
pure exponential solution.
Can I just see that those guys
do solve the equation?
So let me just check -- check
on this one, for example.
Check.
I -- I want to check that the
-- my equation -- let's
remember,
the equation -- du/dt is Au.
I plug in e to the lambda one t
x1 and let's just see that the
equation's okay.
I believe this is a solution to
that equation.
So just plug it in.
On the left-hand side,
I take the time derivative --
so the left-hand side will be
lambda
one, e to the lambda one t x1,
right?
The time derivative -- this is
the term that depends on time,
it's just ordinary exponential,
its derivative brings down a
lambda one.
On the other side of the
equation it's A times this
thing.
A times either the lambda one t
x
one, and does that check out?
Do we have equality there?
Yes, because either the lambda
one t appears on both sides and
the other one is Ax1 equal
lambda one x1 -- check.
Do you -- so,
the -- we've come to the first
point to remember.
These pure solutions.
Those pure solutions are the --
those pure exponentials are the
differential equations analogue
of -- last time we had pure
powers.
Last time -- so -- so last
time, the analog was lambda --
lambda one to the K-th power x1,
some amount of that,
plus some amount of lambda two
to
the K-th power x2.
That was our formula from last
time.
I put it up just to -- so your
eye compares those two formulas.
Powers of lambda in the -- in
the difference equation -- that
-- this was in the -- this was
for the equation uk plus one
equals A uk.
That was for the finite step --
stepping by one.
And we got powers,
now this is the one we're
interested in,
the exponentials.
So -- so that's -- that's the
solution -- what are c1 and c2?
Then we're through.
What are c1 and c2?
Well, of course we know these
actual things.
Let me just -- let me come back
to this.
c1 is -- we haven't figured out
yet, but e to the lambda one t,
the lambda one is zero so
that's just a one times x1 which
is two one.
So it's c1 times this one
that's not moving times the
vector, the eigenvector two one
and c2 times -- what's e to the
lambda two t?
Lambda two is minus three.
So this is the term that has
the minus three t and its
eigenvector is this one minus
one.
So this vector solves the
equation
and any multiple of it.
This vector solves the equation
if it's got that factor e to the
minus three t.
We've got the answer except for
c1 and c2.
So -- so everything I've done
is immediate as soon as you know
the eigenvalues and
eigenvectors.
So how do we get c1 and c2?
That has to come from the
initial condition.
So now I -- now I use -- u of
zero is given as one zero.
So this is the initial
condition that will find c1 and
c2.
So let me do that on the board
underneath.
At t equals zero,
then -- I get c1 times this guy
plus c2 and now I'm at times
zero.
So that's a one and this is a
one minus one and that's
supposed to agree with u of zero
one zero.
Okay.
That should be two equations.
That should give me c1 and c2
and then I'm through.
So what are c1 and
c2?
Let's see.
I guess we could actually spot
them by eye or we could solve
two equations in two unknowns.
Let's see.
If these were both ones -- so
I'm just adding -- then I would
get three zero.
So what's the -- what's the
solution, then?
If -- if c1 and c2 are both
ones, I get three zero,
so I want, like,
one third of that,
because I want to get one zero.
So I think it's c1 equals a
third, c2 equals a third.
So finally I have the answer.
Let me keep it in the -- in
this board here.
Finally the answer is one third
of
this plus one third of this.
Do you see what -- what's
actually happening with this
flow?
This flow started out at -- the
solution started out at one
zero.
Started at one zero.
Then as time went on,
people moved,
essentially.
Some fraction of this
one moved here.
And -- and in the limit,
there's -- there's the limit,
as -- right?
As t goes to infinity,
as t gets very large,
this disappears and this is the
steady state.
So the steady state is -- so
the steady state -- u --
we could call it u at infinity
is one third of two and one.
It's -- it's two thirds of one
third.
So that's the -- we really -- I
mean, you're getting,
like, total,
insight into the behavior of
the solution,
what the differential
equation does.
Of course, we don't -- wouldn't
always have a steady state.
Sometimes we would approach
zero.
Sometimes we would blow up.
Can we straighten out those
cases?
The eigenvalue should tell us.
So when do we get -- so -- so
let me ask first,
when do we get stability?
That's u of t going to zero.
When would the solution go to
zero no matter what the initial
condition is?
Negative eigenvalues,
right.
Negative eigenvalues.
But now I have to -- I have to
ask you for one more step.
Suppose the eigenvalues are
complex numbers?
Because we know they could be.
Then we want stability -- this
-- this -- we want -- we need
all these e to the lambda t-s
all going to zero and somehow
that asks us to have lambda
negative.
But suppose lambda is a complex
number?
Then what's the test?
What -- if lambda's a complex
number like, oh,
suppose lambda is negative plus
an imaginary part?
Say lambda is minus three plus
six i?
What -- what happens then?
Can we just,
like, do a -- a case here?
If -- if this lambda is minus
three plus six it,
how big is that number?
Does this -- does this
imaginary part play a -- play a
-- play a role here or not?
Or how big is -- what's the
absolute value of that -- of
that quantity?
It's just e to the minus
three t, right?
Because this other part,
this -- the -- the magnitude --
the -- this -- e to the six it
-- what -- that has absolute
value one.
Right?
That's just this cosine of six
t plus i, sine of six t.
And the absolute value squared
will be cos squared plus sine
squared will be one.
This is -- this complex number
is running around the unit
circle.
This com- this -- the -- it's
the real part that matters.
This is what I'm trying to do.
Real part of lambda has to be
negative.
If lambda's a complex number,
it's the real part,
the minus three,
that either makes us go to zero
or doesn't, or let -- or blows
up.
The imaginary part won't --
will just, like,
oscillate between the two
components.
Okay.
So that's stability.
And what about -- what about a
steady state?
When would we have,
a steady state,
always in the same direction?
So let me -- I'll take this
part away -- when -- so that
was, like, checking that it's --
that it's the real part that we
care about.
Now, we have a steady state
when -- when lambda one is zero
and
the other eigenvalues have
what?
So I'm looking -- like,
that example was,
like, perfect for a steady
state.
We have a zero eigenvalue and
the other eigenvalues,
we want those to disappear.
So the other eigenvalues have
real part negative.
And we blow up,
for sure -- we blow up if any
real part of lambda is positive.
So if I -- if I reverse the
sign of A -- of the matrix A --
suppose instead of the matrix I
had, the A that I had,
I changed it -- I changed all
its sines.
What would that do to the
eigenvalues and eigenvectors?
If I -- if --
if I know the eigenvalues and
eigenvectors of A,
tell me about minus A.
What happens to the
eigenvalues?
For minus A,
they'll all change sine.
So I'll have blow up.
This -- instead of the e to the
minus three t,
if I change that to minus --
if I change the sines in that
matrix, I would change the trace
to plus three,
I would have an e to the plus
three t and I would have blow
up.
Of course the zero eigenvalue
would stay at zero,
but the other guy is taking off
in -- if I reversed all the
sines.
Okay.
So this is --
this is the stability picture.
And for a two by two matrix,
we can actually pin down even
more closely what that means.
Can I -- let -- can I do that?
Let me do that -- I want to --
for a two by two matrix,
I can tell whether the real
part of the eigenvalues is
negative,
I -- well, let me -- let me
tell you what I have in mind for
that.
So two by two stability -- let
me -- this is just a little
comment.
Two by two stability.
So my matrix,
now, is just a b c d and I'm
looking for the real parts of
both eigenvalues to be negative.
Okay.
What -- how can I tell from
looking at the matrix,
without computing its
eigenvalues, whether the two
eigenvalues are negative,
or at least their real parts
are negative?
What would that tell me about
the trace?
So -- so the trace --
that's this a plus d -- what
can you tell me about the trace
in the case of a two by two
stable matrix?
That means the eigenvalues have
-- are negative,
or at least the real parts of
those eigenvalues are negative
-- then, when I take the -- when
I
look at the matrix and find its
trace, what -- what do I know
about that?
It's negative,
right.
This is the sum of the -- this
equals -- this equals lambda one
plus lambda two,
so it's negative.
The two eigenvalues,
by the way, will have --
if they're complex -- will have
plus six i and minus six i.
The complex parts will -- will
be conjugates of each other and
disappear when we add and the
trace will be negative.
Okay, the trace has to be
negative.
Is that enough -- is a negative
trace enough to make the matrix
stable?
Shouldn't be enough,
right?
Can I -- can you make -- what's
a matrix that has a negative
trace but still it's not stable?
So it -- it has a blow -- it
still has a blow-up factor and a
-- and a -- and a decaying one.
So what would be a -- so just
-- just to see -- maybe I just
put that here.
This -- now I'm looking for an
example where the trace could be
negative but still blow up.
Of course -- yeah,
let's just take one.
Oh, look, let me -- let me make
it minus two zero zero one.
Okay.
There's a case where that
matrix has
negative trace -- I know its
eigenvalues of course.
They're minus two and one and
it blows up.
It's got -- it's got a plus one
eigenvalue here,
so there would be an e to the
plus t in the solution and it'll
blow up if it has any second
component at all.
I need another condition.
And it's a condition on the
determinant.
And what's that condition?
If I know that the two
eigenvalues -- suppose I know
they're negative,
both negative.
What does that tell me about
the determinant?
Let me ask again.
If I know both the eigenvalues
are negative,
then I know the trace is
negative but the determinant is
positive, because it's the
product of the two eigenvalues.
So this determinant is lambda
one times lambda two.
This is -- this is lambda one
times lambda two and if they're
both negative,
the product is positive.
So positive determinant,
negative trace.
I can easily track down the --
this condition also for the --
if -- if there's an imaginary
part hanging around.
Okay.
So that's a -- like a small but
quite useful,
because two by two is always
important -- comment on
stability.
Okay.
So let's just look at the
picture again.
Okay.
The main part of my lecture,
the one thing you want to be
able to, like,
just do automatically is this
step of solving the system.
Find the eigenvalues,
find the eigenvectors,
find the coefficients.
And notice --
what's the matrix -- in this
linear system here,
I can't help -- if I -- if I
have equations like that --
that's my equations column at a
time -- what's the matrix form
of that equation?
So -- so this -- this system of
equations is --
is some matrix multiplying c1,
c2 to give u of zero.
One zero.
What's the matrix?
Well, it's obviously two one,
one minus one,
but we have a name,
or at least a letter --
actually a name for that matrix.
Wh- what matrix are we s- are
we -- are we dealing with here
in this
step of finding the c-s?
Its letter is S -- it's the
eigenvector matrix.
Of course.
These are the eigenvectors,
there in the columns of our
matrix.
So this is S c equals u of zero
-- is the -- that step where you
find the actual coefficients,
you find out how much of each
pure
exponential is in the solution.
By getting it right at the
start, then it stays right
forever.
I -- you're seeing this picture
that each -- each pure
exponential goes on its own way
once you start it from u of
zero.
So you start it by figuring out
how much each one is present in
u of
zero and then off they go.
Okay.
So -- so that's a system of two
equations in two unknowns
coupled -- the matrix sort of
couples u1 and u2 and the
eigenvalues and eigenvectors
uncouple it, diagonalize it.
Actually --
okay, now can I -- can I think
in terms of S and lambda?
So I want to write the solution
down, again in terms of S and
lambda.
Okay.
I'll do that on this far board.
So I'm coming back to -- I'm
coming back to our equation
du/dt equals Au.
Now this matrix A couples them.
The whole point of eigenvectors
is to uncouple.
So one way to see that is
introduce set u equal A -- not
A.
It's S, the eigenvector matrix
that uncouples it.
So I'm -- I'm taking this
equation as I'm given,
coupled with -- with A has --
is probably full of
non-zeroes, but I'm -- by
uncoupling it,
I mean I'm diagonalizing it.
If I can get a diagonal matrix,
I'm -- I'm in.
Okay.
So I plug that in.
This is A S v.
And this is S dv/dt.
S is a constant.
It's -- this it the eigenvector
matrix.
This is the eigenvector matrix.
Okay.
Now I'm going to bring S
inverse over here.
And what have I got?
That combination S inverse A S
is lambda, the diagonal matrix.
That's -- that's the point,
that in -- if I'm using the
eigenvectors as my basis,
then my system of equations is
just diagonal.
I -- each -- there's no
coupling anymore -- dv1/dt is
lambda one v1.
So let's just write that down.
dv1/ dt is lambda one v1 and so
on for all n of the equations.
It's a system of equations but
they're not connected,
so they're easy to solve and
why don't I just write down the
solution?
v -- well, v is now some e to
the lambda one t -- well,
okay -- I guess my idea here
now is to use,
the natural notation --
v of T is e to the lambda tv of
zero.
And u of t will be Se to the
lambda t S inverse,
u of zero.
This is the -- this is the,
formula I'm headed for.
This -- this matrix,
S e to the lambda t S inverse,
that's my exponential.
That's my e to the A t,
is this S e to the lambda t S
inverse.
So my -- my job really now is
to explain what's going on with
this matrix up in the
exponential.
What does that mean?
What does it mean to say e to a
matrix?
This ought to be easier because
this
is e to a diagonal matrix,
but still it's a matrix.
What do we mean by e to the A
t?
Because really e to the A t is
my answer here.
My -- my answer to this
equation is -- this u of t,
this is my -- this is my e to
the A t u of zero.
So it's -- my job is really now
to
say what's -- what does that
mean?
What's the exponential of a
matrix and why is that formula
correct?
Okay.
So I'll put that on the board
underneath.
What's the exponential of a
matrix?
Let me come back here.
So I'm talking about matrix
exponentials.
e to the At.
Okay.
How are we going to define
the exponential of a -- of
something?
The trick -- the idea is -- the
thing to go back to is
exponential -- there's a power
series for exponentials.
That's how you -- you -- the
good way to define e to
the x is the power series one
plus x plus one half x squared,
one six x cubed and we'll do it
now when the -- when we have a
matrix.
So the one becomes the
identity, the x is At,
the x squared is At squared and
I divide by two.
The cube, the x cube is At
cubed over six,
and what's the
general term in here?
At to the n-th power divided by
-- and it goes on.
But what do I divide by?
So, you see the pattern -- here
I divided by one,
here I divided by one by two by
six, those are the factorials.
It's n factorial.
That was, like,
the one beautiful
Taylor series.
The one beautiful Taylor series
-- well, there are two -- there
are two beautiful Taylor series
in this world.
The Taylor series for e to the
x is the s with x to the n-th
over n factorial.
And all I'm doing is doing the
same thing for matrixes.
The other beautiful Taylor
series is just the sum of x to
the n-th not divided by n
factorial.
Can you -- do you know what
function that one is?
So if I take -- this is the
series, all these sums are going
from zero to infinity.
What's -- what function have I
got --
this is like a side comment --
this is one plus x plus x
squared plus x cubed plus x to
the fourth not divided by
anything, what's -- what's that
function?
One plus x plus x squared plus
x cubed plus x fourth forever is
one over one minus x.
It's the geometric series,
the nicest power series of all.
So, actually,
of course, there would be a
similar thing here.
If -- if I wanted,
I minus A t inverse would be --
now I've got matrixes.
I've got matrixes everywhere,
but it's just like that series
with -- and just like this one
without the divisions.
It's I plus At plus At squared
plus At cubed and forever.
So that's actually a -- a
reasonable way to find the
inverse of a matrix.
If I chop it off -- well,
it's reasonable if t is small.
If t is a small number,
then -- then t squared is
extremely small,
t cubed is even smaller,
so approximately that inverse
is I plus At.
I can keep more terms if I
like.
Do you see what I'm doing?
I'm just saying we can do the
same thing for matrixes that we
do for ordinary functions and
the good thing about the
exponential series -- so in a
way, this series is better than
this one.
Why?
Because this one always
converges.
I'm dividing by these bigger
and bigger numbers,
so whatever matrix A and
however large t is,
that series -- these terms go
to zero.
The series adds up to a finite
sum,
e to the At is a -- is -- is
completely defined.
Whereas this second guy could
fail, right?
If At is big -- somehow if At
has an eigenvalue larger than
one, then when I square it it'll
have that eigenvalue squared,
when I cube it the
eigenvalue will be cubed --
that series will blow up unless
the eigenvalues of At are
smaller than one.
So when the eigenvalues of At
are smaller than one -- so I'd
better put that in.
The -- all eigenvalues of At
below one -- then that series
converges and gives
me the inverse.
Okay.
So this is the guy I'm chiefly
interested in,
and I wanted to connect it to
-- oh, okay.
What's -- how do I -- how do I
get -- this is my,
like, main thing now to do --
how do I get e to the At --
how do I see that e to the At
is the same as this?
In other words,
I can find e to the At by
finding S and lambda,
because now e to the lambda t
is easy.
Lambda's a diagonal matrix and
we can write down either the
lambda t -- and will right -- in
a minute.
But how --
do you see what -- do you see
that we're hoping for a -- we're
hoping that we can compute
either the A T from S and lambda
-- and I have to look at that
definition and say,
okay, how do -- how do I get an
S and the lambda to come out of
that?
Okay, can -- do you see how I
-- I want to connect that to
that, from that definition.
So let me erase this -- the
geometric series,
which isn't part of the
differential equations case and
get the S and the lambda into
this picture.
Oh, okay.
Here we go.
So identity is fine.
Now -- all right,
you -- you -- you'll see how
I'm -- how I'm -- how I going to
get A replaced by S and S is in
lambda's?
Well I use the fundamental
formula of this whole chapter.
A is S lambda S inverse and
then times t.
That's At.
Okay.
What's A squared t?
I can -- I've got the divide by
two, I've got the t squared and
I've got an A squared.
All right, I -- so I've got a
-- there's A -- there's A.
Now square it.
So what happens when I square
it?
We've seen that before.
When I square it,
I get S lambda squared S
inverse, right?
When I square that thing,
the -- there's an S and a -- an
S cancels out an S inverse.
I'm left with the S on the
left, the S inverse on the right
and lambda squared in the
middle.
And so on.
The next one'll be S lambda
cubed, S inverse -- times t
cubed over three factorial.
And now -- what do I do now?
I want to pull an S out from
everything.
I want an S out of the whole
thing.
Well, look, I'd better write
the identity how?
I -- I want to be able to pull
an S
out and an S inverse out from
the other side,
so I just write the identity as
S times S inverse.
So I have an S there and an S
inverse from this side and what
have I got in the middle?
If I pull out an S and an S
inverse, what have I got in the
middle?
I've got the identity,
a lambda t, a lambda squared t
squared over two -- I've got e
to the lambda t.
That's what's in the middle.
That's my formula for e to the
At.
Oh, now I have to ask you.
Does this formula always work?
This formula always works --
well, except it's an infinite
series.
But what do I mean by always
work?
And this one doesn't always
work and I just have to remind
you of what assumption is built
into this formula that's not
built into the original.
The assumption that A can be
diagonalized.
You'll remember that there are
some small -- sm- some subset of
matrixes that don't have n
independent eigenvectors,
so we don't have an S inverse
for those matrixes and the whole
diagonalization breaks down.
We could still make it
triangular.
I'll tell you about that.
But diagonal we can't do for
those particular degenerate
matrixes that don't have enough
independent eigenvectors.
But otherwise,
this is golden.
Okay.
So that's the formula -- that's
the matrix exponential.
Now it just remains for me to
say what is e to the lambda t?
Can I just do that?
Let me just put that in the
corner here.
What is the exponential of a
diagonal matrix?
Remember lambda is diagonal,
lambda one down to lambda n.
What's the exponential of that
diagonal matrix?
Because our whole point is that
this ought to be simple.
Our whole point is that to take
the exponential of a diagonal
matrix ought to be completely
decoupled --
it ought to be diagonal,
in other words,
and it is.
It's just e to the lambda one
t, e to the lambda two t,
e to the lambda n t,
all zeroes.
So -- so if we have a diagonal
matrix and I plug it into this
exponential formula,
everything's diagonal and the
diagonal terms are just the
ordinary
scaler exponentials e to the
lambda one t.
Okay, so that's -- that's -- in
a sense, I'm doing here,
on this board,
with -- with,
like, formulas what I did on
the -- in the first half of the
lecture with specific matrix A
and specific
eigenvalues and eigenvectors.
The -- so let me show you the
formulas again.
But the -- so you -- I guess --
what should you know from this
lecture?
You should know what this
matrix exponential is and,
like, when does it go to zero?
Tell me again,
now,
the answer to that.
When does e to the At approach
-- get smaller and smaller as t
increases?
Well, the S and the S inverse
aren't moving.
It's this one that has to get
smaller and smaller and that one
has this simple diagonal form.
And it goes to zero provided
every
one of these lambdas -- I -- I
need to have each one of these
guys go to zero,
so I need every real part of
every eigenvalue negative.
Right?
If the real part is negative,
that's -- that takes the
exponential -- that forces --
the exponential goes to zero.
Okay, so that -- that's
really the difference.
If I can just draw the --
here's a picture of the -- of
the -- this is the complex
plain.
Here's the real axis and here's
the imaginary axis.
And where do the eigenvalues
have to be for stability in
differential equations?
They have to be over here,
in the left half plain.
So the left half plain is this
plain, real part of lambda,
less than zero.
Where do the ma- where do the
eigenvalues have to be for
powers of the matrix to go to
zero?
Powers of the matrix go to zero
if the eigenvalues are in here.
So this is the stability region
for powers -- this is the region
--
absolute value of lambda,
less than one.
That's the stability for --
that tells us that the powers of
A go to zero,
this tells us that the
exponential of A goes to zero.
Okay.
One final example.
Let me just write down how to
deal with a final example.
Let's see.
So my final example will be a
single equation,
u''+bu'+Ku=0.
One equation,
second order.
How do I -- and maybe I should
have used -- I'll use -- I
prefer to use y here,
because that's what you see in
differential equations.
And I want u to be a vector.
So how do I change one second
order equation into a two by two
first order system?
Just the way I did for
Fibonacci.
I'll let u be y prime and y.
What I'm going to do is I'm
going to add an extra equation,
y prime equals y prime.
So I take this -- so by -- so
using this as the vector
unknown, now my equation is u
prime.
My first order system is u
prime, that'll be y double prime
y prime, the derivative of u,
okay, now the differential
equation is telling me that y
double prime is m- so I'm just
looking for -- what's this
matrix?
y prime y.
I'm looking for the matrix A.
What's the matrix in case I
have a single first order
equation and I want to make it
into a two by two system?
Okay, simple.
The first row of the matrix is
given by the equation.
So y''-by'-ky
-- no problem.
And what's the second row on
the matrix?
Then we're done.
The second row of the matrix I
want just to be the trivial
equation y prime equals y prime,
so I need a one and a zero
there.
So matrixes like these,
the gen- the general case,
if I had a five by five --
if I had a fifth order equation
and I wanted a five by five
matrix, I would see the
coefficients of the equation up
there and then my four trivial
equations would put ones here.
This is the kind of matrix that
goes from a fifth order to a
five by five first order.
So the -- and the eigenvalues
will
come out in a natural way
connected to the differential
equation.
Okay, that's differential
equations.
The -- a parallel lecture
compared to powers of a matrix
we can now do exponentials.
Thanks.