OK.
So, coming nearer the end of
the course, this lecture will be
a mixture of the linear algebra
that comes with a change of
basis.
And a change of basis from one
basis to another basis is
something you really do in
applications.
And, I would like to talk about
those applications.
I got a little bit involved
with compression.
Compressing a signal,
compressing an image.
And that's exactly
change-of-basis.
And then, the main theme in
this chapter is th- the
connection between a linear
transformation,
which doesn't have to have
coordinates, and the matrix that
tells us that transformation
with respect to coordinates.
So the matrix is the
coordinate-based description of
the linear transformation.
Let me start out with the nice
part, which is just to tell you
something about image
compression.
Those of you -- well,
everybody's going to meet
compression, because you know
that the amount of data that
we're getting -- well,
these lectures are compressed.
So that, actually,
probably you see my motion as
jerky?
Shall I use that word?
Have you looked on the web?
I should like to find a better
word.
Compressed, let's say.
So the complete signal is,
of course, in those video
cameras, and in the videotape,
but that goes to the bottom of
building nine,
and out of that comes a jumpy
motion because it uses a
standard system for compressing
images.
And, you'll notice that the
stuff that sits on the board
comes very clearly,
but it's my motion that needs a
whole lot of bits,
right?
So, and if I were to run up and
back up there and back,
that would need too many bits,
and I'd be compressed even
more.
So, what does compression mean?
Let me just think of a still
image.
And of course,
satellites, and computations of
the climate, computations of
combustion, the computers and
sensors of all kinds are just
giving us overwhelming amounts
of data.
The Web is, too.
Now, some compression can be
done with no loss.
Lossless compression is
possible just using,
sort of, the fact that there
are redundancies.
But I'm talking here about
lossy compression.
So I'm talking about -- here's
an image.
And what does an image consist
of?
It consists of a lot of little
pixels, right?
Maybe five hundred and twelve
by five hundred and twelve.
Two to the ninth by two to the
ninth pixels,
and so this is pixel number
one, one, so that's a pixel.
And if we're in black and
white, the typical pixel would
tell us a gray-scale,
from zero to two fifty five.
So a pixel is usually a value
of one of the xi,
so this would be the i-th
pixel, is -- it's usually a real
number on a scale from zero to
two fifty five.
In other words,
two to the eighth
possibilities.
So usually, that's the
standard, so that's eight --
eight bits.
But then we have that for every
pixel, so we have five hundred
and twelve squared pixels,
we're really operating x is a
vector in R^n,
but what is n?
n is five hundred and twelve
squared.
That's our problem,
right there.
A pixel is a vector that gives
us the information about the
image.
I'm sorry.
The image that comes through is
a vector of that length that --
that's the information that we
have about the image,
if it's a color image,
we would have three times that
length, because we'd need three
coordinates to get color.
So it would be three times five
hundred and twelve squared.
It's an enormous amount of
information, and we couldn't
send out the image for these
lectures without compressing it.
It would overload the system.
So it has to be compressed.
The standard compression,
and still used with lectures
is, called JPEG.
I think that stands for Joint
Photographic Experts Group.
They established a system of
compression.
And I just want to tell you
what it's about.
It's a change-of-basis.
What basis do we have?
The current basis we have is,
you could say,
the standard basis is,
every pixel,
give a value.
So that's like we have a vector
x which is five hundred and
twelve squared long and,
in the i-th position,
we get a number like one twenty
one or something.
The pixel next to it might be
one twenty four,
maybe where my tie begins to
enter, so if it was mostly blue
shirt, this would be a slight
difference in shading,
but pretty close,
then the tie would be a
different color,
so we might have quite a few
pixels for the blue shirt,
and a whole lot more for the
blackboard, that are very close.
And that's what are very
correlated.
And that's what gives us the
possibility of compression.
For example,
before the lecture starts,
if we had a blank blackboard,
then there's an image,
but it would make no sense to
take that image and tell you
what it is pixel by pixel.
I mean, there's a case in which
all pixel values,
all gray levels are the same --
or practically the same,
depending on the erasing of the
board, but extremely close --
and, so that's an image where
the standard basis is lousy.
That's the basic fact,
that the standard basis which
gives the value of every pixel
makes no use of the fact that
we're getting a whole lot of
pixels whose gray levels -- the
neighboring pixels tend to have
the same gray level as their
neighbors.
So how do we take advantage of
that fact?
Well, one basis vector that
would be extremely nice to
include in the basis would be a
vector of all ones.
That's not in our standard
basis, so let me just write
again, the standard basis is our
one, and all the rest zeroes,
zero, one, and all the rest,
zeroes, everybody knows what
these standard basis is.
Now, any other basis for R --
so this is -- for this very
high-dimensional space -- now
I'm going to speak about a
better basis.
Better basis -- and let me just
emphasize, one vector that would
be extremely nice to have in
that basis is the vector of all
ones.
Why is that?
Let me just say again,
because that vector of all
ones, by itself,
one vector is able to
completely give the information
on a solid image.
Of course, our image won't be
solid, it will have a mix of
solid and signal.
So having that one vector in
the basis is going to save us a
whole lot.
Now, the question is,
what other vectors should be in
the basis?
The extreme vector in the basis
might be a vector of one minus
one, one minus one,
one minus one.
That would be a vector that
shows --
I mean, that's like a
checkerboard vector,
right?
That's a vector that would,
if the image was like a huge
checkerboard of plus,
minus, plus,
minus, that vector would carry
the whole signal.
But much more common would be
maybe to have half the image,
darker and the other half
lighter.
So another vector that might be
quite useful in here would be
half ones and half minus ones.
I'm just trying to get across
the idea of that a basis could
be where, that first of all,
we've got the bases at our
disposal.
Like, we're free to choose
that.
And it's a billion-dollar
decision what we choose.
So, and TV people would rather
pre- would prefer one basis
based on the way the signal is
scanned, and movie people would
prefer another,
I mean, there's giant politics
in this question that really
reduces to a linear algebra
problem, what basis to choose.
I'll just mention the best
known basis, which JPEG uses,
-- let me put that here -- is
the Fourier basis.
So when you use the Fourier
basis, that includes --
this is the constant vector,
the D C vector if we're
electrical engineers,
the l- vector of all ones,
so it would include one,
one, one, one.
Often eight by eight is a good
choice.
Eight by eight is a good
So, what do I mean by this
eight by eight?
I mean that the big signal,
which is five twelve by five
twelve, gets broken down,
and JPEG does this,
into eight by eight blocks.
And we -- sort of,
this is too much to deal with
at once.
So what JPEG does is take this
eight by eight block,
which is sixty four
coefficients,
sixty four, pixels,
and changes the basis on that
piece.
And then, now,
let's see, I was going to write
down Fourier,
so you remember Fourier as this
vector of all ones,
and then, the vector --
oh, well, actually,
I gave a lecture earlier about
the Fourier matrix,
this matrix whose columns are
powers of a complex number w.
I won't repeat that,
because I don't want to go into
the details of the Fourier
basis, just to tell you how
compression works.
So what happens in JPEG?
What happens to the video,
to each image,
of these lectures?
It gets broken into eight by
eight blocks.
OK.
Within each block,
we have sixty four
coefficients,
sixty four basis vectors,
sixty four pixels,
and we change basis in sixty
four dimensional space using
these Fourier vectors.
Just note, that was a lossless
step.
Let me emphasize.
In comes the signal x.
We change basis.
This is the basis change.
Change basis.
Choose a better basis.
So it produces,
the coefficients c.
So sixty four pixels come in,
sixty four coefficients come
out.
Now comes the compression.
Now come -- this was lossless.
It's just -- we know that R --
R sixty four has plenty of
bases, and we've chosen one.
Now, in that basis,
we write the signal in that
basis, and that's what my
lecture -- that's the math part
of my lecture.
Now here's the application
part.
The next part is going to be
the compression step.
And that's lossy.
We're going to lose
information.
And what will actually happen
at that step?
Well, one thing we could do is
just throw away the small
coefficients.
So that's called thresholding,
we set some threshold.
Every coefficient,
every basis vector that's not
in there more than the threshold
value, and we set them threshold
so that our eye can't see the
difference, or can hardly see
the difference,
whether we throw away that
little bit of that basis vector
or keep it.
So this compression step
produces a compressed set of
coefficients.
I'll just keep going here.
So it keeps going,
this compression step produces
some coefficient c hat.
And with many zeroes.
So that's where the compression
came.
Probably, there is enough of
this vector of all ones -- we
very seldom throw that away.
Usually, its coefficient will
be large.
But the coefficient of
something like this,
that quickly alternative
vector, there's probably very
little of that in any smooth
signal.
That's high-frequency -- this
is low-frequency,
zero frequency.
This stuff is the highest
frequency we could have,
and if the noise,
the jitter is producing that
sort of output,
but a smooth lecture like this
one is, has very little of that
highest frequency,
very little noise in this
lecture.
OK, so we throw away whatever
there is, and we're left with
just a few coefficients,
and then we reconstruct a
signal using those coefficients.
We take those coefficients,
times their basis vectors,
but this sum doesn't have sixty
four terms any more.
Probably, it has about two or
three terms.
So that would -- say it has
From sixty four down to three,
that's compression of twenty
one to one.
That's the kind of compression
you're looking for.
And everybody is looking for
that sort of compression.
Let's see, I guess I met the
problem with the FBI and
fingerprints.
So there's a whole lot of still
images.
You know, with your thumb,
you make these inky marks which
go somewhere.
it used to go to Washington and
get stored in a big file.
So Washington had a file of
thirty million murderers,
cheaters on quizzes,
other stuff,
and actually,
there was no way to retrieve
them in time.
So suppose you're at the police
station, they say,
OK, this person may have done
this, check with Washington,
have they got -- are his or her
fingerprints on file?
Well, Washington won't know the
answer within a week if it's got
filing cabinets full of
fingerprints.
So of course,
the natural step is digitizing.
So all fingerprints are now
digitized, so now it's at least
electronic, but still there's
too much information in each
one.
I mean, you can't search
through that many,
fingerprints if the digital
image is five twelve squared by
five twelve squared,
if it's that many pixels.
So you get compressed.
So the FBI had to decide what
basis to choose for compression
of fingerprints.
And then they built a big new
facility in West Virginia,
and that's where fingerprints
now are sent.
So I think, if you get your
fingerprints done now at the
police station,
if it's an up-to-date police
station, it happens digitally,
and the signal is sent
digitally, and then in West
Virginia, it's compressed and
indexed.
And then, if they want to find
you, they can do it within
minutes instead of within a
week.
OK.
So this compression comes up
for signals, for images,
for video -- which is,
like these lectures -- there's
another aspect.
You could treat the video as
one still image after another
one, and compress each one,
and then run them and make a
video.
But that misses --
well, you can see why that's
not optimal.
In a video thing,
you have a sequence of images,
so video is really a sequence
of images but what about one
image to the next image?
They're extremely correlated.
I mean that I'm getting an
image every split-second,
and also, I'm moving slightly.
That's what's producing the,
jumpy motion on the video.
But I'm not,
like, you know -- each image in
the sequence is pretty close to
the one before.
So you have to use,
like, prediction and
correction.
I mean, the image of me one
instant -- one time-step later,
you would assume would be the
same, and then plus a small
correction.
And you would only code and
digitize the correction,
and compress the correction.
So a sequence of images that's
highly correlated and the
problem in compression is always
to use this correlation,
this fact that,
in time, or in space,
things don't change instantly,
they're very often smooth
changes, and,
you can predict one value from
the previous value.
OK.
So those are applications which
are pure linear algebra.
I could, well,
maybe you'll allow me to tell
you, and the book describes,
the new basis that's the
competition for Fourier.
So the competition for Fourier
is called wavelets,
and I can describe what that
basis is like,
say, in the eight by eight
case.
So the eight by eight wavelet
basis is the vector of all ones,
eight ones, then the vector of
four ones and four minus ones,
then the vector of two ones,
and two minus ones,
and four zeroes.
And also the vector of four
zeroes and two ones and two
minus ones.
So now I'm up to four,
and I need four more,
right?
For R^8?
The next basis vector will be
one minus one and six zeroes,
and then three more like that,
with the one minus one there,
and there, and there.
So those are eight vectors in
eight-dimensional space,
those are called wavelets,
and it's a very simple
wavelet choice,
it's a more sophisticated
choice.
This is a little jumpy,
to jump between one and minus
one.
And, actually,
you can see,
now, suppose you compare the
wavelet basis with the Fourier
basis above.
How could I write this guy,
which is in the Fourier basis,
it's an eight --
it's a vector in R^8.
How would I write that as a
combination of the wavelet
basis?
Have I told you enough about
the wavelet basis that you can
see, how does this very fast guy
-- what combination of the
wavelet basis is that very fast
guy?
It would be this one -- it
would be the sum of these four,
right?
That very fast guy will be that
one minus one,
and the next one,
and the next one.
So this is the sum of those
last four wavelets.
This one, we've kept,
and so on.
So, each -- well,
every -- well,
that's what a basis does.
Every vector in R^8 is some
combination of those,
and for the linear algebra --
so the linear algebra is this
step, find the coefficient.
That's the step we want to
take.
What if I give you the basis,
like this wavelet basis,
and I give you the pixel --
so here are the pixel values,
P1, P2, down to P8 -- what's
the job?
What's the linear algebra here?
So these are the values,
this is in the standard basis,
right?
Those are just the values at
eight successive points.
I guess I'm dropping down to
one dimension,
instead of eight by eight,
I'm just going to take eight
pixel values along that first
top row.
So what do I want to do?
In standard basis,
here are the pixel values.
I want to write that as a
combination of c1 times this
guy, plus c2 times this guy,
plus c3, these are the
coefficients,
plus c4 times this one -- do
you see what I'm doing?
I want to write this vector P
as a combination of c1 times the
first wavelet plus c8 times the
eighth wavelet.
That's the transform step.
That's the lossless step.
That's the step from P -- oh,
I'm calling it P here,
and I called it x there,
so let me -- at the risk of
moving, and therefore making
this jumpy -- suppose the signal
I'm now calling P,
that a pixel values,
and I'm looking for the
coefficients.
OK, tell me how to do it.
If I give you eight basis
vectors, and I give you the
input signal,
and I ask for the coefficients,
what do I do?
What's the step?
I'm trying to solve this,
I want to know the eight
coefficients,
so I'm changing from the
standard basis,
which is just the eight
gray-scale values to the wavelet
basis, where the same vector is
represented by eight numbers.
It's got to take eight numbers
to tell you a vector in R^8,
and those eight numbers are the
coefficients of the basis.
Look, we've done this thing
before.
There is the equation in vector
notation, we want to see it as a
matrix.
This is a combination of
columns of the wavelet matrix,
right?
This is P equals c1,
c2, down to c8,
and these guys are the columns.
I mean, this is the step that
we're constantly taking in this
course, the first basis vector
goes in the first column,
the second basis vector goes in
the second column,
and so on, the eight columns of
this wavelet matrix are the
eight basis vectors.
This is a wavelet matrix W.
So, the step to change basis --
so now I'm finally coming to
this change-of-basis,
so the change of basis that,
let me stay with this board,
but -- well,
let me just go above it,
here.
So the standard basis,
we know, the wavelet basis we
have here, and the transform is
simply, solve the equations,
P=W C.
So the coefficients
are W inverse P.
Right.
This shows a critical point.
A good basis has a nice,
fast, inverse.
So good basis means what?
Eh?
So this is like the
billion-dollar competition,
and it's not over yet.
People are going to come up
with better bases than these.
So a good basis will be,
first good thing would be fast.
I have to be able to multiply
by W fast, and multiply by W --
by its inverse fast.
That's -- if a basis doesn't
allow you to do that fast,
then it's going to take so much
time that you can't afford it.
So these bases -- the Fourier
basis, everybody said,
OK, I know how to deal quickly
with the Fourier basis,
because we have something
called the Fast Fourier
Transform.
So there's a FFT that came in
my earlier lecture,
and comes in the last chapter
of the
book, so change-of-basis is
done -- if, for the Fourier
basis, it's done fast by the FFT
and there's a fast wavelet
transform.
I can change,
for this wavelet example,
this matrix is easy to invert.
It's just somebody had a smart
idea in choosing that wavelet
basis and inverting it,
it has a nice inverse.
Actually, you can see why it
has a nice inverse.
Do you see any property of
these eight basis vectors?
Well, I've only written five of
them, but if you see that
property for those five,
you'll see it for the three
remaining.
Well, if I give you those eight
vectors and ask,
what's a nice property?
Well, you would say,
first, they're all ones and
minus ones and zeroes.
So every multiplication is very
fast using -- just in binary.
But what's the other great
property of those vectors?
Anybody see it?
So, of course,
when I think about a basis,
one nice property -- I don't
have to have it,
but I'm happy if it's there --
is that they're orthogonal.
If the basis vectors are
orthogonal, then I'm in good
shape.
And these are...
do you see?
Take the dot product of that
with that, you get four plus
ones and four minus ones,
you get zero.
Take the dot product of that
with that.
You get two plus ones and two
minus ones.
Or the dot product of that with
that.
Two plus ones and two minus
ones.
You can easily check that
that's an orthogonal basis.
It's not orthonormal.
To fix it up,
I should divide by the length,
to make them unit vectors.
Let's suppose I do that.
So somewhere in here,
I've got to account for the
fact that this has length square
root of eight,
that has length square root of
four, that has length square
root of two.
But that's just a constant
factor that's easy to --
so suppose we've done that.
Then, tell me what's W inverse?
That's what chapter four,
section four point four was
about.
If we have orthonormal columns
then the inverse is the same as
the transpose.
So if we have a fast way to
multiply by W,
which we do,
the inverse is going to look
just the same,
and we'll have a fast way to do
W inverse.
So that's the wavelet basis
passes this requirement for
fast.
We can use it fast.
But there's a second
requirement, is it any good?
Because the the very fastest
thing we could do is not to
change basis at all.
Right?
The fastest thing would be,
OK, stay with the standard
basis, stay with eight pixel
values.
But that was poor from
compression point of view,
right?
Those eight pixel values,
if I just took those eight
numbers, I can't throw some of
those away.
If I throw away ninety percent
-- if I compress ten to one,
and throw away ninety percent
of my pixel values,
well, my picture's just gone
dark.
Whereas, the basis that was
good, the wavelet basis or the
Fourier basis,
if I throw away c5,
c6, c7, and c8,
all I'm throwing away is little
blips that are probably there in
very small amounts.
So the second property that we
need is good compression.
So first, it has to be fast,
and secondly,
a few basis vectors should come
close to the signal.
So a few is enough.
Can I write it that way?
A few basis vectors are enough
to reproduce the image just
exactly as on a video of these
18.06 lectures.
Uh, I don't know what the
compression rate is,
I'll ask, David,
who does the compression --
and, by the way,
I'll try to get the lectures,
that are relevant for the quiz
up onto the Web in time.
So I'll send them a message
today.
So, he's using the Fourier
basis because the JPEG -- so
JPEG two thousand,
which will be the next standard
for image compression,
will include wavelets.
So, I mean, you're actually
getting a kind of up-to-date,
picture of where this big world
of signal and image processing
is.
That Fourier is what everybody
knew, and what people
automatically used,
and the new one is wavelets,
where this is the simplest set
of wavelets.
And this isn't the one that the
FBI uses, by the way,
the FBI uses a smoother
wavelet, instead of jumping from
one to minus one,
it's a smooth,
Cutoff.
and, that's what we'll be in in
JPEG two thousand.
OK, so that's that application.
Now, let me come to the math,
the linear algebra part of the
lecture.
Well, we've actually seen a
change-of-basis.
So let -- let me just review
that
eh-eh change-of-basis idea,
and then the i- and then the
transformation to a matrix.
OK.
So this, I hope you see that
these applications are really
big.
Now, I have to talk a little
about change-of-basis,
and a little about that.
The matrix.
OK.
So change-of-basis.
Basically, forgive that put,
OK, I have, I have my vector in
one basis, and I want to change
to a different one.
Actually, you saw it for the
wavelet case.
So I need the -- let the matrix
W, and the columns of W be the
new basis vectors.
Then the change-of-basis
involves, just as it did there,
W inverse.
So we have the vector,
say, x, in the old basis,
and that converts to a vector,
let's say, c,
in the new basis,
and the relation is exactly
what we had there,
that x is W c.
That's the step we have to
take.
There's a matrix W that gives
us a change-of-basis.
OK.
What I want to do is think
about transformations on
matrices.
So here's the question to
complete this lecture.
Suppose I have a linear
transformation T.
So we would think of it as an
eight -- as a n by n matrix.
And it's computed with respect
to a certain basis.
So T -- no, I'm sorry.
I've got the transformation T,
period.
That's taking eight-dimensional
space to eight-dimensional
space.
Now, let's get matrices in
there.
OK.
So, with respect to a first
basis, say v1 up to v8,
it has a matrix A.
I'm just setting up letters
here.
With respect to a second basis,
say, I'll make it u1 up to --
or w1, since I've used (w)s,
w1 up to w8,
it has a matrix B.
And my question is,
what's the connection between A
and B?
How is the matrix -- the
transformation T is settled.
We could say,
it's a rotation,
for example.
So that would be one
transformation of
eight-dimensional space,
just spin it a little.
Or project it.
Or whatever linear
transformation we've got.
Now, we have to remember -- my
first step is to remind you how
you create that matrix A.
Then my second step is,
we would use the same method to
create B, but because it came
from the same transformation,
there's got to be a relation
between A and B.
What's the relation between A
and B?
And let me jump to the answer
on that one.
That if I have the same
transformation,
and I'm compute on its matrix
in one basis,
and then I computer it in
another basis,
those two matrices are similar.
So these two matrices are
similar.
Now, do you remember what
similar matrices meant?
Similar.
A is similar to -- the two
matrices are similar.
Similar.
And what do I mean by that?
I mean that I take the matrix
B, and I can compute it from the
matrix A using some similarity,
some matrix M on one side,
and M inverse on the other.
And this M will be the
change-of-basis matrix.
This part of the lecture is,
admittedly, compressed.
What I wanted you to -- it's
really the conclusion that I
want you to spot.
Now, I have to go back and say,
what does it mean for A to be
the matrix of this
transformation T.
So I have to remind you what
that meant, that was in the last
lecture.
Then this is the conclusion
that if I change to a different
basis, we now know -- see,
if I change to a different
basis, two things happen.
Every vector has new
coordinates.
There, the rule is this one,
between the old coordinates and
the new ones.
Every matrix changes,
every transformation has a new
matrix.
And the new matrix is related
this way, the M could be the
same as the W.
The M there would be the W
here.
OK.
So, can I, in the remaining
minutes, recapture my lecture --
the end of my lecture that was
just before Thanksgiving,
about the matrix?
OK.
What's the matrix?
And I'll just take one basis.
So now this part is going to go
onto this board here.
What is the matrix?
What is A?
OK.
Using a basis v1 up to v8.
Mm.
OK.
What's the point?
The point is,
if I know what the
transformation does to those
eight basis vectors,
I know it completely.
I know T, I know everything
about T, I know T completely
from knowing T of V -- what T
does to v1, what T does to v2,
what T does to v8.
Why is that?
It's because T is a linear
transformation.
So that if I know what these
outputs are -- so these are the
inputs v1 up to v8,
these are the outputs from the
transformation,
like everyone rotated,
everyone projected,
whatever transformation I've
done, then why is it that I know
everything?
How does linearity work?
Why?
This is because every x is some
combination of these basis
vectors, right?
c1v1, c2v2, c8v8,
they were a basis.
That's the whole point of a
basis, that every vector is a
combination of the basis vectors
in exactly one way.
And then, what is T of x?
The point is,
I claim that we know T of x
completely for every x,
because every x is a
combination of those --
and now we use the linear
transformation part to say that
the output from x has to be c1
times the output from v1 plus v2
times the output from v2,
and so on.
Up through c8 times the output
from v8.
So this is like just saying,
OK.
We know everything when we know
what T does to each basis
vector.
OK.
So those are the eight things
we need.
Now -- but we need these
answers in this basis.
So this first output is some
combination of the eight basis
vectors.
So write T acting on the first
input --
in other words,
write the first output as a
combination of the basis
vectors, say a11 v1 + a21 v2 and
so on a81 v8.
Write T of v2 as some
combination a12 of v1,
a22 of v2 and so on.
I'm creating the matrix A,
column by column.
Those numbers go in the first
column, these numbers go in the
second column,
the matrix A that thi- this --
this is our matrix that
represents T in this basis is
these numbers.
a11 down to a18,
a21 down to a28,
and so on.
OK.
That's the recipe.
In other words,
if I give you a transformation,
and a basis.
So that's what I have to give
you.
The inputs are the basis and to
tell you what the transformation
is.
And then, you tell me -- you
compute T for each basis,
expand that result in the
basis, and that gives you the
sixty four numbers that go into
the matrix A.
Let me suppose -- let's close
with the best example of all.
Suppose v1 to v8,
this basis, is the
eigenvectors.
Suppose we have an eigenvector
basis so that T(vi) is in the
same direction of vi.
Now, my question is,
what is A?
Can you carry through the
steps?
Let's do them together,
because we can do it in one
minute.
So, we've chosen this perfect
basis.
And, actually,
with signal image processing,
they might look for the
eigenvectors.
But that would take more
calculation time that just
saying, OK, we'll use the
wavelet basis.
Or, OK, we'll use the Fourier
basis.
But the very best basis is the
eigenvector basis.
OK, what's the matrix?
So, what's the first column of
the matrix?
How do I get the first column?
I take the first basis vector
v1.
I opt -- I look to see,
what does the transformation do
to it?
The output is lambda one v1.
I express that output as a
combination so the first input
is v1.
Its output is lambda one v1.
Now write lambda one v1 as a
combination of the basis
vectors, well,
it's already done.
It's just lambda one times the
first basis vector and zero
times the others.
So this first column will have
lambda one and zeroes.
OK.
Second input is v2.
Output is lambda two v2.
OK, write that output as a
combination of the (v)s.
It's already done.
It's just lambda two times the
second v.
So we need, in the second
column, we have lambda two times
the second v.
Well, you see what's coming,
that in that basis,
in the eigenvector basis,
the matrix is diagonal.
So that's the perfect basis,
that's the basis we'd love to
have for image processing,
but to find the eigenvectors of
our pixel matrix would be too
expensive.
So we do something cheaper and
close, which is to choose a good
basis like wavelets.
OK, thanks.
So I'll -- quiz review on
Wednesday, all day.
Thanks.