OK, here's the last lecture in
the chapter on orthogonality.
So we met orthogonal vectors,
two vectors,
we met orthogonal subspaces,
like the row space and null
space.
Now today we meet an orthogonal
basis, and an orthogonal matrix.
So we really --
this chapter cleans up
orthogonality.
And really I want -- I should
use the word orthonormal.
Orthogonal is -- so my vectors
are q1,q2 up to qn -- I use the
letter "q", here,
to remind me,
I'm talking about orthogonal
things, not just any vectors,
but orthogonal ones.
So what does that mean?
That means that every q is
orthogonal to every other q.
It's a natural idea,
to have a basis that's headed
off at ninety-degree angles,
the inner products are all
zero.
Of course if q is -- certainly
qi is not orthogonal to itself.
But there we'll make the best
choice again,
make it a unit vector.
Then qi transpose qi is one,
for a unit vector.
The length squared is one.
And that's what I would use the
word normal.
So for this part,
normalized,
unit length for this part.
OK.
So first part of the lecture is
how does having an orthonormal
basis make things nice?
It certainly does.
It makes all the calculations
better, a whole lot of numerical
linear algebra is built around
working with orthonormal
vectors,
because they never get out of
hand, they never overflow or
underflow.
And I'll put them into a matrix
Q, and then the second part of
the lecture will be suppose my
basis, my columns of A are not
orthonormal.
How do I make them so?
And the two names associated
with that simple idea are Graham
and Schmidt.
So the first part is we've got
a basis like this.
Let's put those into the
columns of a matrix.
So a matrix Q that has -- I'll
put these orthonormal vectors,
q1 will be the first column,
qn will be the n-th column.
And I want to say,
I want to write this property,
qi transpose qj being zero,
I want to put that in a matrix
form.
And just the right thing is to
look at Q transpose Q.
So this chapter has been
looking at A transpose A.
So it's natural to look at Q
transpose Q.
And the beauty is it comes out
perfectly.
Because Q transpose has these
vectors in its rows,
the first row is q1 transpose,
the nth row is qn transpose.
So that's Q transpose.
And now I want to multiply by
Q.
That has q1 along to qn in the
columns.
That's Q.
And what do I get?
You really -- this is the first
simplest most basic fact,
that how do orthonormal
vectors, orthonormal columns in
a matrix, what happens if I
compute Q transpose Q?
Do you see it?
If I take the first row times
the first column,
what do I get?
A one.
If I take the first row times
the second column,
what do I get?
Zero.
That's the orthogonality.
The first row times the last
column is zero.
And so I'm getting ones on the
diagonal and I'm getting zeroes
everywhere else.
I'm getting the identity
matrix.
You see how that's --
it's just like the right
calculation to do.
If you have orthonormal
columns, and the matrix doesn't
have to be square here.
We might have just two columns.
And they might have four,
lots of components.
So but they're orthonormal,
and when we do Q transpose
times Q,
that Q transpose times Q or A
transpose A just asks for all
those dot products.
Rows times columns.
And in this orthonormal case,
we get the best possible
answer, the identity.
OK, so this is -- so I mean now
we have a new bunch of important
matrices.
What have we seen previously?
We've seen in the distant past
we had triangular matrices,
diagonal matrices,
permutation matrices,
that was early chapters,
then we had row echelon forms,
then in this chapter we've
already seen projection
matrices,
and now we're seeing this new
class of matrices with
orthonormal columns.
That's a very long expression.
I sorry that I can't just call
them orthogonal matrices.
But that word orthogonal
matrices -- or maybe I should be
able to call it orthonormal
matrices, why don't we call it
orthonormal --
I mean that would be an
absolutely perfect name.
For Q, call it an orthonormal
matrix because its columns are
orthonormal.
OK, but the convention is that
we only use that name orthogonal
matrix, we only use this -- this
word orthogonal,
we don't even say orthonormal
for some unknown reason,
matrix when it's square.
So in the case when this is a
square matrix,
that's the case we call it an
orthogonal matrix.
And what's special about the
case when it's square?
When it's a square matrix,
we've got its inverse,
so --
so in the case if Q is square,
then Q transpose Q equals I
tells us -- let me write that
underneath -- tells us that Q
transpose is Q inverse.
There we have the easy to
remember property for a square
matrix with orthonormal columns.
That -- I need to write some
examples down.
Let's see.
Some examples like if I take
any -- so examples,
let's do some examples.
Any permutation matrix,
let me take just some random
permutation matrix.
Permutation Q equals let's say
oh, make it three by three,
say zero, zero,
one, one, zero,
zero, zero, one,
zero.
OK.
That certainly has unit vectors
in its columns.
Those vectors are certainly
perpendicular to each other.
And if I -- and so that's it.
That makes it a Q.
And -- if I took its transpose,
if I multiplied by Q transpose,
shall I do that --
and let me stick in Q transpose
here.
Just to do that multiplication
once more, transpose it'll put
the -- make that into a column,
make that into a column,
make that into a column.
And the transpose is also --
another Q.
Another orthonormal matrix.
And when I multiply that
product I get I.
OK, so there's an example.
And actually there's a second
example.
But those are real easy
examples, right,
I mean to get orthogonal
columns by just putting ones in
different places is like too
easy.
So let me keep going with
examples.
So here's another simple
example.
Cos theta sine theta,
there's a unit vector,
oh, let me even take it,
well, yeah.
Cos theta sine theta and now
the other way I want sine theta
cos theta.
But I want the inner product to
be zero.
And if I put a minus there,
it'll do it.
So that's --
unit vector,
that's a unit vector.
And if I take the dot product,
I get minus plus zero.
OK.
For example Q equals say one,
one, one, minus one,
is that an orthogonal matrix?
I've got orthogonal columns
there, but it's not quite an
orthogonal matrix.
How shall I fix it to be an
orthogonal matrix?
Well, what's the length of
those column vectors,
the dot product with themselves
is -- right now it's two,
right, the -- the length
squared.
The length squared would be one
plus one would be two,
the length would be square root
of two,
so I better divide by square
root of two.
OK.
So there's a -- there now I
have got an orthogonal matrix,
in fact, it's this one -- when
theta is pi over four.
The cosines and well almost,
I guess the minus sine is down
there, so maybe,
I don't know,
maybe minus pi over four or
something.
OK.
Let me do one final example,
just to show that you can get
bigger ones.
Q equals let me take that
matrix up in the corner and I'll
sort of repeat that pattern,
repeat it again,
and then minus it down here.
That's one of the world's
favorite orthogonal matrices.
I hope I got it right,
is -- can you see whether -- if
I take the inner product of one
column with another one,
let's see, if I take the inner
product of that column with that
I have two minuses and two
pluses, that's good.
When I take the inner product
of that with that I have a plus
and a minus, a minus and a plus.
Good.
I think it all works out.
And what do I have to divide by
now?
To make those into unit
vectors.
Right now the vector one,
one, one, one has length two.
Square root of four.
So I have to divide by two to
make it unit vector,
so there's another.
That's my entire array of
simple examples.
This construction is named
after a guy called Adhemar and
we know how to do it for two,
four, sixteen,
sixty-four and so on,
but we -- nobody knows exactly
which size matrices have --
which size -- which sizes allow
orthogonal matrices of ones and
minus ones.
So Adhemar matrix is an
orthogonal matrix that's got
ones and minus ones,
and a lot of ones -- some we
know, some other sizes,
there couldn't be a five by
five I think.
But there are some sizes
that nobody yet knows whether
there could be or can't be a
matrix like that.
OK.
You see those orthogonal
matrices.
Now let me ask what -- why is
it good to have orthogonal
matrices?
What calculation is made easy?
If I have an orthogonal matrix.
And -- let me remember that
the matrix could be
rectangular.
Shall I put down -- I better
put a rectangular example down.
So the -- these were all square
examples.
Can I put down just -- a
rectangular one just to be sure
that we realize that this is
possible.
let's help me out.
Let's see,
if I put like a one,
two, two and a minus two,
minus one, two.
That's -- a matrix -- oh its
columns aren't normalized yet.
I always have to remember to do
that.
I always do that last because
it's easy to do.
What's the length of those
columns?
So if I wanted them --
if I wanted them to be length
one, I should divide by their
length, which is -- so I'd look
at one squared plus two squared
plus two squared,
that's one and four and four is
nine, so I take the square root
and I need to divide by three.
OK.
So there is -- well,
without that,
I've got one orthonormal
vector.
I mean just one unit vector.
Now put that guy in.
Now I have a basis for the
column space for a
two-dimensional space,
an orthonormal basis,
right?
These two columns are
orthonormal, they would be an
orthonormal basis for this
two-dimensional space that they
span.
Orthonormal vectors by the way
have got to be independent.
It's easy to show that
orthonormal vectors since
they're headed off all at ninety
degrees there's no combination
that gives zero.
Now if I wanted to create now a
third one, I could either just
put in some third vector that
was independent
and go to this Graham-Schmidt
calculation that I'm going to
explain, or I could be inspired
and say look,
that -- with that pattern,
why not put a one in there,
and a two in there,
and try to fix up the signs so
that they worked.
Hmm.
I don't know if I've done this
too brilliantly.
Let's see, what signs,
that's minus,
maybe I'd make a minus sign
there, how would that be?
Yeah, maybe that works.
I think that those three
columns are orthonormal and they
-- the beauty of this -- this is
the last example I'll probably
find where there's no square
root, the -- the punishing thing
in Graham-Schmidt,
maybe we better know that in
advance, is that because I want
these vectors to be unit
vectors, I'm always running into
square roots.
I'm always dividing by lengths.
And those lengths are square
roots.
So you'll see as soon as I do a
Graham-Schmidt example,
square roots are going to show
up.
But here are some examples
where we did it without any
square root.
OK.
So -- so great.
Now next question is what's the
good of having a Q?
What formulas become easier?
Suppose I want to project,
so suppose Q -- suppose Q has
orthonormal columns.
I'm using the letter Q to mean
this, I'll write it this one
more time, but I always mean
when I write a Q,
I always mean that it has
orthonormal columns.
So suppose I want to project
onto its column space.
So what's the projection
matrix?
What's the projection matrix is
I project onto a column space?
OK, that gives me a chance to
review the projection section,
including that big formula,
which used to be -- those four
As in a row, but now it's got
Qs, because I'm projecting onto
the column space of Q,
so do you remember what it was?
It's Q Q transpose Q inverse Q
transpose.
That's my four Qs in a row.
But what's good here?
What --
what makes this formula nice if
I'm projecting onto a column
space when I have orthonormal
basis for that space?
What makes it nice is this is
the identity.
I don't have to do any
inversion.
I just get Q Q transpose.
So Q Q transpose is a
projection matrix.
Oh, I can't help --
I can't resist just checking
the properties,
what are the properties of a
projection matrix?
There are two properties to
know for any projection matrix.
And I'm saying that this is the
right projection matrix when
we've got this orthonormal basis
in the columns.
OK.
So there's the projection
matrix.
Suppose the matrix is square.
First just tell me first this
extreme case.
If my matrix is square and it's
got these orthonormal columns,
then what's the column space?
If I have a square matrix and I
have independent columns,
and even orthonormal columns,
then the column space is the
whole space, right?
And what's the projection
matrix onto the whole space?
The identity matrix.
If I'm projecting in the whole
space, every vector B is right
where it's supposed to be and I
don't have to move it by
projection.
So this would be -- I'll put in
parentheses this is I if Q is
square.
Well that we said that already.
If Q is square,
that's the case where Q
transpose is Q inverse,
we can put it on the right,
we can put it on the left,
we always get the identity
matrix, if it's square.
But if it's not a square matrix
then it's not -- we don't get
the identity matrix.
We have Q Q transpose,
and just again what are those
two properties of a projection
matrix?
First of all,
it's symmetric.
OK, no problem,
that's certainly a symmetric
matrix.
So what's that second property
of a projection?
That if you project and project
again you don't move the second
time.
So the other property of a
projection matrix should be that
Q Q transpose twice should be
the same
as Q Q transpose once.
That's projection matrices.
And that property better fall
out right away because from the
fact we know about orthonormal
matrices, Q transpose Q is I.
OK, you see it.
In the middle here is sitting Q
Q t- Q transpose Q,
sorry, that's what I meant to
say,
Q transpose Q is I.
So that's sitting right in the
middle, that cancels out,
to give the identity,
we're left with one Q Q
transpose, and we're all set.
OK.
So this is the projection
matrix -- all the equation --
all the messy equations of this
chapter become trivial when our
matrix -- when we have this
orthonormal basis.
I mean what do I mean by all
the equations?
Well, the most important
equation was the normal
equation, do you remember old A
transpose A x hat equals A
transpose b?
But now -- now A is Q.
Now I'm thinking I
have Q transpose Q X hat equals
Q transpose b.
And what's good about that?
What's good is that matrix on
the left side is the identity.
The matrix on the left is the
identity, Q transpose Q,
normally it isn't,
normally it's that matrix of
inner products and you've to
compute all those dopey inner
products and -- and -- and solve
the system.
Here the inner products are all
one or zero.
This is the identity matrix.
It's gone.
And there's the answer.
There's no inversion involved.
Each component of x is a Q
times b.
What that equation
is saying is that the i-th
component is the i-th basis
vector times b.
That's -- probably the most
important formula in some major
parts of mathematics,
that if we have orthonormal
basis, then the component
in the -- in the i-th,
along the i-th -- the
projection on the i-th basis
vector is just qi transpose b.
That number x that we look for
is just a dot product.
OK.
OK, so I'm ready now for the
sort of like second half of the
lecture.
Where we don't start with an
orthogonal matrix,
orthonormal vectors.
We just start with independent
vectors and we want to make them
orthonormal.
So I'm going to -- can I do
that now?
Now here comes Graham-Schmidt.
So -- Graham-Schmidt.
So this
is a calculation,
I won't say -- I can't quite
say it's like elimination,
because it's different,
our goal isn't triangular
anymore.
With elimination our goal was
make the matrix triangular.
Now our goal is make the matrix
orthogonal.
Make those columns orthonormal.
So let me start with two
columns.
So I start with vectors a and
b.
And they're just like -- here,
let me draw them.
Here's a.
Here's b.
For example.
A isn't specially horizontal,
wasn't meant to be,
just a is one
vector, b is another.
I want to produce those two
vectors, they might be in
twelve-dimensional space,
or they might be in
two-dimensional space.
They're independent,
anyway.
So I better be sure I say that.
I start with independent
vectors.
And I want to produce out of
that q
1 and q2, I want to produce
orthonormal vectors.
And Graham and Schmidt tell me
how.
OK.
Well, actually you could tell
me how, we don't need --
frankly, I don't know -- there's
only one idea here,
if Graham had the idea,
I don't know what Schmidt did.
But OK.
So you'll see it.
We don't need either of them,
actually.
OK, so what I going to do.
I'll take that -- this first
guy.
OK.
Well, he's fine.
That direction is fine except
-- yeah, I'll say OK,
I'll settle for that direction.
So I'm going to --
I'm going to get,
so what I going to -- my goal
is I'm going to get orthogonal
vectors and I'll call those
capital A and B.
So that's the key step is to
get from any two vectors to two
orthogonal vectors.
And then at the end,
no problem, I'll get
orthonormal vectors,
how will --
what will those will be my qs,
q1 and q2, and what will they
be?
Once I've got A and B
orthogonal, well,
look, it's no big deal -- maybe
that's what Schmidt did,
he, brilliant Schmidt,
thought OK, divide by the
length, all right.
That's Schmidt's contribution.
OK.
But Graham had a little more
thinking to do,
right?
We haven't done Graham's part.
This part except OK,
I'm happy with A,
A can be A.
That first direction is fine.
Why should -- no complaint
about that.
The trouble is the second
direction is not fine.
Because it's not orthogonal to
the first.
I'm looking for a vector
that's -- starts with B,
but makes it orthogonal to A.
What's the vector?
How do I do that?
How do I produce from this
vector a piece that's orthogonal
to this one?
And the -- remember these
vectors might be in two
dimensions or they might be in
twelve
dimensions.
I'm just looking for the idea.
So what's the idea?
Where did we have orthogonal --
a vector showing up that was
orthogonal to this guy?
Well, that was the first basic
calculation of the whole
chapter.
We -- we did a projection and
the projection gave us this
part,
which was the part in the A
direction.
Now, the part we want is the
other part, the e part.
This part.
This is going to be our -- that
guy is that guy.
This is our vector B.
That gives us that
ninety-degree angle.
So B is you could say -- B is
really what we previously called
e.
The error vector.
And what is it?
I mean what do I -- what is B
here?
A is A, no problem.
B is -- OK, what's this error
piece?
Do you remember?
It's I start with the original
B and I take away what?
Its projection,
this P.
This -- the vector B,
this error vector,
is the original vector removing
the projection.
So instead of wanting the
projection,
now that's what I want to throw
away.
I want to get the part that's
perpendicular.
And there will be a
perpendicular part,
it won't be zero.
Because these vectors were
independent, so B -- if B was
along the direction of A,
then if the original B and A
were in the same direction,
then I'm -- I've only got one
direction.
But here they're in two
independent directions and all
I'm doing is getting that guy.
So what's its formula?
What's the formula for that if
-- I want to subtract
the projection,
so do you remember the
projection?
It's some multiple of A and
what's that multiple?
It's -- it's that thing we
called x in the very very first
lecture on this chapter.
There's an A transpose A in the
bottom and there's an A
transpose B, isn't that it?
I think that's Graham's
formula.
Or Graham-Schmidt.
No, that's Graham.
Schmidt has got to divide the
whole thing by the length,
so he -- his formula makes a
mess which I'm not willing to
write down.
So let's just see that what I
saying here?
I'm saying that this vector is
perpendicular to A.
That these are orthogonal.
A is perpendicular to B.
Can you check that?
How do you see that yes,
of course, we -- our picture is
telling us, yes,
we did it right.
How would I check that this
matrix is perpendicular to A?
I would multiply by A transpose
and I better get zero,
right?
I should check that.
A transpose B should come out
zero.
So this is A transpose times --
now what did we say B was?
We start with the original B,
and we take away this
projection, and that should come
out zero.
Well, here we get an A
transpose B minus -- and here is
another A transpose B,
and the -- and it's an A
transpose A over A transpose A,
a one, those cancel,
and we do get zero.
Right.
Now I guess I can do numbers in
there.
But I have to take a third
vector to be sure we've got this
system down.
So now I have to say if I have
independent vectors A,
B and C, I'm looking for
orthogonal vectors A,
B and capital C,
and then of course the third
guy will just be C over its
length, the unit vector.
So this is now the problem.
I got B here.
I got A very easily.
And now -- if you see the idea,
we could figure out a formula
for C.
So now that -- so this is like
a typical homework quiz problem.
I give you two vectors,
you do this,
I give you three vectors,
and you have to make them
orthonormal.
So you do this again,
the first vector's fine,
the second vector is
perpendicular
to the first,
and now I need a third vector
that's perpendicular to the
first one and the second one.
Right?
Tthis is the end of a -- the
lecture is to find this guy.
Find this vector -- this vector
C, that's perpendicular we n- at
this point we know A and B.
But C, the little c that we're
given, is off in some -- it's
got to come out of the
blackboard to be independent,
so -- so can I sort of draw off
-- off comes a c somewhere.
I don't know,
where I going to put the darn
thing?
Maybe I'll put it off,
oh, I don't know,
like that somehow,
C, little c.
And I already know that
perpendicular direction,
that one and that one.
So now what's the idea?
Give me the Graham-Schmidt
formula for C.
What is this C here?
Equals what?
What I going to do?
I'll start with the given one.
As before.
Right?
I start with the vector I'm
given.
And what do I do with it?
I want to remove out of it,
I want to subtract off,
so I'll put a minus sign in,
I want to subtract off its
components in the A,
capital A and capital B
directions.
I just want to get those out of
there.
Well, I know how to do that.
I did it with B.
So I'll just -- so let me take
away -- what if I do this?
What have I done?
I've got little c and what have
I subtracted from it?
Its component,
its projection if
you like, in the A direction.
And now I've got to subtract
off its component B transpose C
over B transpose B,
that multiple of B,
is its component in the B
direction.
And that gives me the vector
capital C that if anything is --
if there's any justice,
this C should be perpendicular
to A and it should be
perpendicular to B.
And the only thing it's --
hasn't got is unit vector,
so we divide by its length to
get that too.
OK.
Let me do an example.
Can I -- I'll make my life
easy, I'll just take two
vectors.
So let me do a numerical
example.
If I'll give you two vectors,
you give me back the
Graham-Schmidt orthonormal
basis, and we'll see how to
express that in matrix form.
OK.
So let me give you the two
vectors.
So I'll take the vector A
equals let's say
one, one, one,
why not?
And B equals let's say one,
zero, two, OK?
I didn't want to cheat and make
them orthogonal in the first
place because then
Graham-Schmidt wouldn't be
needed.
OK.
So those are not orthogonal.
So what is capital A?
Well that's the same as big A.
That was fine.
What's B?
So B is this b -- is the
original B, and then I subtract
off some multiple of the A.
And what's the multiple?
What goes in here?
B -- here's the A -- this is
the -- this is the little b,
this is the big A,
also the little a,
and I want to multiply it by
that right -- that right ratio,
which has A transpose A,
here's my ratio.
I'm just doing this.
So it's A transpose B,
what is A transpose B,
it looks like three.
And what is A -- oh,
my -- what's A transpose A?
Three.
I'm sorry.
I didn't know that was going to
happen.
OK.
But it happened.
Why should we knock it?
OK.
So do you see it all right?
That's A transpose B,
there's A transpose A,
that's the fraction,
so I take this away,
and I get one take away one is
a zero, zero minus this one is a
minus one, and two minus the one
is a one.
OK.
And what's this vector that we
finally found?
This is B.
And how do I know it's right?
How do I know I've got a vector
I want?
I check that B is perpendicular
to -- that A and B are
perpendicular.
That A is perpendicular to B.
Just look at that.
That one -- the dot product of
that with that is zero.
OK.
So now what is my q1 and q2?
Why don't I put them in a
matrix?
Of course.
Since I'm always putting these
-- so the Q, I'll put the q1 and
the
q2 in a matrix.
And what are they?
Now when I'm writing q-s I'm
supposed to make things
normalized.
I'm supposed to make things
unit vectors.
So I'm going to take that A but
I'm going to divide it by square
root of three.
And I'm going to take this B
but I'm
going to divide it by square
root of two to make it a unit
vector, and there is my matrix.
That's my matrix with
orthonormal columns coming from
Graham-Schmidt and it sort of it
-- it came from the original
one, one, one,
one, zero, two,
right?
That was my original guys.
These were the two I started
with.
These are the two that I'm
happy to end with.
Because those are orthonormal.
So that's what Graham-Schmidt
did.
It -- well, tell me about the
column spaces of these matrices.
How is the column space of Q
related to the column space of
A?
So I'm always asking you things
like this, and that makes you
think,
OK, the column space is all
combinations of the columns,
it's that plane,
right?
I've got two vectors in
three-dimensional space,
their column space is a plane,
the column space of this matrix
is a plane, what's the relation
between the planes?
Between the two column spaces?
They're one and the same,
right?
It's the same column space.
All I'm taking is here this B
thing that I computed,
this B thing that I computed is
a combination of B and A,
and A was little A,
so I'm always working here with
this in the same space.
I'm just like getting
ninety-degree angles in there.
Where my original column space
had a perfectly good basis,
but it wasn't as good as this
basis, because it wasn't
orthonormal.
Now this one is orthonormal,
and I have a basis then that --
so now projections,
all the calculations I would
ever want to do are -- are a
cinch with this orthonormal
basis.
One final point.
One final point
in this chapter.
And it's -- just like
elimination.
We learned how to do
elimination, we know all the
steps, we can do it.
But then I came back to it and
said look at it as a matrix in
matrix language and elimination
gave me -- what was elimination
in
matrix language?
I'll just put it up there.
A was LU.
That was matrix,
that was elimination.
Now, I want to do the same for
Graham-Schmidt.
Everybody who works in linear
algebra isn't going to write out
the columns are orthogonal,
or orthonormal.
And isn't going to
write out these formulas.
They're going to write out the
connection between the matrix A
and the matrix Q.
And the two matrices have the
same column space,
but there's some -- some matrix
is taking the -- and I'm going
to call it R,
so A equals QR is the magic
formula here.
It's the expression of
Graham-Schmidt.
And I'll -- let me just capture
that.
So that's the -- my final step
then is A equal QR.
Maybe I can squeeze it in here.
So A has columns,
let's say a1 and a2.
Let me suppose n is two,
just two vectors.
OK.
So that's some combination of
q1 and q2.
And times some matrix R.
They have the same column
space.
This is just -- this matrix
just includes in it whatever
these numbers like three over
three and one over square root
of three and
one over square root of two,
probably that's what it's got.
One over square root of three,
one over square root of two,
something there,
but actually it's got a zero
there.
So the main point about this A
equal QR is this R turns out to
be upper
triangular.
It turns out that this zero is
upper triangular.
We could see why.
Let me see, I can put in
general formulas for what these
are.
This I think in here should be
the inner product of a1 with q1.
And this one should be the --
the inner product of a1 with
q2.
And that's what I believe is
zero.
This will be something here,
and this will be something here
with inner -- a1 transpose q2,
sorry a2 transpose q1 and a2
transpose q2.
But why is that guy zero?
Why is a1 q2 zero?
That's the key to this being --
this R here being upper
triangular.
You know why a1q2 is zero,
because a1 -- that was my --
this was really a and b here.
This was really a and b.
So this is a transpose q2.
And the whole point of
Graham-Schmidt was that we
constructed these later q-s to
be perpendicular to the earlier
vectors, to the earlier -- all
the earlier vectors.
So that's why we get a
triangular matrix.
The -- result is extremely
satisfactory.
That if I have a matrix
with independent columns,
the Graham-Schmidt produces a
matrix with orthonormal columns,
and the connection between
those is a triangular matrix.
That last point,
that the connection is a
triangular matrix,
please look in the book,
you have to see that one more
time.
OK.
Thanks, that's great.