Are we ready?
Okay, ready for me to start.
Ready for the taping to start
in a minute.
He's going to raise his hand
and signal when I'm on.
Just a minute,
though, let them settle.0
Okay, guys.
Okay, give me the signal,
then, when you want me to
start.
Okay, this is linear algebra,
lecture four.
And, the first thing I have to
do is something that was on the
list for last time,
but here it is now.
What's the inverse of a
product?
If I multiply two matrices
together and I know their
inverses, how do I get the
inverse of A times B?
So I know what inverses mean
for a single matrix A and for a
matrix B.
What matrix do I multiply by to
get the identity if I have A B?
Okay, that'll be simple but so
basic.
Then I'm going to use that to
-- I will have a product of
matrices and the product that
we'll meet will be these
elimination matrices and the net
result of today's lectures is
the big formula for elimination,
so the net result of today's
lecture is this great way to
look at Gaussian elimination.
We know that we get from A to U
by elimination.
We know the steps -- but now we
get the right way to look at it,
A equals L U.
So that's the high point for
today.
Okay.
Can I take the easy part,
the first step first?
So, suppose A is invertible --
and of course it's going to be a
big question,
when is the matrix invertible?
But let's say A is invertible
and B is invertible,
then what matrix gives me the
inverse of A B?
So that's the direct question.
What's the inverse of A B?
Do I multiply those separate
inverses?
Yes.
I multiply the two matrices A
inverse and B inverse,
but what order do I multiply?
In reverse order.
And you see why.
So the right thing to put here
is B inverse A inverse.
That's the inverse I'm after.
We can just check that A B
times that matrix gives the
identity.
Okay.
So why -- once again,
it's this fact that I can move
parentheses around.
I can just erase them all and
do the multiplications any way I
want to.
So what's the right
multiplication to do first?
B times B inverse.
This product here I is the
identity.
Then A times the identity is
the identity and then finally A
times A inverse gives the
identity.
So forgive the dumb example in
the book.
Why do you, do the inverse
things in reverse order?
It's just like -- you take off
your shoes, you take off your
socks, then the good way to
invert that process is socks
back on first,
then shoes.
Sorry, okay.
I'm sorry that's on the tape.
And, of course,
on the other side we should
really just check -- on the
other side I have B inverse,
A inverse.
That does multiply A B,
and this time it's these guys
that give the identity,
squeeze down,
they give the identity,
we're in shape.
Okay.
So there's the inverse.
Good.
While we're at it,
let me do a transpose,
because the next lecture has
got a lot to -- involves
transposes.
So how do I -- if I transpose a
matrix,
I'm talking about square,
invertible matrices right now.
If I transpose one,
what's its inverse?
Well, the nice formula is --
let's see.
Let me start from A,
A inverse equal the identity.
So -- give me a first row.
And let me transpose both
sides.
That will bring a transpose
into the picture.
So if I transpose the identity
matrix, what do I have?
The identity,
right?
If I exchange rows and columns,
the identity is a symmetric
matrix.
It doesn't know the difference.
If I transpose these guys,
that product,
then again it turns out that I
have to reverse the order.
I can transpose them
separately, but when I multiply,
those transposes come in the
opposite order.
So it's A inverse transpose
times A transpose giving the
identity.
So that's -- this equation is
-- just comes directly from that
one.
But this equation tells me what
I wanted to know,
namely what is the inverse of
this guy A transpose?
What's the inverse of that --
if I transpose a matrix,
what'ss the inverse of the
result?
And this equation tells me that
here it is.
This is the inverse of A
transpose.
Inverse of A transpose.
Of A transpose.
So I'll put a big circle around
that, because that's the answer,
that's the best answer we could
hope for.
That if you want to know the
inverse of A transpose and you
know the inverse of A,
then you just transpose that.
So in a -- to put it another
way, transposing and inversing
you can do in either order for a
single matrix.
Okay.
So these are like basic facts
that we can now use,
all right -- so now I put it to
use.
I put it to use by thinking --
we're really completing,
the subject of elimination.
Actually, -- the thing about
elimination is it's the right
way to understand what the
matrix has got.
This A equal L U is the most
basic factorization of a matrix.
I always worry that you will
think this course is all
elimination.
It's just row operations.
And please don't.
We'll be beyond that,
but it's the right algebra to
do first.
Okay.
So, now I'm coming near the end
of it, but I want to get it in a
decent form.
So my decent form is matrix
form.
I have a matrix A,
let's suppose it's a good
matrix, I can do elimination,
no row exchanges --
So no row exchanges for now.
Pivots all fine,
nothing zero in the pivot
position.
I get to the very end,
which is U.
So I get from A to U.
And I want to know what's the
connection?
How is A related to U?
And this is going to tell me
that there's a matrix L that
connects them.
Okay.
Can I do it for a two by two
first?
Okay.
Two by two, elimination.
Okay, so I'll do it under here.
Okay.
So let my matrix A be --
We'll keep it simple,
say two and an eight,
so we know that the first pivot
is a two, and the multiplier's
going to be a four and then let
me put a one here and what
number do I not want to put
there?
Four.
I don't want a four there,
because in that case,
the second pivot would not --
we wouldn't have a second
pivot.
The matrix would be singular,
general screw-up.
Okay.
So let me put some other number
here like seven.
Okay.
Now I want to operate on that
with my elementary matrix.
So what's the elementary
matrix?
Strictly speaking,
it's E21, because it's the guy
that's going to produce a zero
in that position.
And it's going to produce U in
one shot, because it's just a
two by two matrix.
So two one and I'm going to
take four of those away from
those, produce that zero and
leave a three there.
And that's U.
And what's the matrix that did
it?
Quick review,
then.
What's the elimination
elementary matrix E21 -- it's
one zero, thanks.
And --
negative four one,
right.
Good.
Okay.
So that -- you see the
difference between this and what
I'm shooting for.
I'm shooting for A on one side
and the other matrices on the
other side of the equation.
Okay.
So I can do that right away.
Now here's going to be my A
equals L U.
And you won't have any trouble
telling me what -- so A is still
two one eight seven.
L is what you're going to tell
me and U is still two one zero
three.
Okay.
So what's L in this case?
Well, first -- so how is L
related to this E guy?
It's the inverse,
because I want to multiply
through by the inverse of this,
which will put the identity
here, and the inverse will show
up there and I'll call it L.
So what is the inverse of this?
Remember those elimination
matrices are easy to invert.
The inverse matrix for this one
is 1 0 4 1, it's actually flip
sign.
Okay.
Do you want -- if we did the
numbers right,
we must -- this should be
correct.
Okay.
And of course it is.
That says the first row's
right, four times the first row
plus the second row is eight
seven.
Good.
Okay.
That's simple,
two by two.
But it already shows the form
that we're headed for.
It shows -- so what's the L
stand for?
Why the letter L?
If U stood for upper
triangular, then of course L
stands for lower triangular.
And actually,
it has ones on the diagonal,
where this thing has the pivots
on the diagonal.
Oh, sometimes we may want to
separate out the pivots,
so can I just mention that
sometimes we could also write
this as -- we could have this
one zero four one -- I'll just
show you how I would divide out
this matrix of pivots -- two
three.
There's a diagonal matrix.
And I just -- whatever is left
is here.
Now what's left?
If I divide this first row by
two to pull out the two,
then I have a one and a one
half.
And if I divide the second row
by three to pull out the three,
then I have a one.
So if this is L U,
this is maybe called L D or
pivot U.
And now it's a little more
balanced, because we have ones
on the diagonal here and here.
And the diagonal matrix in the
middle.
So both of those...
Matlab would produce either
one.
I'll basically stay with L U.
Okay.
Now I have to think about
bigger than two by two.
But right now,
this was just like easy
exercise.
And, to tell the truth,
this one was a minus sign and
this one was a plus sign.
I mean, that's the only
difference.
But, with three by three,
there's a more significant
difference.
Let me show you how that works.
Let me move up to a three by
three, let's say some matrix A,
okay?
Let's imagine it's three by
three.
I won't write numbers down for
now.
So what's the first elimination
step that I do,
the first matrix I multiply it
by, what letter will I use for
that?
It'll be E two one,
because it's --
the first step will be to get a
zero in that two one position.
And then the next step will be
to get a zero in the three one
position.
And the final step will be to
get a zero in the three two
position.
That's what elimination is,
and it produced U.
And again, no row exchanges.
I'm taking the nice case,
now, the typical case,
too -- when I don't have to do
any row exchange,
all I do is these elimination
steps.
Okay.
Now, suppose I want that stuff
over on the right-hand side,
as I really do.
That's, like,
my point here.
I can multiply these together
to get a matrix E,
but I want it over on the
right.
I want its inverse over there.
So what's the right expression
now?
If I write A and U,
what goes there?
Okay.
So I've got the inverse of
this, I've got three matrices in
a row now.
And it's their inverses that
are going to show up,
because each one is easy to
invert.
Question is,
what about the whole bunch?
How easy is it to invert the
whole bunch?
So, that's what we know how to
do.
We know how to invert,
we should take the separate
inverses, but they go in the
opposite order.
So what goes here?
E three two inverse,
right, because I'll multiply
from the left by E three two
inverse, then I'll pop it up
next to U.
And then will come E three one
inverse.
And then this'll be the only
guy left standing and that's
gone when Ido an E two one
inverse.
So there is L.
That's L U.
L is product of inverses.
Now you still can ask why is
this guy preferring inverses?
And let me explain why.
Let me explain why is this
product nicer than this one?
This product turns out to be
better than this one.
Let me take a typical case
here.
Let me take a typical case.
So let me -- I have to do three
by three for you to see the
improvement.
Two by two, it was just one E,
no problem.
But let me go up to this case.
Suppose my matrices E21 --
suppose E21 has a minus two in
there.
Suppose that -- and now suppose
-- oh, I'll even suppose E31 is
the identity.
I'm going to make the point
with just a couple of these.
Okay.
Now this guy will have -- do
something -- now let's suppose
minus five one.
Okay.
There's typical.
That's a typical case in which
we didn't need an E31.
Maybe we already had a zero in
that three one position.
Okay.
Let me see -- is that going to
be enough to,
show my point?
Let me do that multiplication.
Okay.
So if I do that multiplication
it's like good practice to
multiply these matrices.
Tell me what's above the
diagonal when I do this
multiplication?
All zeroes.
When I do this multiplication,
I'm going to get ones on the
diagonal and zeroes above.
Because -- what does that say?
That says that I'm subtracting
rows from lower rows.
So nothing is moving upwards as
it did last time in
Gauss-Jordan.
Okay.
Now -- so really,
what I have to do is check this
minus two one zero,
now this is -- what's that
number?
This is the number that I'm
really have in mind.
That number is ten.
And this one is -- what goes
here?
Row three against column two,
it looks like the minus five.
It's that ten.
How did that ten get in there?
I don't like that ten.
I mean -- of course,
I don't want to erase it,
because it's right.
But I don't want it there.
It's because -- the ten got in
there because I subtracted two
of row one from row two,
and then I subtracted five of
that new row two from row three.
So doing it in that order,
how did row one effect row
three?
Well, it did,
because two of it got removed
from row two and then five of
those got removed from row
three.
So altogether ten of row one
got thrown into row three.
Now my point is in the reverse
direction -- so now I can do it
-- below it I'll do the
inverses.
Okay.
And, of course,
opposite order.
Reverse order.
Okay.
So now this is going to -- this
is the E that goes on the left
side.
Left of A.
Now I'm going to do the
inverses in the opposite order,
so what's the --
So the opposite order means I
put this inverse first.
And what is its inverse?
What's the inverse of E21?
Same thing with a plus sign,
right?
For the individual matrices,
instead of taking away two I
add back two of row one to row
two, so no problem.
And now, in reverse order,
I want to invert that.
Just right?
I'm doing just this,
this.
So now the inverse is again the
same thing, but add in the five.
And now I'll do that
multiplication and I'll get a
happy result.
I hope.
Did I do it right so far?
Yes, okay.
Let me do the multiplication.
I believe this comes out.
So row one of the answer is one
zero zero.
Oh, I know that all this is
going to be left,
right?
Then I have two one zero.
So I get two one zero there,
right?
And what's the third row?
What's the third row in this
product?
Just read it out to me,
the third row?
And this is my matrix L.
And it's the one that goes on
the left of U.
It goes into -- what do I mean
here?
Maybe rather than saying left
of A, left of U,
let me right down again what I
mean.
E A is U, whereas A is L U.
Okay.
Let me make the point now in
words.
The order that the matrices
come for L is the right order.
The two and the five don't sort
of interfere to produce this ten
in the right order,
the multipliers just sit in the
matrix L.
That's the point -- that if I
want to know L,
I have no work to do.
I just keep a record of what
those multipliers were,
and that gives me L.
So I'll draw the -- let me say
it.
So this is the A=L U.
So if no row exchanges,
the multipliers that those
numbers that we multiplied rows
by and subtracted,
when we did an elimination step
-- the multipliers go directly
into L.
Okay.
So L is -- this is the way,
to look at elimination.
You go through the elimination
steps, and actually if you do it
right, you can throw away A as
you create L U.
If you think about it,
those steps of elimination,
as when you've finished with
row two of A,
you've created a new row two of
U, which you have to save,
and you've created the
multipliers that you used --
which you have to save,
and then you can forget A.
So because it's all there in L
and U.
So that's -- this moment is
maybe the new insight in
elimination that comes from
matrix --
doing it in matrix form.
So it was -- the product of Es
is -- we can't see what that
product of Es is.
The matrix E is not a
particularly attractive one.
What's great is when we put
them on the other side --
their inverses in the opposite
order, there the L comes out
just right.
Okay.
Now -- oh gosh,
so today's a sort of,
like, practical day.
Can we think together how
expensive is elimination?
How many operations do we do?
So this is now a kind of new
topic which I didn't list as --
on the program,
but here it came.
How many operations on an n by
n matrix A.
I mean, it's a very practical
question.
Can we solve systems of order a
thousand, in a second or a
minute or a week?
Can we solve systems of order a
million in a second or an hour
or a week?
I mean, what's the -- if it's n
by n, we often want to take n
bigger.
I mean, we've put in more
information.
We make the whole thing is more
accurate for the bigger matrix.
But it's more expensive,
too, and the question is how
much more expensive?
If I have matrices of order a
hundred.
Let's say a hundred by a
Let me take n to be a hundred.
Say n equal a hundred.
How many steps are we doing?
How many operations are we
actually doing that we --
And let's suppose there aren't
any zeroes, because of course if
a matrix has got a lot of zeroes
in good places,
we don't have to do those
operations, and,
it'll be much faster.
It's going to move -- it's
going to change all rows,
But -- so just think for a
moment about the first step.
So here's our matrix A,
hundred by a hundred.
And the first step will be --
that column, is got zeroes down
here.
So it's down to 99 by 99,
right?
That's really like the first
stage of elimination,
to get from this hundred by
hundred non-zero matrix to this
stage where the first pivot is
sitting up here and the first
row's okay the first column is
okay.
So, eventually -- how many
steps did that take?
You see, I'm trying to get an
idea.
Is the answer proportional to
n?
Is the total number of steps in
elimination, the total number,
is it proportional to n -- in
which case if I double n from a
hundred to two hundred -- does
it take me twice as long?
Does it square,
so it would take me four times
as long?
Does it cube so it would take
me eight times as long?
Or is it n factorial,
so it would take me a hundred
times as long?
I think, you know,
from a practical point of view,
we have to have some idea of
the cost, here.
So these are the questions that
I'm -- let me ask those
questions again.
Is it proportional -- does it
go like N, like N squared,
like N cubed -- or some higher
power of N?
Like N factorial where every
step up multiplies by a hundred
and then by a hundred and one
and then by a hundred and two --
which is it?
Okay, so that's the only way I
know to answer that is to think
through what we actually had to
do.
Okay.
So what was the cost here?
Well, let's see.
What do I mean by an operation?
I guess I mean,
well an addition or -- yeah.
No big deal.
I guess I mean an addition or a
subtraction or a multiplication
or a division.
Okay.
And actually,
what operation I doing all the
time?
When I multiply row one by
multiplier L and I subtract from
row six.
What's happening there
individually?
What's going on?
If I multiply -- I do a
multiplication by L and then a
subtraction.
So I guess operation -- Can I
count that for the moment as,
like, one operation?
Or you may want to count them
separately.
The typical operation is
multiply plus a subtract.
So if I count those together,
my answer's going to come out
half as many as if --
I mean, if I count them
separately, I'd have a certain
number of multiplies,
certain number of subtracts.
That's really want to do.
Okay.
How many have I got here?
So, I think -- let's see.
It's about -- well,
how many, roughly?
How many operations to get from
here to here?
Well, maybe one way to look at
it is all these numbers had to
get changed.
The first row didn't get
changed, but all the other rows
got changed at this step.
So this step -- well,
I guess maybe -- shall I say it
cost about a hundred squared.
I mean, if I had changed the
first row, then it would have
been exactly hundred squared,
because --
because that's how many numbers
are here.
A hundred squared numbers is
the total count of the entry,
and all but this insignificant
first row got changed.
So I would say about a hundred
squared.
Okay.
Now, what about the next step?
So now the first row is fine.
The second row is fine.
And I'm changing these zeroes
are all fine,
so what's up with the second
step?
And then you're with me.
Roughly, what's the cost?
If this first step cost a
hundred squared,
about, operations then this
one, which is really working on
this guy to produce this,
costs about what?
How many operations to fix?
About ninety-nine squared,
or ninety-nine times
ninety-eight.
But less, right?
Less, because our problem's
getting smaller.
About ninety-nine squared.
And then I go down and down and
the next one will be
ninety-eight squared,
the next ninety-seven squared
and finally I'm down around one
squared or --
where it's just like the little
numbers.
The big numbers are here.
So the number of operations is
about n squared plus that was n,
right?
n was a hundred?
n squared for the first step,
then n minus one squared,
then n minus two squared,
finally down to three squared
and two squared and even one
squared.
No way I should have written
that -- squeezed that in.
Let me try it so the count is N
squared plus N minus one squared
plus -- all the way down to one
squared.
That's a pretty decent count.
Admittedly, we didn't catch
every single tiny operation,
but we got the right leading
term here.
And what do those add up to?
Okay, so now we're coming to
the punch of this,
question, this operation count.
So the operations on the left
side, on the matrix A to finally
get to U.
And anybody -- so which of
these quantities is the right
ballpark for that count?
If I add a hundred squared to
ninety nine squared to ninety
eight squared --
ninety seven squared,
all the way down to two squared
then one squared,
what have I got,
about?
It's just one of these -- let's
identify it first.
Is it N?
Certainly not.
Is it n factorial?
No.
If it was n factorial,
we would -- with determinants,
it is n factorial.
I'll put in a bad mark against
determinants,
because that -- okay,
so what is it?
It's n -- well,
this is the answer.
It's this order -- n cubed.
It's like I have n terms,
right?
I've got n terms in this sum.
And the biggest one is N
squared.
So the worst it could be would
be n cubed, but it's not as bad
as -- it's N cubed times --
it's about one third of n
cubed.
That's the magic operation
count.
Somehow that one third takes
account of the fact that the
numbers are getting smaller.
If they weren't getting
smaller, we would have n terms
times n squared,
but it would be exactly n
cubed.
But our numbers are getting
smaller -- actually,
do you remember where does one
third come in this -- I'll even
allow a mention of calculus.
So calculus can be mentioned,
integration can be mentioned
now in the next minute and not
again for weeks.
It's not that I don't like
18.01, but18.06 is better.
Okay.
So, -- so what's -- what's the
calculus formula that looks
like?
It looks like -- if we were in
calculus instead of summing
stuff, we would integrate.
So I would integrate x squared
and I would get one third x
cubed.
So if that was like an integral
from one to N,
of x squared b x,
if the answer would be one
third n cubed --
and it's correct for the sum
also, because that's,
like, the whole point of
calculus.
The whole point of calculus is
-- oh, I don't want to tell you
the whole -- I mean,
you know the whole point of
calculus.
Calculus is like sums except
it's continuous.
Okay.
And algebra is discreet.
So the answer is one third n
cubed.
Now I'll just -- let me say one
more thing about operations.
What about the right-hand side?
This was what it cost on the
left side.
This is on A.
Because this is A that we're
working with.
But what's the cost on the
extra column vector b that we're
hanging around here?
So b costs a lot less,
obviously, because it's just
one column.
We carry it through elimination
and then actually we do back
substitution.
Let me just tell you the answer
there.
It's n squared.
So the cost for every right
hand side is n squared.
So let me -- I'll just fit that
in here --
for the the cost of b turns out
to be n squared.
So you see if we have,
as we often have,
a a matrix A and several
right-hand sides,
then we pay the price on A,
the higher price on A to get it
split up into L and U to do
elimination on A,
but then we can process every
right-hand side at low cost.
Okay.
So the -- We really have
discussed the most fundamental
algorithm for a system of
equations.
Okay.
So, I'm ready to allow row
exchanges.
I'm ready to allow -- now what
happens to this whole -- today's
lecture if there are row
exchanges?
When would there be row
There are row -- we need to do
row exchanges if a zero shows up
in the pivot position.
So moving then into the final
section of this chapter,
which is about transposes --
well, we've already seen some
transposes, and -- the title of
this section is,
"Transposes and Permutations."
Okay.
So can I say,
now, where does a permutation
come in?
Let me talk a little about
permutations.
So that'll be up here,
So these are the matrices that
I need to do row exchanges.
And I may have to do two row
exchanges.
Can you invent a matrix where I
would have to do two row
exchanges and then would come
out fine?
Yeah let's just,
for the heck of it -- so I'll
put it here.
Let me do three by threes.
Actually, why don't I just
plain list all the three by
three permutation matrices.
There're a nice little group of
them.
What are all the matrices that
exchange no rows at all?
Well, I'll include the
identity.
So that's a permutation matrix
that doesn't do anything.
Now what's the permutation
matrix that exchanges -- what is
P12?
The permutation matrix that
exchanges rows one and two would
be -- 0 1 0 -- 1 0 0,
right.
I just exchanged those rows of
the identity and I've got it.
Okay.
Actually, I'll -- yes.
Let me clutter this up.
Okay.
Give me a complete list of all
the row exchange matrices.
So what are they?
They're all the ways I can take
the identity matrix and
rearrange its rows.
How many will there be?
How many three by three
permutation matrices?
Shall we keep going and get the
answer?
So tell me some more.
What one are you going to do
now?
I'm going to switch rows one
and --
One and three,
okay.
leaving two alone.
Okay.
Now what else?
Switch -- what would be the
next easy one -- is switch two
and three, good.
So I'll leave one zero zero
alone and I'll switch --
I'll move number three up and
number two down.
Okay.
Those are the ones that just
exchange single -- a pair of
rows.
This guy, this guy and this guy
exchanges a pair of rows,
but now there are more
possibilities.
What's left?
So tell -- there is another one
here.
What's that?
right?
Where shall we put them?4
STUDENT: Zero one zero?
STRANG: Zero one zero.
Okay, now a second row -- say
zero zero one and the third guy
one zero zero.
So that is like a cycle.
That puts row two moves up to
row one, row three moves up to
row two and row one moves down
to row three.
And there's one more,
which is -- let's see.
What's left?
I'm lost.
STUDENT: Is it zero zero one?
STRANG: Okay.
STUDENT: One zero zero.
STRANG: One zero zero,
okay.
Zero one zero.
Okay.
Great.
Six.
Six of them.
Six P.
And they're sort of nice,
because what happens if I
write, multiply two of them
together?
If I multiply two of these
matrices together,
what can you tell me about the
answer?
It's on the list.
If I do some row exchanges and
then I do some more row
exchanges, then all together
I've done row exchanges.
So if I multiply -- but,
I don't know.
And if I invert,
then I'm just doing row
exchanges to get back again.
So the inverses are all there.
It's a little family of
matrices that -- they've got
their own -- if I multiply,
I'm still inside this group.
If I invert I'm inside this
group --
actually, group is the right
name for this subject.
It's a group of six matrices,
and what about the inverses?
What's the inverse of this guy,
for example?
What's the inverse -- if I
exchange rows one and two,
what's the inverse matrix?
Just tell me fast.
The inverse of that matrix is
-- if I exchange rows one and
two, then what I should do to
get back to where I started is
the same thing.
So this thing is its own
inverse.
That's probably its own
This is probably not --
actually, I think these are
inverses of each other.
Oh, yeah, actually -- the
inverse is the transpose.
There's a curious fact about
permutations matrices,
that the inverses are the
transposes.
And final moment -- how many
are there if I --
how many four by four
permutations?
So let me take four by four --
how many Ps?
Well, okay.
Make a good guess.
Twenty four,
right.
Twenty four Ps.
Okay.
So, we've got these permutation
matrices, and in the next
lecture, we'll use them.