OK.
This is linear algebra lecture
eleven.
And at the end of lecture ten,
I was talking about some vector
spaces, but they're -- the
things in those vector spaces
were not what we usually call
vectors.
Nevertheless,
you could add them and you
could multiply by numbers,
so we can call them vectors.
I think the example I was
working with they were matrices.
So the -- so we had like a
matrix space,
the space of all three by three
matrices.
And I'd like to just pick up on
that, because --
we've been so specific about n
dimensional space here,
and you really want to see that
the same ideas work as long as
you can add and multiply by
scalars.
So these new,
new vector spaces,
the example I took was the
space M of all three by three
matrices.
OK.
I can add them,
I can multiply by scalars.
I can multiply two of them
together, but I don't do that.
That's not part of the vector
space picture.
The vector space part is just
adding the matrices and
multiplying by numbers.
And that's fine,
we stay within this space of
three by three matrices.
And I had some subspaces that
were interesting,
like the symmetric,
the subspace of symmetric
matrices, symmetric three by
threes.
Or the subspace of upper
triangular three by threes.
Now I, I use the word subspace
because it follows the rule.
If I add two symmetric
matrices, I'm still symmetric.
If I multiply two symmetric
matrices, is the product
automatically symmetric?
No.
But I'm not multiplying
matrices.
I'm just adding.
So I'm fine.
This is a subspace.
Similarly, if I add two upper
triangular matrices,
I'm still upper triangular.
And, that's a subspace.
Now I just want to take these
as example and ask,
well, what's a basis for that
subspace?
What's the dimension of that
And what's bd- dimension of the
whole space?
So, there's a natural basis for
all three by three matrices,
and why don't we just write it
down.
So, so M, a basis for M.
Again, all three by threes.
OK.
And then I'll just count how
many members are in that basis
and I'll know the dimension.
And OK, it's going to take me a
little time.
In fact, what is the dimension?
Any idea of what I'm coming up
with next?
How many numbers does it take
to specify that three by three
matrix?
Nine.
Nine is the,
is the dimension I'm going to
find.
And the most obvious basis
would be the matrix that's that
matrix and then this matrix with
a one there and that's two of
them, shall I put in the third
one, and then onwards,
and the last one maybe would
end with the one.
OK.
That's like the standard basis.
In fact, our space is
practically the same as nine
dimensional space.
It's just the nine numbers are
written in a square instead of
in a column.
But somehow it's different and,
and ought to be thought of as
-- natural for itself.
Because now what about the
symmetric three by threes?
So that's a subspace.
Just let's just think,
what's the dimension of that
subspace and what's a basis for
that subspace.
OK.
And I guess this question
occurs to me.
If I look at this subspace of
symmetric three by threes,
well, how many of these
original basis members belong to
the subspace?
I think only three of them do.
This one is symmetric.
This last one is symmetric.
And the one in the middle with
a, with a one in that position
--
in the two two position,
would be symmetric.
But so I've got three of these
original nine are symmetric,
but, so this is an example
where -- but that's,
that's not all,
right?
What's the dimension?
Let's put the dimensions down.
Dimension of the,
of M, was nine.
What's the dimension of --
shall we call this S -- is what?
What's the dimension of this?
I'm sort of taking simple
examples where we can,
we can, spot the answer to
these questions.
So how many -- if I have a
symmetric --
think of all symmetric matrices
as a subspace,
how many parameters do I choose
in three by three symmetric
matrices?
Six, right.
If I choose the diagonal that's
three, and the three entries
above the diagonal,
then I know what the three
entries below.
So the dimension is six.
I guess what's the dimension of
this here?
Let's call this space U for
upper triangular.
So what's the dimension of that
space of all upper triangular
three by threes?
Again six.
And, but we haven't got a -- we
haven't seen -- well,
actually, maybe we have got a
basis here for,
the upper triangulars.
I guess six of these guys,
one, two, three,
four, and a,
and a couple more,
would be upper triangular.
So there's a accidental case
where the big basis contains in
it a basis for the subspace.
But with the symmetric guy,
it didn't have.
The symmetric guy the,
basis -- so you see -- a basis
is the basis for the big space,
we generally need to think it
all over again to get a basis
for the subspace.
And then how do I get other
subspaces?
Well, we spoke before about,
the subspace the symmetric
matrices and the upper
triangular.
This is symmetric and upper
OK.
What's the, what's the
dimension of that space?
Well, what's in that space?
So what's -- if a matrix is
symmetric and also upper
triangular, that makes it
diagonal.
So this is the same as the
diagonal matrices,
diagonal three by threes.
And the dimension of this,
of S intersect U,
right -- you're OK with that
symbol?
That's, that's the vectors that
are in both S and U,
and that's D.
So S intersect U is the
diagonals.
And the dimension of the
diagonal matrices is three.
And we've got a basis,
no problem.
OK, as I write that,
I think, OK,
what about putting -- so this
is like, this intersection --
is taking all the vectors that
are in both, that are symmetric
and also upper triangular.
Now we looked at the union.
Suppose I take the matrices
that are symmetric or upper
triangular.
What -- why was that no good?
So why is it no -- why I not
interested in the union,
putting together those two
subspaces?
So this, these are matrices
that are in S or in U,
or possibly both,
so they, the diagonals
included.
But what's bad about this?
It's not a subspace.
It's like having,
taking, you know,
a couple of lines in the plane
and stopping there.
A line -- this is -- so there's
a three dimensional subspace of
a nine dimensional space,
there's -- ooh,
sorry, six.
There's a six dimensional
subspace of a nine dimensional
space.
There's another one.
But they, they're headed in
different directions,
so we, we can't just put them
together.
We have to fill in.
So that's what we do.
To get this bigger space that
I'll write with a plus sign,
this is combinations of things
in S and things in U.
OK.
So that's the final space I'm
going to introduce.
I have a couple of subspaces.
I can take their intersection.
And now I'm interested in not
their union but their sum.
So this would be the,
this is the intersection,
and this will be their sum.
So what do I need for a
subspace here?
I take anything in S plus
anything in U.
I don't just take things that
are in S and pop in also,
separately, things that are in
U.
This is the sum of any element
of S, that is,
any symmetric matrix,
plus any in U,
any element of U.
OK.
Now as long as we've got an
example here,
tell me what we get.
If I take every symmetric
matrix, take all symmetric
matrices, and add them to all
upper triangular matrices,
then I've got a whole lot of
matrices and it is a subspace.
And what's -- it's a vector
space,
and what vector space would I
then have?
Any idea what,
what matrices can I get out of
a symmetric plus an upper
triangular?
I can get anything.
I get all matrices.
I get all three by threes.
It's worth thinking about that.
It's just like stretch your
mind a little,
just a little,
to, to think of these subspaces
and what their intersection is
and what their sum is.
And now can I give you a little
-- oh, well, let's figure out
the dimension.
So what's the dimension of S
plus U?
In this example is nine,
because we got all three by
threes.
So the original spaces had,
the original symmetric space
had dimension six and the
original upper triangular space
had dimension six.
And actually I'm seeing here a
nice formula.
That the dimension of S plus
the dimension of U -- if I have
two subspaces,
the dimension of one plus the
dimension of the other --
equals the dimension of their
intersection plus the dimension
of their sum.
Six plus six is three plus
nine.
That's kind of satisfying,
that these natural operations
-- and we've -- this is it,
actually, this is the set of
natural things to do with,
with subspaces.
That, the dimensions come out
in a good way.
OK.
Maybe I'll take just one more
example of a vector space that
doesn't have vectors in it.
It's come from differential
equations.
So this is a one more new
vector space that we'll give
just a few minutes to.
Suppose I have a differential
equation like d^2y/dx^2+ y=0.
OK.
I look at the solutions to that
equation.
So what are the solutions to
that equation?
y=cos(x) is a solution.
y=sin(x) is a solution.
y equals -- well,
e to the (ix) is a solution,
if you want,
if you allow me to put that in.
But why should I put that in?
It's already there.
You see, I'm really looking at
a null space here.
I'm looking at the null space
of a differential equation.
That's the solution space.
And describe the solution
space, all solutions to this
differential equation.
So the equation is y''+y=0.
Cosine's, cosine's a solution,
sine is a solution.
Now tell me all the solutions.
They're -- so I don't need
e^(ix).
Forget that.
What are all the complete
solutions?
Is what?
A combination of these.
The complete solution is y
equals some multiple of the
cosine plus some multiple of the
sine.
That's a vector space.
What's the dimension of that
space?
What's a basis for that space?
OK, let me ask you a basis
first.
If I take the set of solutions
to that second order
differential equation --
there it is,
those are the solutions.
What's a basis for that space?
Now remember,
what's the, what question I
asking?
Because if you know the
question I'm asking,
you'll see the answer.
A basis means all the guys in
the space are combinations of
these basis vectors.
Well, this is a basis.
sin x, cos x there is a basis.
Those two -- they're like the
special solutions,
right?
We had special solutions to
Ax=b.
Now we've got special solutions
to differential equations.
Sorry, we had special solutions
to Ax=0, I misspoke.
The special solutions were for
the null space just as here
we're talking about the null
space.
Do you see that here is a --
those two -- and what's the
dimension of the solution space?
How many vectors in this basis?
Two, the sine and cosine.
Are those the only basis for
this space?
By no means.
e^(ix) and e^(-ix) would be
another basis.
Lots of bases.
But do you see that really what
a course in differential --
in linear differential
equations is about is finding a
basis for the solution space.
The dimension of the solution
space will always be -- will be
two, because we have a second
order equation.
So that's, like there's 18.03
in --
five minutes of 18.06 is enough
to, to take care of 18.03.
OK.
So there's a -- that's one more
example.
And of course the point of the
example is these things don't
look like vectors.
They look like functions.
But we can call them vectors,
because we can add them and we
can multiply by constants,
so we can take linear
combinations.
That's all we have to be
allowed to do.
So that's really why this idea
of linear algebra and basis and
dimension and so on plays a
wider role than --
our constant discussions of m
by n matrices.
OK.
That's what I wanted to say
about that topic.
Now of course the key,
number associated with
matrices, to go back to that
number, is the rank.
And the rank,
what do we know about the rank?
Well, we know it's not bigger
than m and it's not bigger than
n.
So but I'd like to have a
little discussion on the rank.
Maybe I'll put that here.
So I'm picking up this topic of
rank one matrices.
And the reason I'm interested
in rank one matrices is that
they ought to be simple.
If the rank is only one,
the matrix can't get away from
us.
So for example,
let me take -- let me create a
rank one matrix.
OK.
Suppose it's three -- suppose
it's two by three.
And let me give you the first
row.
What can the second row be?
Tell me a possible second row
here, for, for this matrix to
have rank one.
A possible second row is?
Two eight ten.
The second row is a multiple of
the first row.
It's not independent.
So tell me a basis for the --
oh yeah, sorry to keep bringing
up these same questions.
After the quiz I'll stop,
but for now,
tell me a basis for the row
space.
A basis for the row space of
that matrix is the first row,
right?
The first row,
one four five.
A basis for the column space of
this matrix is?
What's the dimension of the
column space?
The dimension of the column
space is also one,
right?
Because it's also the rank.
The dimension -- you remember
the dimension of the column
space equals the rank equals the
dimension of the column space of
the transpose,
which is the row space of A.
OK, and in this case it's one,
r is one.
And sure enough,
all the columns are -- all the
other columns are multiples of
that column.
Now there's -- there ought to
be a nice way to see that,
and here it is.
I can write that matrix as its
pivot column,
one two, times its -- times one
four five.
A column times a row,
one column times one row gives
me a matrix, right?
If I multiply a column by a
row, that, g- that's a two by
one matrix times a one by three
matrix, and the result of the
multiplication is two by three.
And it comes out right.
So what I want to -- my point
is the rank one matrices that
every rank one matrix has the
form some column times some row.
So U is a column vector,
V is a column vector --
but I make it into a row by
putting in V transpose.
So that's the -- complete
picture of rank one matrices.
We'll be interested in rank one
matrices.
Later we'll find,
oh, their determinant,
that'll be easy,
their eigenvalues,
that'll be interesting.
Rank one matrices are like the
building blocks for all
matrices.
And actually maybe you can
guess.
If I took any matrix,
a five by seventeen matrix of
rank four, then it seems pretty
likely --
and it's true,
that I could break that five by
seventeen matrix down as a
combination of rank one
matrices.
And probably how many of those
would I need?
If I have a five by seventeen
matrix of rank four,
I'll need four of them,
right.
Four rank one matrices.
So the rank one matrices are
the, are the building blocks.
And out -- I can produce every,
I can produce every five by --
every rank four matrix out of
four rank one matrices.
OK.
That brings me to a question,
of course.
Would the rank four matrices
form a subspace?
Let me take all five by
seventeen matrices and think
about rank four -- the subset of
rank four matrices.
Let me -- I'll write this down.
You seem I'm reviewing for the
quiz, because I'm asking the
kind of questions that are short
enough but --
that bring out do you know what
these words mean.
So I take -- my matrix space M
now is all five by seventeen
matrices.
And now the question I ask is
the subset of,
of rank four matrices,
is that a subspace?
If I add a matrix of --
so if I multiply a matrix of
rank four by -- of rank four or
less, let's say,
because I have to let the zero
matrix in if it's going to be a
subspace.
But, but that doesn't just
because the zero matrix got in
there doesn't mean I have a
subspace.
So if I -- so the,
the question really comes down
to --
if I add two rank four
matrices, is the sum rank four?
What do you think?
If -- no, not usually.
Not usually.
If I add two rank four
matrices, the sum is probably --
what could I say about the sum?
Well, actually,
well, the rank could be five.
It's a general fact,
actually, that the rank of A
plus B can't be more than rank
of A plus the rank of B.
So this would say if I added
two of those,
the rank couldn't be larger
than eight, but I know actually
the rank couldn't be as large as
eight anyway.
What -- how big could the rank
be, for, for the rank of a
matrix in M?
Could be as large as five,
right, right.
So they're all sort of natural
ideas.
So it's rank four matrices or
rank one matrices -- let me,
let me change that to rank one.
Let me take the subset of rank
one matrices.
Is that a vector space?
If I add a rank one matrix to a
rank one matrix?
No.
It's most likely going to have
rank two.
So this is -- So I'll just make
that point.
Not a subspace.
OK.
Those are topics that I wanted
to, just fill out the,
the previous lectures.
The I'll ask one more subspace
question, a, a more,
a more, likely example.
Suppose I'm in -- let me put,
put this example on a new
board.
Suppose I'm in R,
in R^4.
So my typical vector in R^4 has
four components,
v1, v2, v3, and v4.
Suppose I take the subspace of
vectors whose components add to
zero.
So I let S be all v,
all vectors v in four
dimensional space with
v1+v2+v3+v4=0.
So I just want to consider that
bunch of vectors.
Is it a subspace,
first of all?
It is a subspace.
What's -- how do we see that?
I -- formally I should check.
If I have one vector that with
whose components add to zero and
I multiply that vector by six --
the components still add to
zero, just six times as -- six
times zero.
If I have a couple of v and a w
and I add them,
the, the components still add
to zero.
OK, it's a subspace.
What's the dimension of that
space and what's a basis for
that space?
So you see how I can just
describe a space and we --
we can ask for the dimension --
ask for the basis first and the
dimension.
Of course, the dimension's the
one that's easy to tell me in a
single word.
What's the dimension of our
subspace S here?
And a basis tell me -- some
vectors in it.
Well, I'm going to make ask you
again to guess the dimension.
Again I think I heard it.
Three.
The dimension is three.
Now how does this connect to
our Ax=0?
Is this the null space of
something?
Is that the null space of a
matrix?
And then we can look at the
matrix and, and we know
everything about those
subspaces.
This is the null space of what
matrix?
What's the matrix where the
null space is then Ab=0.
So I want this equation to be
Ab=0.
b is now the vector.
And what's the matrix that,
that we're seeing there?
It's the matrix of four ones.
Do you see that that's -- that
if I look at Ab=0 for this
matrix A, I multiply by b and I
get this requirement,
that the components add to
zero.
So I'm really when I speak
about S --
I'm speaking about the null
space of that matrix.
OK.
Let's just say we've got a
matrix now, we want its null
space.
Well, we -- tell me its rank
first.
The rank of that matrix is one,
thanks.
So r is one.
What's the general formula for
the dimension of the null space?
The dimension of the null space
of a matrix is -- in general,
an m by n matrix of rank r?
How many independent guys in
the null space?
n-r, right?
n-r.
In this case,
n is four, four columns.
The rank is one,
so the null space is three
dimensions.
So of course y- you could see
it in this case,
but you can also see it here in
our systematic way of dealing
with the four fundamental
subspaces of a matrix.
So what actually what,
what are all four subspaces
then?
The row space is clear.
The row space is in R^4.
Yeah, can we take the four
fundamental subspaces of this
matrix?
Let's just kill this example.
The row space is one
dimensional.
It's all multiples of that,
of that row.
The null space is three
dimensional.
Oh, you better give me a basis
for the null space.
So what's a basis for the null
space?
The special solutions.
To find the special solutions,
I look for the free variables.
The free variables here are --
there's the pivot.
The free variables are two,
three, and four.
So the basis,
basis for S,
for S will be -- I'm expecting
three vectors,
three special solutions.
I give the value one to that
free variable,
and what's the pivot variable
if the --
this is going to be a vector in
S?
Minus one.
Now they're always added to --
the entries add to zero.
The second special solution has
a one in the second free
variable, and again a minus one
makes it right.
The third one has a one in the
third free variable,
and again a minus one makes it
right.
That's my answer.
That's the answer I would be
looking for.
The -- a basis for this
subspace S, you would just list
three vectors,
and those would be the natural
three to list.
Not the only possible three,
but those are the special
three.
OK, tell me about the column
space, What's the column space
of this matrix A?
So the column space is a
subspace of R^1,
because m is only one.
The columns only have one
component.
So the column space of S,
the column space of A is
somewhere in the space R^1,
because we only have --
these columns are short.
And what is the column space
actually?
I just, it's just talking with
these words is what I'm doing.
The column space for that
matrix is R^1.
matrix is all multiples of that
column.
And all multiples give you all
of R^1.
And what's the,
the remaining fourth space,
the null space of A transpose
is what?
So we transpose A.
We look for combinations of the
columns now that give zero for A
transpose.
And there aren't any.
The only thing,
the only combination of these
rows to give the zero row is the
zero combination.
OK.
So let's just check dimensions.
The null space has dimension
three.
The row space has dimension
one.
Three plus one is four.
The column space has dimension
one, and what's the dimension of
this, like, smallest possible
space?
What's the dimension of the
zero space?
It's a subspace.
Zero.
What else could it be?
I mean, let's -- we have to
take a reasonable answer --
and the only reasonable answer
is zero.
So one plus zero gives -- this
was n, the number of columns,
and this is m,
the number of rows.
And let's just,
let me just say again then the,
the, the subspace that has only
that one point,
that point is zero dimensional,
of course.
And the basis is empty,
because if the dimension is
zero, there shouldn't be anybody
in the basis.
So the basis of that smallest
subspace is the empty set.
And the number of members in
the empty set is zero,
so that's the dimension.
OK.
Good.
Now I have just five minutes to
tell you about -- well,
actually, about some,
some, some, this is now,
this last topic of small world
graphs, and leads into,
a lecture about graphs and
linear algebra.
But let me tell you -- in these
last minutes the graph that I
interested in.
It's the graph where -- so what
is a graph?
Better tell you that first.
OK.
What's a graph?
This isn't calculus.
We're not, I'm not thinking of,
like, some sine curve.
The word graph is used in a
completely different way.
It's a set of,
a bunch of nodes and edges,
edges connecting the nodes.
So I have nodes like five nodes
and edges -- I'll put in some
edges, I could put,
include them all.
There's -- well,
let me put in a couple more.
There's a graph with five nodes
and one two three four five six
edges.
And some five by six matrix is
going to tell us everything
about that graph.
Let me leave that matrix to
next time and tell you about the
question I'm interested in.
Suppose, suppose the graph
isn't just, just doesn't have
just five nodes,
but suppose every,
suppose every person in this
room is a node.
And suppose there's an edge
between two nodes if those two
people are friends.
So have I described a graph?
It's a pretty big graph,
hundred, hundred nodes.
And I don't know how many edges
are in there.
There's an edge if you're
friends.
So that's the graph for this
class.
A, a similar graph you could
take for the whole country,
so two hundred and sixty
million nodes.
And edges between friends.
And the question for that graph
is how many steps does it take
to get from anybody to anybody?
What two people are furthest
apart in this friendship graph,
say for the US?
By furthest apart,
I mean the distance from --
well, I'll tell you my distance
to Clinton.
It's two.
I happened to go to college
with somebody who knows Clinton.
I don't know him.
So my distance to Clinton is
not one, because I don't,
happily or not,
don't know him.
But I know somebody who does.
He's a Senator and so I presume
he knows him.
OK.
I don't know what your -- well,
what's your distance to
Clinton?
Well, not more than three,
right.
Actually, true.
You know me.
I take credit for reducing your
Clinton distance to three --
what's your distance to Monica.
Not, anybody below -- below
four is in trouble here.
Or maybe three,
but, right.
So -- and what's Hillary's
distance to Monica?
I don't think we'd better put
that on tape here.
That's one or two,
I guess.
Is that right?
I don't -- well,
we won't, think more about
that.
So actually,
the, the real question is what
are large distances?
How, how far apart could people
be separated?
And roughly this number six
degrees of separation has kind
of appeared as the movie title,
as the book title,
and it's with this meaning.
That roughly speaking --
six might be a fairly -- not
too many people.
If you sit next to somebody on
an airplane, you get talking to
them.
You begin to discuss mutual
friends to sort of find out,
OK, what connections do you
have, and very often you'll find
you're connected in,
like, two or three or four
steps.
And you remark,
it's a small world,
and that's how this expression
small world came up.
But six, I don't know if you
could find -- if it took six,
I don't know if you would
successfully discover those six
in a, in an airplane
conversation.
But here's the math question,
and I'll leave it for next,
for lecture twelve,
and do a lot of linear algebra
in lecture twelve.
But the interesting point is
that with a few shortcuts,
the distances come down
dramatically.
That, I mean,
all your distances to Clinton
immediately drop to three by
taking linear algebra.
That's, like,
an extra bonus for taking
linear algebra.
And to understand
mathematically what it is about
these graphs --
or like the graphs of the World
Wide Web.
There's a fantastic graph.
So many people would like to
understand and model the web.
What the -- where the edges are
links and the nodes are,
sites, websites.
I'll leave you with that graph,
and I'll see you --
have a good weekend,
and see you on Monday.