Okay.
This is the lecture on the
singular value decomposition.
But everybody calls it the SVD.
So this is the final and best
factorization of a matrix.
Let me tell you what's coming.
The factors will be,
orthogonal matrix,
diagonal matrix,
orthogonal matrix.
So it's things that we've seen
before, these special good
matrices, orthogonal diagonal.
The new point is that we need
two orthogonal matrices.
A can be any matrix whatsoever.
Any matrix whatsoever has this
singular value decomposition,
so a diagonal one in the
middle, but I need two different
-- probably different orthogonal
matrices to be able to do this.
Okay.
And this factorization has
jumped into importance and is
properly, I think,
maybe the bringing together of
everything in this course.
One thing we'll bring together
is the very good family of
matrices that we just studied,
symmetric, positive,
definite.
Do you remember the stories
with those guys?
Because they were symmetric,
their eigenvectors were
orthogonal, so I could produce
an orthogonal matrix -- this is
my usual one.
My usual one is the
eigenvectors and eigenvalues
In the symmetric case,
the eigenvectors are
orthogonal, so I've got the good
-- my ordinary s has become an
especially good Q.
And positive definite,
my ordinary lambda has become a
positive lambda.
So that's the singular value
decomposition in case our matrix
is symmetric positive definite
-- in that case,
I don't need two -- U and a V
-- one orthogonal matrix will do
for both sides.
So this would be no good in
general, because usually the
eigenvector matrix isn't
orthogonal.
So that's not what I'm after.
I'm looking for orthogonal
times diagonal times orthogonal.
And let me show you what that
means and where it comes from.
Okay.
What does it mean?
You remember the picture of any
linear transformation.
This was, like,
the most important figure in
And what I looking for now?
A typical vector in the row
space
-- typical vector,
let me call it v1,
gets taken over to some vector
in the column space,
say u1.
So u1 is Av1.
Okay.
Now, another vector gets taken
over here somewhere.
What I looking for?
In this SVD,
this singular value
decomposition,
what I'm looking for is an
orthogonal basis here that gets
knocked over into an orthogonal
basis over there.
See that's pretty special,
to have an orthogonal basis in
the row space that goes over
into an orthogonal basis --
so this is like a right angle
and this is a right angle --
into an orthogonal basis in the
column space.
So that's our goal,
is to find -- do you see how
things are coming together?
First of all,
can I find an orthogonal basis
for this row space?
Of course.
No big deal to find an
orthogonal basis.
Graham Schmidt tells me how to
do it.
Start with any old basis and
grind through Graham Schmidt,
out comes an orthogonal basis.
But then, if I just take any
old orthogonal basis,
then when I multiply by A,
there's no reason why it should
be orthogonal over here.
So I'm looking for this special
set up where A takes these basis
vectors into orthogonal vectors
over there.
Now, you might have noticed
that the null space I didn't
include.
Why don't I stick that in?
You remember our usual figure
had a little null space and a
little null space.
And those are no problems.
Those null spaces are going to
show up as zeroes on the
diagonal of sigma,
so that doesn't present any
difficulty.
Our difficulty is to find
these.
So do you see what this will
mean?
This will mean that A times
these v-s, v1,
v2, up to -- what's the
dimension of this row space?
Vr.
Sorry, make that V a little
smaller -- up to vr.
So that's -- Av1 is going to be
the first column,
so here's what I'm achieving.
Oh, I'm not only going to make
these orthogonal,
but why not make them
orthonormal?
Make them unit vectors.
So maybe the unit vector is
here, is the u1,
and this might be a multiple of
it.
So really, what's happening is
Av1 is some multiple of u1,
right?
These guys will be unit vectors
and they'll go over into
multiples of unit vectors and
the multiple I'm not going to
call lambda anymore.
I'm calling it sigma.
So that's the number -- the
stretching number.
And similarly,
Av2 is sigma two u2.
This is my goal.
And now I want to express that
goal in matrix language.
That's the usual step.
Think of what you want and then
express it as a matrix
multiplication.
So Av1 is sigma one u1 --
actually, here we go.
Let me pull out these -- u1,
u2 to ur and then a matrix with
the sigmas.
Everything now is going to be
in that little part of the
blackboard.
Do you see that this equation
says what I'm trying to do with
my figure.
A times the first basis vector
should be sigma one times the
other basis -- the other first
basis vector.
These are the basis vectors in
the row space,
these are the basis vectors in
the column space and these are
the multiplying factors.
So Av2 is sigma two times u2,
Avr is sigma r times ur.
And then we've got a whole lot
of zeroes and maybe some zeroes
at the end, but that's the heart
of it.
And now if I express that in --
as matrices, because you knew
that was coming -- that's what I
have.
So, this is my goal,
to find an orthogonal basis in
the orthonormal,
even -- basis in the row space
and an orthonormal basis in the
column space so that I've sort
of diagonalized the matrix.
The matrix A is,
like, getting converted to this
diagonal matrix sigma.
And you notice that usually I
have to allow myself two
different bases.
My little comment about
symmetric positive definite was
the one case where it's A Q
equal Q sigma,
where V and U are the same Q.
But mostly, you know,
I'm going to take a matrix like
-- oh, let me take a matrix like
four four minus three three.
Okay.
There's a two by two matrix.
It's invertible,
so it has rank two.
So I'm going to look for two
vectors, v1 and v2 in the row
space, and U -- so I'm going to
look for v1, v2 in the row
space, which of course is R^2.
And I'm going to look for u1,
u2 in the column space,
which of course is also R^2,
and I'm going to look for
numbers sigma one and sigma two
so that it all comes out right.
So these guys are orthonormal,
these guys are orthonormal and
these are the scaling factors.
So I'll do that example as soon
as I get the matrix picture
straight.
Okay.
Do you see that this expresses
what I want?
Can I just say two words about
null spaces?
If there's some null space,
then we want to stick in a
basis for those,
for that.
So here comes a basis for the
null space, v(r+1) down to vm.
So if we only had an r
dimensional row space and the
other n-r dimensions were in the
null space --
okay, we'll take an orthogonal
-- orthonormal basis there.
No problem.
And then we'll just get zeroes.
So, actually,
w- those zeroes will come out
on the diagonal matrix.
So I'll complete that to an
orthonormal basis for the whole
space, R^m.
I complete this to an
orthonormal basis for the whole
space R^n and I complete that
with zeroes.
Null spaces are no problem
here.
So really the true problem is
in a matrix like that,
which isn't symmetric,
so I can't use its
eigenvectors,
they're not orthogonal -- but
somehow I have to get these
orthogonal --
in fact, orthonormal guys that
make it work.
I have to find these
orthonormal guys,
these orthonormal guys and I
want Av1 to be sigma one u1 and
Av2 to be sigma two u2.
Okay.
That's my goal.
Here's the matrices that are
going to get me there.
Now these are orthogonal
matrices.
I can put that -- if I multiply
on both sides by V inverse,
I have A equals U sigma V
inverse, and of course you know
the other way I can write V
inverse.
This is one of those square
orthogonal matrices,
so it's the same as U sigma V
transpose.
Okay.
Here's my problem.
I've got two orthogonal
matrices here.
And I don't want to find them
both at once.
So I want to cook up some
expression that will make the Us
disappear.
I would like to make the Us
disappear and leave me only with
the Vs.
And here's how to do it.
It's the same combination that
keeps showing up whenever we
have a general rectangular
matrix, then it's A transpose A,
that's the great matrix.
That's the great matrix.
That's the matrix that's
symmetric, and in fact positive
definite or at least positive
semi-definite.
This is the matrix with nice
properties, so let's see what
will it be?
So if I took the transpose,
then, I would have -- A
transpose A will be what?
What do I have?
If I transpose that I have V
sigma transpose U transpose,
that's the A transpose.
Now the A -- and what have I
got?
Looks like worse,
because it's got six things now
together, but it's going to
collapse into something good.
What does U transpose U
collapse into?
I, the identity.
So that's the key point.
This is the identity and we
don't have U anymore.
And sigma transpose times
sigma, those are diagonal
matrixes, so their product is
just going to have sigma
squareds on the diagonal.
So do you see what we've got
here?
This is V times this easy
matrix sigma one squared sigma
two squared times V transpose.
This is the A transpose A.
This is -- let me copy down --
A transpose A is that.
Us are out of the picture,
now.
I'm only having to choose the
Vs, and what are these Vs?
And what are these sigmas?
Do you know what the Vs are?
They're the eigenvectors that
-- see, this is a perfect
eigenvector, eigenvalue,
Q lambda Q transpose for the
matrix A transpose A.
A itself is nothing special.
But A transpose A will be
special.
It'll be symmetric positive
definite, so this will be its
eigenvectors and this'll be its
eigenvalues.
And the eigenvalues'll be
positive because this thing's
positive definite.
So this is my method.
This tells me what the Vs are.
And how I going to find the Us?
Well, one way would be to look
at A A transpose.
Multiply A by A transpose in
the opposite order.
That will stick the Vs in the
middle, knock them out,
and leave me with the Us.
So here's the overall picture,
then.
The Vs are the eigenvectors of
A transpose A.
The Us are the eigenvectors of
A A transpose,
which are different.
And the sigmas are the square
roots of these and the positive
square roots,
so we have positive sigmas.
Let me do it for that example.
This is really what you should
know and be able to do for the
SVD.
Okay.
Let me take that matrix.
So what's my first step?
Compute A transpose A,
because I want its
eigenvectors.
Okay.
So I have to compute A
transpose A.
So A transpose is four four
minus three three,
and A is four four minus three
three, and I do that
multiplication and I get sixteen
-- I get twenty five -- I get
sixteen minus nine -- is that
seven?
And it better come out
symmetric.
And -- oh, okay,
and then it comes out 25.
Okay.
So, I want its eigenvectors and
its eigenvalues.
Its eigenvectors will be the
Vs, its eigenvalues will be the
squares of the sigmas.
Okay.
What are the eigenvalues and
eigenvectors of this guy?
Have you seen that two by two
example enough to recognize that
the eigenvectors are -- that one
one is an eigenvector?
So this here is A transpose A.
I'm looking for its
eigenvectors.
So its eigenvectors,
I think, are one one and one
minus one, because if I multiply
that matrix by one one,
what do I get?
If I multiply that matrix by
one one, I get 32 32,
which is 32 of one one.
So there's the first
eigenvector, and there's the
eigenvalue for A transpose A.
So I'm going to take its square
root for sigma.
Okay.
What's the eigenvector that
goes -- eigenvalue that goes
with this one?
If I do that multiplication,
what do I get?
I get some multiple of one
minus one, and what is that
multiple?
Looks like 18.
Okay.
So those are the two
eigenvectors,
but -- oh, just a moment,
I didn't normalize them.
To make everything absolutely
right, I ought to normalize
these eigenvectors,
divide by their length,
square root of two.
So all these guys should be
true unit vectors and,
of course, that normalization
didn't change the 32 and the 18.
Okay.
So I'm happy with the Vs.
Here are the Vs.
So now let me put together the
pieces here.
Here's my A.
Let me write down A again.
If life is right,
we should get U,
which I don't yet know -- U I
don't yet know,
sigma I do now know.
What's sigma?
So I'm looking for a U sigma V
transpose.
U, the diagonal guy and V
Okay.
Let's just see that come out
right.
So what are the sigmas?
They're the square roots of
these things.
So square root of 32 and square
root of 18.
Zero zero.
Okay.
What are the Vs?
They're these two.
And I have to transpose --
maybe that just leaves me with
ones --
with one over square root of
two in that row and the other
one is one over square root of
two minus one over square root
of two.
Now finally,
I've got to know the Us.
Well, actually,
one way to do -- since I now
know all the other pieces,
I could put those together and
figure out what the Us are.
But let me do it the A A
transpose way.
Okay.
Find the Us now.
u1 and u2.
And what are they?
I look at A A transpose -- so A
is supposed to be U sigma V
transpose, and then when I
transpose that I get V sigma
transpose U transpose.
So I'm just doing it in the
opposite order,
A times A transpose,
and what's the good part here?
That in the middle,
V transpose V is going to be
the identity.
So this is just U sigma sigma
transpose, that's some diagonal
matrix with sigma squareds and U
transpose.
So what I seeing here?
I'm seeing here,
again, a symmetric positive
definite or at least
semi-definite matrix and I'm
seeing its eigenvectors and its
eigenvalues.
So if I compute A A transpose,
its eigenvectors will be the
things that go into U.
Okay, so I need to compute A A
transpose.
I guess I'm going to have to go
-- can I move that up just a
little?
Maybe a little more and do A A
transpose.
So what's A?
Four four minus three and
three.
And what's A transpose?
Four four minus three and
three.
And when I do that
multiplication,
what do I get?
Sixteen and sixteen,
thirty two.
Uh, that one comes out zero.
Oh, so this is a lucky case and
that one comes out 18.
So this is an accident that A A
transpose happens to come out
diagonal, so we know easily its
eigenvectors and eigenvalues.
So its eigenvectors -- what's
the first eigenvector for this A
A transpose matrix?
It's just one zero,
and when I do that
multiplication,
I get 32 times one zero.
And the other eigenvector is
just zero one and when I
multiply by that I get 18.
So this is A A transpose.
Multiplying that gives me the
32 A A transpose.
Multiplying this guy gives me
First of all,
I got 32 and 18 again.
Am I surprised?
You know, it's clearly not an
accident.
The eigenvalues of A A
transpose were exactly the same
as the eigenvalues of -- this
one was A transpose A.
That's no surprise at all.
The eigenvalues of A B are the
same as the eigenvalues of B A.
That's a very nice fact,
that eigenvalues stay the same
if I switch the order of
multiplication.
So no surprise to see 32 and
What I learned -- first the
check that things were
numerically correct,
but now I've learned these
eigenvectors,
and actually they're about as
nice as can be.
They're the best orthogonal
matrix, just the identity.
Okay.
So my claim is that it ought to
all fit together,
that these numbers should come
out right.
The numbers should come out
right because the matrix
multiplications use the
properties that we want.
Okay.
Shall we just check that?
Here's the identity,
so not doing anything -- square
root of 32 is multiplying that
row, so that square root of 32
divided by square root of two
means square root of 16,
four, correct?
And square root of 18 is
divided by square root of two,
so that leaves me square root
of 9, which is three,
but --
well, Professor Strang,
you see the problem?
Why is that -- okay.
Why I getting minus three three
here and here I'm getting three
minus three?
Phooey.
I don't know why.
It shouldn't have happened,
but it did.
Now, okay, you could say,
well, just -- the eigenvector
there could have -- I could have
had the minus sign here for that
eigenvector, but I'm not happy
about that.
Hmm.
Okay.
So I realize there's a little
catch here somewhere and I may
not see it until Wednesday.
Which then gives you a very
important reason to come back on
Wednesday, to catch that sine
difference.
So what did I do illegally?
I think I put the eigenvectors
in that matrix V transpose --
okay, I'm going to have to
think.
Why did that come out with with
the opposite sines?
So you see -- I mean,
if I had a minus there,
I would be all right,
but I don't want that.
I want positive entries down
the diagonal of sigma squared.
Okay.
It'll come to me,
but, I'm going to leave this
example to finish.
Okay.
And the beauty of,
these sliding boards is I can
make that go away.
Can I,-- let me not do it,
though, yet.
Let me take a second example.
Let me take a second example
where the matrix is singular.
So rank one.
Okay, so let me take as an
example two, where my matrix A
is going to be rectangular again
-- let me just make it four
three eight six.
Okay.
That's a rank one matrix.
So that has a null space and
only a one dimensional row space
and column space.
So actually,
my picture becomes easy for
this matrix, because what's my
row space for this one?
So this is two by two.
So my pictures are both two
dimensional.
My row space is all multiples
of that vector four three.
So the whole -- the row space
is just a line,
right?
That's the row space.
And the null space,
of course, is the perpendicular
line.
So the row space for this
matrix is multiples of four
three.
Typical row.
Okay.
What's the column space?
The columns are all multiples
of four eight,
three six, one two.
The column space,
then, goes in,
like, this direction.
So the column space -- when I
look at those columns,
the column space -- so it's
only one dimensional,
because the rank is one.
It's multiples of four eight.
Okay.
And what's the null space of A
transpose?
It's the perpendicular guy.
So this was the null space of A
and this is the null space of A
transpose.
Okay.
What I want to say here is that
choosing these orthogonal bases
for the row space and the column
space is, like,
no problem.
They're only one dimensional.
So what should V be?
V should be -- v1,
but -- yes, v1,
rather -- v1 is supposed to be
a unit vector.
There's only one v1 to choose
here, only one dimension in the
row space.
I just want to make it a unit
vector.
So v1 will be -- it'll be this
vector, but made into a unit
vector, so four -- point eight
point six.
Four fifths,
three fifths.
And what will be u1?
u1 will be the unit vector
there.
So I want to turn four eight or
one two into a unit vector,
so u1 will be -- let's see,
if it's one two,
then what multiple of one two
do I want?
That has length square root of
five, so I have to divide by
square root of five.
Let me complete the singular
value decomposition for this
matrix.
So this matrix,
four three eight six,
is -- so I know what u1 --
here's A and I want to get U the
basis in the column space.
And it has to start with this
guy, one over square root of
five two over square root of
five.
Then I want the sigma.
Okay.
What are we expecting now for
sigma?
This is only a rank one matrix.
We're only expecting a sigma
one, which I have to find,
but zeroes here.
Okay.
So what's sigma one?
It should be the -- where did
these sigmas come from?
They came from A transpose A,
so I -- can I do that little
calculation over here?
A transpose A is four three --
four three eight six times four
three eight six.
This had better -- this is a
rank one matrix,
this is going to be --
the whole thing will have rank
one, that's 16 and 64 is 80,
12 and 48 is 60,
9 and 36 is 45.
Okay.
It's a rank one matrix.
Of course.
Every row is a multiple of four
three.
And what's the eigen -- what
are the eigenvalues of that
matrix?
So this is the calculation --
this is like practicing,
now.
What are the eigenvalues of
this rank one matrix?
Well, tell me one eigenvalue,
since the rank is only one,
one eigenvalue is going to be
zero.
And then you know that the
other eigenvalue is going to be
a hundred and twenty five.
So that's sigma squared,
right, in A transpose A.
So this will be the square root
of a hundred and twenty five.
And then finally,
the V transpose -- the Vs will
be -- there's v1,
and what's v2?
What's v2 in the -- how do I
make this into an orthonormal
basis?
Well, v2 is,
in the null space direction.
It's perpendicular to that,
so point six and minus point
eight.
So those are the Vs that go in
here.
Point eight,
point six and point six minus
point eight.
Okay.
And I guess I better finish
this guy.
So this guy,
all I want is to complete the
orthonormal basis --
it'll be coming from there.
It'll be a two over square root
of five and a minus one over
square root of five.
Let me take square root of five
out of that matrix to make it
look better.
So one over square root of five
times one two two minus one.
Okay.
So there I have -- including
the square root of five --
that's an orthogonal matrix,
that's a diagonal matrix and
its rank is only one.
And now if I do that
multiplication,
I pray that it comes out right.
The square root of five will
cancel into that square root of
one twenty five and leave me
with the square root of 25,
which is five,
and five will multiply these
numbers and I'll get whole
numbers and out will come A.
Okay.
That's like a second example
showing how the null space guy
-- so this -- this vector and
this one were multiplied by this
zero.
So they were easy to deal with.
Tthe key ones are the ones in
the column space and the row
space.
Do you see how I'm getting
columns here,
diagonal here,
rows here, coming together to
produce A.
Okay, that's the singular value
decomposition.
So, let me think what I want to
add to complete this topic.
So that's two examples.
And now let's think what we're
really doing.
We're choosing the right basis
for the four subspaces of linear
algebra.
Let me write this down.
So v1 up to vr is an
orthonormal basis for the row
space.
u1 up to ur is an orthonormal
basis for the column space.
And then I just finish those
out by v(r+1),
the rest up to vn is an
orthonormal basis for the null
space.
And finally,
u(r+1) up to is an orthonormal
basis for the null space of A
transpose.
Do you see that we finally got
the bases right?
They're right because they're
orthonormal, and also -- again,
Graham Schmidt would have done
this in chapter four.
Here we needed eigenvalues,
because these bases make the
matrix diagonal.
A times V I is a multiple of U
I.
So I'll put "and" -- the matrix
has been made diagonal.
When we choose these bases,
there's no coupling between Vs
and no coupling between Us.
Each A -- A times each V is in
the direction of the
corresponding U.
So it's exactly the right basis
for the four fundamental
subspaces.
And of course,
their dimensions are what we
know.
The dimension of the row space
is the rank r,
and so is the dimension of the
column space.
The dimension of the null space
is n-r, that's how many vectors
we need, and m-r basis vectors
for the left null space,
the null space of A transpose.
Okay.
I'm going to stop there.
I could develop further from
the SVD, but we'll see it again
in the very last lectures of the
course.
So there's the SVD.
Thanks.