-- one and -- the lecture on
symmetric matrixes.
So that's the most important
class of matrixes,
symmetric matrixes.
A equals A transpose.
So the first points,
the main points of the lecture
I'll tell you right away.
What's special about the
eigenvalues?
eigenvectors?
This is -- the way we now look
at a matrix.
We want to know about its
eigenvalues and eigenvectors and
if we have a special type of
matrix, that should tell us
something about eigenvalues and
eigenvectors.
Like Markov matrixes,
they have an eigenvalue equal
one.
Now symmetric matrixes,
can I just tell you right off
what the main facts -- the two
main facts are?
The eigenvalues of a symmetric
matrix, real -- this is a real
symmetric matrix,
we -- talking mostly about real
matrixes.
The eigenvalues are also real.
So our examples of rotation
matrixes, where -- where we got
E- eigenvalues that were
complex, that won't happen now.
For symmetric matrixes,
the eigenvalues are real and
the eigenvectors are also very
special.
The eigenvectors are
perpendicular,
orthogonal, so which do you
prefer?
I'll say perpendicular.
Perp- well, they're both long
words.
Okay, right.
So -- I have a -- you should
say "why?" and I'll at least
answer why for case one,
maybe case two,
the checking the Eigen -- that
the eigenvectors are
perpendicular,
I'll leave to,
the -- to the book.
But let's just realize what --
well, first I have to say,
it -- it could happen,
like for the identity matrix --
there's a symmetric matrix.
Its eigenvalues are certainly
all real, they're all one for
the identity matrix.
What about the eigenvectors?
Well, for the identity,
every vector is an eigenvector.
So how can I say they're
perpendicular?
What I really mean is the --
they -- this word are should
really be written can be chosen
perpendicular.
That is, if we have -- it's the
usual case.
If the eigenvalues are all
different, then each eigenvalue
has one line of eigenvectors and
those lines are perpendicular
here.
But if an eigenvalue's
repeated, then there's a whole
plane of eigenvectors and all
I'm saying is that in that
plain, we can choose
perpendicular ones.
So that's why it's a can be
chosen part, is -- this is in
the case of a repeated
eigenvalue where there's some
real, substantial freedom.
But the typical case is
different eigenvalues,
all real, one dimensional
eigenvector space,
Eigen spaces,
and all perpendicular.
So, just -- let's just see the
conclusion.
If we accept those as correct,
what happens -- and I also mean
that there's a full set of them.
I -- so that's part of this
picture here,
that there -- there's a
complete set of eigenvectors,
perpendicular ones.
So, having a complete set of
eigenvectors means -- so normal
-- so the usual -- maybe I put
the -- usually -- usual --
usual case is that the matrix A
we can write in terms of its
eigenvalue matrix and its
eigenvector matrix this way,
right?
We can do that in the usual
case, but now what's special
when the matrix is symmetric?
So this is the usual case,
and now let me go to the
symmetric case.
So in the symmetric case,
A, this -- this should become
somehow a little special.
Well, the lambdas on the
diagonal are still on the
diagonal.
They're -- they're real,
but that's where they are.
What about the eigenvector
matrix?
So what can I do now special
about
the eigenvector matrix when --
when the A itself is symmetric,
that says something good about
the eigenvector matrix,
so what is this -- what does
this lead to?
This -- these perpendicular
eigenvectors,
I can not only -- I can not
only guarantee they're
perpendicular,
I could also make them unit
vectors, no problem,
just s- scale their length to
one.
So what do I have?
I have orthonormal
eigenvectors.
And what does that tell me
about the eigenvector matrix?
What -- what letter should I
now use in place of S --
remember
S has the eigenvectors in its
columns, but now those columns
are orthonormal,
so the right letter to use is
Q.
So that's where -- so we've got
the letter all set up,
so this should be Q lambda Q
inverse.
Q standing in our minds always
for this matrix -- in this case
it's square,
it's -- so these are the
Okay.
columns of Q,
of course.
And one more thing.
What's Q inverse?
For a matrix that has these
orthonormal columns,
we know that the inverse is the
same as the transpose.
So here is the beautiful --
there is the -- the great
description,
the factorization of a
symmetric matrix.
And this is,
like, one of the famous
theorems of linear algebra,
that if I have a symmetric
matrix, it can be factored in
this form.
An orthogonal matrix times
diagonal times the transpose of
that orthogonal matrix.
And, of course,
everybody immediately says yes,
and if this is possible,
then that's clearly symmetric,
right?
That -- take -- we've looked at
products of three guys like that
and taken their transpose and we
got
it back again.
So do you -- do you see the
beauty of this -- of this
factorization,
then?
It -- it completely displays
the eigenvalues and eigenvectors
the symmetry of the -- of the
whole thing, because -- that
product, Q times lambda times Q
transpose,
if I transpose it,
it -- this comes in this
position and we get that matrix
back again.
So that's -- in mathematics,
that's called the spectral
theorem.
Spectrum is the set of
eigenvalues of a matrix.
Spec- it somehow comes from the
idea
of the spectrum of light as a
combination of pure things --
where our matrix is broken down
into pure eigenvalues and
eigenvectors -- in mechanics
it's often called the principle
axis theorem.
It's very useful.
It means that if you have --
we'll see it geometrically.
It means that if I have some
material -- if I look at the
right axis, it becomes diagonal,
it becomes -- the -- the
directions don't couple
together.
Okay.
So that's -- that -- that's
what to remember from -- from
this lecture.
Now, I would like to say why
are the eigenvalues real?
Can I do that?
So -- so -- because that --
something useful comes out.
So I'll just come back -- come
to that question why real
eigenvalues?
Okay.
So I have to start from the
only thing we know,
Ax equal lambda x.
Okay.
But as far as I know at this
moment, lambda could be complex.
I'm going to prove it's not --
and x could be complex.
In fact, for the moment,
even A could be -- we could
even think, well,
what
happens if A is complex?
Well, one thing we can always
do -- this is -- this is like
always -- always okay -- I can
-- if I have an equation,
I can take the complex
conjugate of everything.
That's -- no -- no -- so A
conjugate x conjugate equal
lambda
conjugate x conjugate,
it just means that everywhere
over here that there was a -- an
i, then here I changed it to
a-i.
That's -- that -- you know that
that step -- that conjugate
business, that a+ib,
if I conjugate it it's a-ib.
That's the meaning of conjugate
-- and products behave right,
I can conjugate every factor.
So I haven't done anything yet
except to say what would be true
if, x -- in any case,
even if x and lambda were
complex.
Of course, our -- we're
speaking about real matrixes A,
so I can take that out.
Actually, this already tells me
something about real matrixes.
I haven't used any assumption
of A -- A transpose yet.
Symmetry is waiting in the
wings to be used.
This tells me that if a real
matrix has an eigenvalue lambda
and an eigenvector x,
it also has -- another of its
eigenvalues is lambda bar with
eigenvector x bar.
Real matrixes,
the eigenvalues come in lambda,
lambda bar -- the complex
eigenvalues come in lambda and
lambda bar pairs.
But, of course,
I'm aiming to show that they're
not
complex at all,
here, by getting symmetry in.
So how I going to use symmetry?
I'm going to transpose this
equation to x bar transpose A
transpose equals x bar transpose
lambda bar.
That's just a number,
so I don't mind wear I put that
number.
This is --
this is -- this is a -- then
again okay.
Ax equals lambda x bar
transpose x, right?
But now I'm ready to use
symmetry.
I'm ready -- so this was all
just mechanics.
Now -- now comes the moment to
say, okay, if the matrix is
symmetric, then this A transpose
is the same as A.
You see, at that moment I used
the
assumption.
Now let me finish the
discussion.
Here -- here's the way I
finish.
I look at this original
equation and I take the inner
product.
I multiply both sides by -- oh,
maybe I'll do it with this one.
I take -- I multiply both sides
by x bar transpose.
x bar transpose Ax bar equals
lambda bar x bar transpose x
bar.
Okay, fine.
All right, now what's the other
one?
Oh, for the other one I'll
probably use this guy.
A- I happy about this?
No.
For some reason I'm not.
I'm -- I want to --
if I take the inner product of
this from the right with x bar,
I get x bar transpose Ax bar
equals x bar transpose lambda
bar x bar.
I- I've done something dumb,
because I've got the -- I
should've taken the dot product
of this guy here with -- that's
haven't learned anything.
I've got -- those two equations
are identical,1
so forgive me for doing such a
thing, but, I'll look at the
book.
So I took the dot product --
ye, somehow, it didn't -- I
what I was going to do.
Okay.
So that -- that was -- that's
fine.
That comes directly from that,
multiplying both sides by x bar
transpose, but now I'd like to
get -- why do I have x bars over
there?
Oh, yes.
Forget this.
Okay.
On this one -- right.
On this one,
I took it like that,
I multiply on the right by x.
That's the idea.
Okay.
Now why I happier with this
situation now?
A proof is coming here.
Because I compare this guy with
this one.
And they have the same left
hand side.
So they have the same
right hand side.
So comparing those two,
can -- I'll raise the board to
do this comparison -- this
thing, lambda x bar transpose x
is equal to lambda bar x bar
transpose x.
Okay.
And the conclusion I'm going to
reach -- I -- I
on the right track here?
The conclusion I'm going to
reach is lambda equal lambda
bar.
I would have to track down the
other possibility that this --
this thing is zero,
but let me -- oh -- oh,
yes, that's important.
It's not zero.
So once I know that this isn't
zero, I just cancel it and I
learn that lambda equals lambda
bar.
And so what can you -- do you
-- have you got the reasoning
altogether?
What does this tell us?
Lambda's an eigenvalue of this
symmetric matrix.
We've just proved that it
equaled lambda bar,
so we have just proved that
lambda is real,
right?
If, if a number is equal to its
own complex conjugate,
then there's no imaginary part
at all.
The number is real.
So lambda is real.
Good.
Now, what -- but it depended on
this little
expression, on knowing that
that wasn't zero,
so that I could cancel it out
-- so can we just take a second
on that one?
Because it's an important
quantity.
x bar transpose x.
Okay, now remember,
as far as we know,
x is complex.
So this is --
here -- x is complex,
x has these components,
x1, x2 down to xn.
And x bar transpose,
well, it's transposed and it's
conjugated, so that's x1
conjugated x2 conjugated up to
xn conjugated.
I'm -- I'm -- I'm really
reminding you of crucial
facts about complex numbers
that are going to come into the
next lecture as well as this
one.
So w- what can you tell me
about that product -- I -- I
guess what I'm trying to say is,
if I had a complex vector,
this would be the quantity I
would -- I would like.
This is the quantity I like.
I would take the vector times
its transpose -- now what --
what happens usually if I take a
vector -- a -- a -- x transpose
x?
I mean, that's a quantity we
see all the time,
x transpose x.
That's the length of x squared,
right?
That's this positive length
squared,
it's Pythagoras,
it's x1 squared plus x2 squared
and so on.
Now our vector's complex,
and you see the effect?
I'm conjugating one of these
guys.
So now when I do this
multiplication,
I have x1 bar times x1 and x2
bar times x2 and so on.
So this is an -- this is sum
a+ib.
And this is sum a-ib.
I mean, what's the point here?
What's the point -- when I
multiply a number by its
conjugate, a complex number by
its conjugate,
what do I get?
I get a n- the -- the imaginary
part is gone.
When I multiply a+ib by its
conjugate, what's -- what's the
result of that -- of each of
those separate little
multiplications?
There's an a squared and -- and
what -- how many -- what's -- b
squared comes in with a plus or
a minus?
A plus.
i times minus i is a plus b
squared.
And what about the imaginary
part?
Gone, right?
An iab and a minus iab.
So this -- this is the right
thing to do.
If you want a decent answer,
then multiply numbers by their
conjugates.
Multiply vectors by the
conjugates of x transpose.
So this quantity is positive,
this quantity is positive --
the whole thing is positive
except for the zero vector and
that allows me to know that this
is a positive number,
which I safely cancel out and I
reach the conclusion.
So actually,
in this discussion here,
I've done two things.
If I reached the conclusion
that lambda's real,
which I wanted to do.
But at the same time,
we sort of saw what to do if
things were complex.
If a vector is complex,
then it's x bar transpose x,
this is its length squared.
And as I said,
the next lecture Monday,
we'll -- we'll repeat that this
is the right thing and then do
the right thing for matrixes and
all other -- all other,
complex possibilities.
Okay.
But the main point,
then, is that the eigenvalues
of a symmetric matrix,
it just -- do you -- do --
where did we use symmetry,
by the way?
We used it here,
right?
Let -- can I just -- let --
suppose A was a complex.
Suppose A had been a complex
number.
Could -- could I have made all
this work?
If A was a complex number --
complex matrix,
then here I should have written
A bar.
I erased the bar because I
assumed A was real.
But now let's suppose for a
moment it's not.
Then when I took this step,
what should I have?
What did I do
on that step?
I transposed.
So I should have A bar
transpose.
In the symmetric case,
that was A, and that's what
made everything work,
right?
This -- this led immediately to
that.
This one led immediately to
this when the matrix was real,
so that didn't matter,
and it was
symmetric, so that didn't
matter.
Then I got A.
But -- so now I just get to ask
you.
Suppose the matrix had been
complex.
What's the right equivalent of
sym- symmetry?
So the good matrix -- so here,
let me say -- good matrixes --
by good I mean real
lambdas and perpendicular x-s.
And tell me now,
which matrixes are good?
If they're -- If they're real
matrixes, the good ones are
symmetric, because then
everything went through.
The -- so the good -- I'm
saying now
what's good.
This is -- this is -- these are
the good matrixes.
They have real eigenvalues,
perpendicular eigenvectors --
good means A equal A transpose
if real.
Then -- then that was what --
our proof worked.
But if A is complex,
all -- our proof will still
work
provided A bar transpose is A.
Do you see what I'm saying?
I'm saying if we have complex
matrixes and we want to say are
they -- are they as good as
symmetric matrixes,
then we should not only
transpose the thing,
but conjugate it.
Those are good matrixes.
And of course,
the most important s- the most
important case is when they're
real, this part doesn't matter
and I just have A equal A
transpose symmetric.
Do you -- I -- I'll just repeat
that.
The good matrixes,
if complex, are these.
If real, that doesn't make any
difference so I'm just saying
symmetric.
And of course,
99% of examples and
applications to the matrixes are
real and we don't have that and
then symmetric is the key
property.
Okay.
So that -- that's,
these main facts and now
let me just -- let me just --
so that's this x bar transpose
x, okay.
So I'll just,
write it once more in this
form.
So perpendicular orthonormal
eigenvectors,
real eigenvalues,
transposes of orthonormal
eigenvectors.
That's the symmetric case,
A equal A transpose.
Okay.
Good.
Actually, I'll even take one
more step here.
Suppose -- I -- I can break
this down to show you really
what that says about a symmetric
matrix.
I can break that down.
Let me here -- here go these
eigenvectors.
I -- here go these eigenvalues,
lambda one, lambda two and so
on.
Here go these eigenvectors
transposed.
And what happens if I actually
do out that multiplication?
Do you see what will happen?
There's lambda one times q1
transpose.
So the first row here is just
lambda one q1 transpose.
If I multiply column times row
-- you remember I could do that?
When I multiply matrixes,
I can multiply columns times
rows?
So when I do that,
I get lambda one and then the
column
and then the row and then
lambda two and then the column
and the row.
Every symmetric matrix breaks
up into these pieces.
So these pieces have real
lambdas and they have these
Eigen -- these orthonormal
eigenvectors.
And, maybe you even could tell
me what kind of a matrix have I
got there?
Suppose I take a unit vector
times its transpose?
So column times row,
I'm getting a matrix.
That's a matrix with a special
name.
What's it's -- what kind of a
matrix is it?
We've seen those matrixes,
now, in chapter four.
It's -- is A A transpose with a
unit vector,
so I don't have to divide by A
transpose A.
That matrix is a projection
matrix.
That's a projection matrix.
It's symmetric and if I square
it there'll be another --
there'll be a q1 transpose q1,
which is one.
So I'll get that matrix back
again.
Every -- so every symmetric
matrix -- every symmetric matrix
is a combination of -- of
mutually perpendicular -- so
perpendicular projection
matrixes.
Projection matrixes.
Okay.
That's another way that people
like to think of the spectral
theorem, that every symmetric
matrix can be
broken up that way.
That -- I guess at this moment
-- first I haven't done an
example.
I could create a symmetric
matrix, check that it's -- find
its eigenvalues,
they would come out real,
find its eigenvectors,
they would come out
perpendicular and you would see
it
in numbers, but maybe I'll
leave it here for the moment in
letters.
Oh, I -- maybe I will do it
with numbers,
for this reason.
Because there's one more
remarkable fact.
Can I just put this further
great fact about symmetric
matrixes on the board?
When I have symmetric matrixes,
I know their eigenvalues are
real.
So then I can get interested in
the question are they positive
or negative?
And you remember why that's
important.
For differential equations,
that decides between
instability and stability.
So I'm -- after I know they're
real, then the next question is
are they positive,
are they negative?
And I hate to have to compute
those eigenvalues to answer that
question, right?
Because computing the
eigenvalues of a symmetric
matrix of order let's say 50 --
compute its 50 eigenvalues -- is
a job.
I mean, by pencil and paper
it's a lifetime's job.
I mean, which -- and in fact,
a few years ago -- well,
say, 20 years ago,
or 30, nobody really knew how
to do it.
I mean, so, like,
science was stuck on this
problem.
If you have a matrix of order
50 or
100, how do you find its
eigenvalues?
Numerically,
now, I'm just saying,
because pencil and paper is --
we're going to run out of time
or paper or something before we
get it.
Well -- and you might think,
okay, get
Matlab to compute the
determinant of lambda minus A,
A minus lambda I,
this polynomial of 50th degree,
and then find the roots.
Matlab will do it,
but it will complain,
because it's a very bad way to
find the eigenvalues.
I'm sorry to be saying
this, because it's the way I
taught you to do it,
right?
I taught you to find the
eigenvalues by doing that
determinant and taking the roots
of that polynomial.
But now I'm saying,
okay, I really meant that for
two by twos and three by threes
but I didn't mean you to do it
on a 50 by
50 and you're not too unhappy,
probably, because you didn't
want to do it.
But -- good,
because it would be a very
unstable way -- the 50 answers
that would come out would be
highly unreliable.
So, new ways are -- are much
better to find those 50
eigenvalues.
That's a -- that's a part of
numerical linear algebra.
But here's the remarkable fact
-- that Matlab would quite
happily find the 50 pivots,
right?
Now the pivots are not the same
as the eigenvalues.
But here's the great thing.
If I had a real matrix,
I could find those 50 pivots
and I could see maybe 28 of them
are positive and 22 are negative
pivots.
And I can compute those safely
and quickly.
And the great fact is that 28
of the eigenvalues would be
positive and 22 would be
negative --
that the sines of the pivots --
so this is, like -- I hope you
think this -- this is kind of a
nice thing, that the sines of
the pivots -- for symmetric,
I'm always talking about
symmetric matrixes -- so I'm
really,
like, trying to convince you
that symmetric matrixes are
better than the rest.
So the sines of the pivots are
same as the sines of the
eigenvalues.
The same number.
The number of pivots greater
than zero, the number of
positive pivots is equal to the
number of positive eigenvalues.
So that, actually,
is a very useful -- that gives
you a g- a good start on a
decent way to compute
eigenvalues, because you can
narrow them down,
you can find out how many are
positive, how many are negative.
Then you could shift the matrix
by seven times the identity.
That would shift all the
eigenvalues by seven.
Then you could take the pivots
of that matrix and you would
know how many eigenvalues of the
original were above seven and
below seven.
So this -- this neat little
theorem, that,
symmetric
matrixes have this connection
between the -- nobody's mixing
up and thinking the pivots are
the eigenvalues -- I mean,
the only thing I can think of
is the product of the pivots
equals the product of the
eigenvalues, why is that?
So if I asked you for the
reason on that,
why is the product
of the pivots for a symmetric
matrix the same as the product
of the eigenvalues?
Because they both equal the
determinant.
Right.
The product of the pivots gives
the determinant if no row
exchanges, the product of the
eigenvalues always gives the
determinant.
So -- so the products --
but that doesn't tell you
anything about the 50 individual
ones, which this does.
Okay.
So that's -- those are
essential facts about symmetric
matrixes.
Okay.
Now I -- I said in the -- in
the lecture description that I
would take the last minutes
to start on positive definite
matrixes, because we're right
there, we're ready to say what's
a positive definite matrix?
It's symmetric,
first of all.
On -- always I will mean
symmetric.
So this is the --
this is the next section of the
book.
It's about this -- if symmetric
matrixes are good,
which was, like,
the point of my lecture so far,
then positive,
definite matrixes are -- a
subclass that are excellent,
okay.
Just the greatest.
so what are they?
They're matrixes -- they're
symmetric matrixes,
so all their eigenvalues are
real.
You can guess what they are.
These are symmetric matrixes
with all -- the eigenvalues are
-- okay, tell me what to write.
What -- well,
it -- it's hinted,
of course, by the name for
these things.
All the eigenvalues are
positive.
Okay.
Tell me about the pivots.
We can check the eigenvalues or
we can check the pivots.
All the pivots are what?
And then I'll -- then I'll
finally give an example.
I feel awful that I have got to
this
point in the lecture and I
haven't given you a single
example.
So let me give you one.
Five three two two.
That's symmetric,
fine.
It's eigenvalues are real,
for sure.
But more than that,
I know the sines of those
eigenvalues.
And also I know the sines of
those
pivots, so what's the deal with
the pivots?
The Ei- if the eigenvalues are
all positive and if this little
fact is true that the pivots and
eigenvalues have the same sines,
then this must be true -- all
the pivots are positive.
And that's the good way to
test.
This is the good test,
because I can -- what are the
pivots for that matrix?
The pivots for that matrix are
five.
So pivots are five and what's
the second pivot?
Have we, like,
noticed the formula for the
second pivot in a matrix?
It doesn't necessarily -- you
know, it may come out a fraction
for sure, but what is that
fraction?
Can you tell me?
Well, here, the product of the
pivots is the determinant.
What's the determinant of this
matrix?
Eleven?
So the second pivot must be
eleven over five,
so that the product is eleven.
They're both positive.
Then I know that the
eigenvalues of that matrix are
both positive.
What are the eigenvalues?
Well, I've got to take the
roots of -- you know,
do I put in a minus lambda?
You mentally do this -- lambda
squared minus how many lambdas?
Eight?
Right.
Five and three,
the trace comes in there,
plus what number comes here?
The determinant,
the eleven, so I set that to
zero.
So the eigenvalues are -- let's
see, half of that is four,
look at that positive number,
plus or minus the square root
of
sixteen minus eleven,
I think five.
The eigenvalues -- well,
two by two they're not so
terrible, but they're not so
perfect.
Pivots are really simple.
And this is a -- this is the
family of matrixes that you
really want in differential
equations, because you know the
sines of the eigenvalues,
so you know the stability or
not.
Okay.
There's one other related fact
I can pop in here in -- in the
time available for positive
definite matrixes.
The related fact is to ask you
about determinants.
So what's the determinant?
What can you tell me if I --
remember, positive definite
means all eigenvalues are
positive, all pivots are
positive, so what can you tell
me about the determinant?
It's positive,
too.
But somehow that -- that's not
quite enough.
Here -- here's a matrix minus
one
minus three,
what's the determinant of that
guy?
It's positive,
right?
Is this a positive,
definite matrix?
Are the pivots -- what are the
pivots?
Well, negative.
What are the eigenvalues?
Well, they're also the same.
So somehow I don't just want
the determinant of the whole
matrix.
Here is eleven,
that's great.
Here the determinant of the
whole matrix is three,
that's positive.
I also -- I've got to check,
like, little sub-determinants,
say maybe coming down from the
left.
So the one by one and the two
by two
have to be positive.
So there -- that's where I get
the all.
All -- can I call them
sub-determinants -- are -- see,
I have to -- I need to make the
thing plural.
I need to test n things,
not just the big determinant.
All sub-determinants are
positive.
Then I'm okay.
This passes the test.
Five is positive and eleven is
positive.
This fails the test because
that minus one there is
negative.
And then the big determinant is
positive three.
So t- this --
these -- this fact -- you see
that actually the course,
like, coming together.
And that's really my point now.
In the next -- in this lecture
and particularly next Wednesday
and Friday, the course comes
together.
These pivots that we met in the
first week, these determinants
that we met in the middle of
the course, these eigenvalues
that we met most recently -- all
matrixes are square here,
so coming together for square
matrixes means these three
pieces come together and they
come together in that beautiful
fact, that if -- that all the --
that if I have one of these,
I have the others.
That if I -- but for symmetric
matrixes.
So that -- this will be the
positive definite section and
then the real climax of the
course is to make everything
come together for n by n
matrixes,
not necessarily symmetric --
bring everything together there
and that will be the final
thing.
Okay.
So have a great weekend and
don't forget symmetric matrixes.
Thanks.