OK.
cameras are rolling.
This is lecture fourteen,
starting a new chapter.
Chapter about orthogonality.
What it means for vectors to be
orthogonal.
What it means for subspaces to
be orthogonal.
What it means for bases to be
orthogonal.
So ninety degrees,
this is a ninety-degree
chapter.
So what does it mean -- let me
jump to subspaces.
Because I've drawn here the big
picture.
This is the 18.06 picture here.
And hold it down,
guys.
So this is the picture and we
know a lot about that picture
already.
We know the dimension of every
subspace.
We know that these dimensions
are r and n-r.
are r and m-r.
What I want to show now is what
this figure is saying,
that the angle --
the figure is just my attempt
to draw what I'm now going to
say, that the angle between
these subspaces is ninety
degrees.
And the angle between these
subspaces is ninety degrees.
Now I have to say what does
that mean?
What does it mean for subspaces
to be orthogonal?
But I hope you appreciate the
beauty of this picture,
that that those subspaces are
going to come out to be
orthogonal.
Those two and also those two.
So that's like one point,
one important point to step
forward in understanding those
subspaces.
We knew what each subspace was
like, we could compute bases for
them.
Now we know more.
Or we will in a few minutes.
OK.
I have to say first of all what
does it mean for two vectors to
be orthogonal?
So let me start with that.
Orthogonal vectors.
The word orthogonal is -- is
just another word for
perpendicular.
It means that in n-dimensional
space the angle between those
vectors is ninety degrees.
It means that they form a right
triangle.
It even means that the going
way back to the Greeks that this
angle that this triangle a
vector x, a vector x,
and a vector x+y --
of course that'll be the
hypotenuse, so what was it the
Greeks figured out and it's
neat.
It's the fact that the -- so
these are orthogonal,
this is a right angle,
if -- so let me put the great
name down, Pythagoras,
I'm looking for -- what I
looking for?
I'm looking for the condition
if you give me two vectors,
how do I know if they're
orthogonal?
How can I tell two
perpendicular vectors?
And actually you probably know
the answer.
Let me write the answer down.
Orthogonal vectors,
what's the test for
orthogonality?
I take the dot product which I
tend to write as x transpose y,
because that's a row times a
column, and that matrix
multiplication just gives me the
right thing, that x1y1+x2y2 and
so on, so these vectors are
orthogonal if this result x
transpose y is zero.
That's the test.
OK.
Can I connect that to other
things?
I mean -- it's just beautiful
that here we have we're in n
dimensions, we've got a couple
of vectors, we want to know the
angle between them,
and the right thing to look at
is the simplest thing that you
could imagine,
the dot product.
OK.
Now why?
So I'm answering the question
now why --
let's add some justification to
this fact, that's the test.
OK, so Pythagoras would say
we've got a right triangle,
if that length squared plus
that length squared equals that
length squared.
OK, can I write it as x squared
plus y squared equals x plus y
squared?
Now don't, please don't think
that this is always true.
This is only going to be true
in this -- it's going to be
equivalent to orthogonality.
For other triangles of course,
it's not true.
For other triangles it's not.
But for a right triangle
somehow that fact should connect
to that fact.
Can we just make that
connection?
What's the connection between
this test for orthogonality and
this statement of orthogonality?
Well, I guess I have to say
what is the length squared?
So let's continue on the board
underneath with that equation.
Give me another way to express
the length squared of a vector.
And let me just give you a
vector.
The vector one,
two, three.
That's in three dimensions.
What is the length squared of
the vector x equal one,
two, three?
So how do you find the length
squared?
Well, really you just,
you want the length of that
vector that goes along one --
up two, and out three -- and
we'll come back to that right
triangle stuff.
The length squared is exactly x
transpose x.
Whenever I see x transpose x,
I know I've got a number that's
positive.
It's a length squared unless it
--
unless x happens to be the zero
vector, that's the one case
where the length is zero.
So right -- this is just x1
squared plus x2 squared plus so
on, plus xn squared.
So one -- in the example I gave
you what was the length squared
of that vector one,
two, three?
So you square those,
you get one,
four and nine,
you add, you get fourteen.
So the vector one,
two, three has length fourteen.
So let me just put down a
vector here.
Let x be the vector one,
two, three.
Let me cook up a vector that's
orthogonal to it.
So what's the vector that's
orthogonal?
So right down here,
x squared is one plus four plus
nine, fourteen,
let me cook up a vector that's
orthogonal to it,
we'll get right that that --
those two vectors are
orthogonal, the length of y
squared is five,
and x plus y is one and two
making three,
two and minus one making one,
three and zero making three,
and the length of this squared
is nine plus one plus nine,
nineteen.
And sure enough,
I haven't proved anything.
I've just like checked to see
that my test x transpose y
equals zero, which is true,
right?
Everybody sees that x transpose
y is zero here?
That's maybe the main point.
That you should get really
quick at doing x transpose y,
so it's just this plus this
plus this and that's zero.
And sure enough,
that clicks with fourteen plus
five agreeing with nineteen.
Now let me just do that in
letters.
So that's y transpose y.
And this is x plus y transpose
x plus y.
OK.
So I'm looking,
again, this isn't always true.
I repeat.
This is going to be true when
we have a right angle.
And let's just -- well,
of course, I'm just going to
simplify this stuff here.
There's an x transpose x there.
And there's a y transpose y
there.
And there's an x transpose y.
And there's a y transpose x.
I knew I could do that
simplification because I'm just
doing matrix multiplication and
I've just followed the rules.
OK.
So x transpose x-s cancel.
Y transpose y-s cancel.
And what about these guys?
What can you tell me about the
inner product of x with y and
the inner product of y with x?
Is there a difference?
I think if we --
while we're doing real vectors,
which is all we're doing now,
there isn't a difference,
there's no difference.
If I take x transpose y,
that'll give me zero,
if I took y transpose x I would
have the same x1y1 and x2y2 and
x3y3, it would be the same,
so this is --
this is the same as that,
this is really I'll knock that
guy out and say two of these.
So actually that's the -- this
equation boiled down to this
thing being zero.
Right?
Everything else canceled and
this equation boiled down to
that one.
So that's really all I wanted.
I just wanted to check that
Pythagoras for a right triangle
led me to this -- of course I
cancel the two now.
No problem.
To x transpose y equals zero as
the test.
Fair enough.
OK.
You knew it was coming.
The dot product of orthogonal
vectors is zero.
It's just -- I just want to say
that's really neat.
That it comes out so well.
All right.
Now what about -- so now I know
if two -- when two vectors are
orthogonal.
By the way, what about if one
of these guys is the zero
vector?
Suppose x is the zero vector,
and y is whatever.
Are they orthogonal?
Sure.
In math the one thing about
math is you're supposed to
follow the rules.
So you're supposed to -- if x
is the zero vector,
you're supposed to take the
zero vector dotted with y and of
course you always get zero.
So just so we're all sure,
the zero vector is orthogonal
to everybody.
But what I want to -- what I
now want to think about is
subspaces.
What does it mean for me to say
that some subspace is orthogonal
to some other subspace?
So OK.
Now I've got to write this
down.
So because we're defining
definition of subspace S is
orthogonal so to subspace let's
say T, so I've got a couple of
subspaces.
And what should it mean for
those guys to be orthogonal?
It's just sort of what's the
natural extension from
orthogonal vectors to orthogonal
subspaces?
Well, and in particular,
let's think of some orthogonal
subspaces, like this wall.
Let's say in three dimensions.
So the blackboard extended to
infinity, right,
is a --
is a subspace,
a plane, a two-dimensional
subspace.
It's a little bumpy but anyway,
it's a -- think of it as a
subspace, let me take the floor
as another subspace.
Again, it's not a great
subspace, MIT only built it like
so-so, but I'll put the origin
right here.
So the origin of the world is
right there.
OK.
Thereby giving linear algebra
its proper importance in this.
OK.
So there is one subspace,
there's another one.
The floor.
And are they orthogonal?
What does it mean for two
subspaces to be orthogonal and
in that special case are they
orthogonal?
All right.
Let's finish this sentence.
What does it mean means we have
to know what we're talking about
here.
So what would be a reasonable
idea of orthogonal?
Well, let me put the right
thing up.
It means that every vector in
S, every vector in S,
is orthogonal to --
what I going to say?
Every vector in T.
That's a reasonable and it's a
good and it's the right
definition for two subspaces to
be orthogonal.
But I just want you to see,
hey, what does that mean?
So answer the question about
the -- the blackboard and the
floor.
Are those two subspaces,
they're two-dimensional,
right, and we're in R^3.
It's like a xz plane or
something and a xy plane.
Are they orthogonal?
Is every vector in the
blackboard orthogonal to every
vector in the floor,
starting from the origin right
there?
Yes or no?
I could take a vote.
Well we get some yeses and some
noes.
No is the answer.
They're not.
You can tell me a vector in the
blackboard and a vector in the
floor that are not orthogonal.
Well you can tell me quite a
few, I guess.
Maybe like I could take some
forty-five-degree guy in the
blackboard, and something in the
floor, they're not at ninety
degrees, right?
In fact, even more,
you could tell me a vector
that's in both the blackboard
plane and the floor plane,
so it's certainly not
orthogonal to itself.
So for sure,
those two planes aren't
orthogonal.
What would that be?
So what's a vector that's -- in
both of those planes?
It's this guy running along the
crack there, in the
intersection,
the intersection.
A vector, you know --
if two subspaces meet at some
vector, well then for sure
they're not orthogonal,
because that vector is in one
and it's in the other,
and it's not orthogonal to
itself unless it's zero.
So the only I mean so
orthogonal is for me to say
these two subspaces are
orthogonal first of all I'm
certainly saying that they don't
intersect in any nonzero vector.
But also I mean more than that
just not intersecting isn't good
enough.
So give me an example,
oh, let's say in the plane,
oh well, when do we have
orthogonal subspaces in the
plane?
Yeah, tell me in the plane,
so we don't -- there aren't
that many different subspaces in
the plane.
What what have we got in the
plane as possible subspaces?
The zero vector,
real small.
A line through the origin.
Or the whole plane.
OK.
Now so when is a line through
the origin orthogonal to the
whole plane?
Never, right,
never.
When is a line through the
origin orthogonal to the zero
subspace?
Always.
Right.
When is a line through the
origin orthogonal to a different
line through the origin?
Well, that's the case that we
all have a clear picture of,
they -- the two lines have to
meet at ninety degrees.
They have only the -- so that's
like this simple case I'm
talking about.
There's one subspace,
there's the other subspace.
They only meet at zero.
And they're orthogonal.
OK.
Now.
So we now know what it means
for two subspaces to be
orthogonal.
And now I want to say that this
is true for the row space and
the null space.
OK.
So that's the neat fact.
So row space is orthogonal to
the null space.
Now how did I come up with
that?
But you see the rank it's
great, that means that these --
that these subspaces are just
the right things,
they're just cutting the whole
space up into two perpendicular
subspaces.
OK.
So why?
Well, what have I got to work
with?
All I know is the null space.
The null space has vectors that
solve Ax equals zero.
So this is a guy x.
x is in the null space.
Then Ax is zero.
So why is it orthogonal to the
rows of A?
If I write down Ax equals zero,
which is all I know about the
null space, then I guess I want
you to see that that's telling
me, just that equation right
there is telling me that the
rows of A, let me write it out.
There's row one of A.
Row two.
Row m of A.
that's A.
And it's multiplying X.
And it's producing zero.
OK.
Written out that way you'll see
it.
So I'm saying that a vector in
the row space is perpendicular
to this guy X in the null space.
And you see why?
Because this equation is
telling you that row one of A
multiplying that's a dot
product, right?
Row one of A dot product with
this x is producing this zero.
So x is orthogonal to the first
row.
And to the second row.
Row two of A,
x is giving that zero.
Row m of A times x is giving
that zero.
So x is -- the equation is
telling me that x is orthogonal
to all the rows.
Right, it's just sitting there.
That's all we -- it had to be
sitting there because we didn't
know anything more about the
null space than this.
And now I guess to be totally
complete here I'd now check that
x is orthogonal to each separate
row.
But what else strictly speaking
do I have to do?
To show that those subspaces
are orthogonal,
I have to take this x in the
null space and show that it's
orthogonal to every vector in
the row space,
every vector in the row space,
so what --
what else is in the row space?
This row is in the row space,
that row is in the row space,
they're all there,
but it's not the whole row
space, right,
we just have to like remember,
what does it mean,
what does that word space
telling us?
And what else is in the row
space?
Besides the rows?
All their combinations.
So I really have to check that
sure enough if x is
perpendicular to row one,
row two, all the different
separate rows,
then also x is perpendicular to
a combination of the rows.
And that's just matrix
multiplication again.
You know, I have row one
transpose x is zero,
so on, row two transpose x is
zero, so I'm entitled to
multiply that by some c1,
this by some c2,
I still have zeroes,
I'm entitled to add,
so I have c1 row one so --
so all this when I put that
together that's big parentheses
c1 row one plus c2 row two and
so on.
Transpose x is zero.
Right?
I just added the zeroes and got
zero, and I just added these
following the rule.
No big deal.
The whole point was right
sitting in that.
OK.
So if I come back to this
figure now I'm like a happier
person.
Because I have this -- I now
see how those subspaces are
oriented.
And these subspaces are also
Well, actually why is that
orthogonality?
Well, it's the same statement
for A transpose that that one
was for A.
So I won't take time to prove
it again because we've checked
it for every matrix and A
transpose is just as good a
matrix as A.
So we're orthogonal over there.
So we really have carved up
this --
this was like carving up
m-dimensional space into two
subspaces and this one was
carving up n-dimensional space
into two subspaces.
And well, one more thing here.
One more important thing.
Let me move into three
dimensions.
Tell me a couple of orthogonal
subspaces in three dimensions
that somehow don't carve up the
whole space, there's stuff left
there.
I'm thinking of a couple of
orthogonal lines.
If I -- suppose I'm in three
dimensions, R^3.
And I have one line,
one one-dimensional subspace,
and a perpendicular one.
Could those be the row space
and the null space?
Could I be in three dimensions
and have a row space that's a
line and a null space that's a
line?
No.
Why not?
Because the dimensions aren't
right.
Right?
The dimensions are no good.
The dimensions here,
r and n-r, they add up to
three, they add up to n.
If I take -- just follow that
example -- if the row space is
one-dimensional,
suppose A is what's a good in
R^3, I want a one-dimensional
row space, let me take one,
two, five, two,
four, ten.
What's the dimension of that
row space?
One.
What's the dimension of the
null space?
Tell what's the null space look
like in that case?
The row space is a line,
right?
One-dimensional,
it's just a line through one,
two, five.
Geometrically what's the row
space look like?
What's its dimension?
So here r here n is three,
the rank is one,
so the dimension of the null
space, so I'm looking at this x,
x1, x2, x3.
To give zero.
So the dimension of the null
space is we all know is two.
Right.
It's a plane.
And now actually we know,
we see better,
what plane is it?
What plane is it?
It's the plane that's
perpendicular to one,
two, five.
Right?
We now see.
In fact the two,
four, ten didn't actually have
any effect at all.
I could have just ignored that.
That didn't change the row
space or the null space.
I'll just make that one
equation.
Yeah.
OK.
Sure.
That's the easiest to deal
with.
One equation.
Three unknowns.
And I want to ask --
what would the equation give me
the null space,
and you would have said back in
September you would have said it
gives you a plane,
and we're completely right.
And the plane it gives you,
the normal vector,
you remember in calculus,
there was this dumb normal
vector called N.
Well there it is.
One, two, five.
OK.
What is the what's the point I
want to make here?
I want to make -- I want to
emphasize that not only are the
-- let me write it in words.
So I want to write the null
space and the row space are
orthogonal, that's this neat
fact, which we've --
we've just checked from Ax
equals zero, but now I want to
say more because there's a
little more that's true.
Their dimensions add to the
whole space.
So that's like a little extra
information.
That it's not like I could have
-- I couldn't have a line and a
line in three dimensions.
Those don't add up one and one
don't add to three.
So I used the word orthogonal
complements in R^n.
And the idea of this word
complement is that the
orthogonal complement of a row
space contains not just some
vectors that are orthogonal to
it, but all.
So what does that mean?
That means that the null space
contains all,
not just some but all,
vectors that are perpendicular
to the row space.
OK.
Really what I've done in this
half of the lecture is just
notice some of the nice geometry
that --
that we didn't pick up before
because we didn't discuss
perpendicular vectors before.
But it was all sitting there.
And now we picked it up.
That these vectors are
orthogonal complements.
And I guess I even call this
part one of the fundamental
theorem of linear algebra.
The fundamental theorem of
linear algebra is about these
four subspaces,
so part one is about their
dimension, maybe I should call
it part two now.
Their dimensions we got.
Now we're getting their
orthogonality,
that's part two.
And part three will be about
bases for them.
Orthogonal bases.
So that's coming up.
OK.
So I'm happy with that geometry
right now.
OK.
Now what's my next goal in this
chapter?
Here's the main problem of the
chapter.
The main problem of the chapter
is -- so this is coming.
It's coming attraction.
This is the very last chapter
that's about Ax=b.
I would like to solve that
system of equations when there
is no solution.
You may say what a ridiculous
thing to do.
But I have to say it's done all
the time.
In fact it has to be done.
You get -- so the problem is
solve --
the best possible solve I'll
put quote Ax=b when there is no
solution.
And of course what does that
mean?
b isn't in the column space.
And it's quite typical if this
matrix A is rectangular if I --
maybe I have m equations and
that's bigger than the number of
unknowns, then for sure the rank
is not m,
the rank couldn't be m now,
so there'll be a lot of
right-hand sides with no
solution, but here's an example.
Some satellite is buzzing
along.
You measure its position.
You make a thousand
measurements.
So that gives you a thousand
equations for the -- for the
parameters that --
that give the position.
But there aren't a thousand
parameters, there's just maybe
six or something.
Or you're measuring the --
you're doing questionnaires.
You're measuring resistances.
You're taking pulses.
You're measuring somebody's
pulse rate.
OK.
There's just one unknown.
The pulse rate.
So you measure it once,
OK, fine, but if you really
want to know it,
you measure it multiple times,
but then the measurements have
noise in them,
so there's -- the problem is
that in many many problems we've
got too many equations and
they've got noise in the
right-hand side.
So Ax=b I can't expect to solve
it exactly right,
because I don't even know what
-- there's a measurement mistake
in b.
But there's information too.
There's a lot of information
about x in there.
And what I want to do is like
separate the noise,
the junk, from the information.
And so this is a
straightforward linear algebra
problem.
How do I solve,
what's the best solution?
OK.
Now.
I want to say so that's like
describes the problem in an
algebraic way.
I got some equations,
I'm looking for the best
solution.
Well, one way to find it is --
one way to start,
one way to find a solution is
throw away equations until
you've got a nice,
square invertible system and
solve that.
That's not satisfactory.
There's no reason in these
measurements to say these
measurements are perfect and
these measurements are useless.
We want to use all the
measurements to get the best
information, to get the maximum
information.
But how?
OK.
Let me anticipate a matrix
that's going to show up.
This A is typically
rectangular.
But a matrix that shows up
whenever you have -- and we
chapter three was all about
rectangular matrices.
And we know when this is
solvable, you could do
elimination on it,
right?
But I'm thinking hey,
you do elimination and you get
equation zero equal other
non-zeroes.
I'm thinking we really --
elimination is going to fail.
So that's our question.
Elimination will get us down to
-- will tell us if there is a
solution or not.
But I'm now thinking not.
OK.
So what are we going to do?
All right.
I want to tell you to jump
ahead to the matrix that will
play a key role.
So this is the matrix that you
want to understand for this
chapter four.
And it's the matrix A transpose
A.
What's -- tell me some things
about that matrix.
So A is this m by n matrix,
rectangular,
but now I'm saying that the
good matrix that shows up in the
end is A transpose A.
So tell me something about
that.
Is it -- what's the first thing
you know about A transpose A.
It's square.
Right?
Square because this is m by n
and this is n by m.
So this is the result is n by
n.
Good.
Square.
What else?
It's symmetric.
Good.
Because you remember how to do
that.
If we transpose that matrix
let's transpose it,
A transpose A,
if I transpose it,
then that comes first
transposed, this comes second,
transposed, and then
transposing twice is leaves it
--
brings it back to the same so
it's symmetric.
Good.
Now we now know how to ask more
about a matrix.
I'm interested in is it
invertible?
If not, what's its null space?
So I want to know about --
because you're going to see,
well, let me --
let me even,
well I shouldn't do this,
but I will.
Let me tell you what equation
to solve when you can't solve
that one.
The good equation comes from
multiplying both sides by A
transpose, so the good equation
that you get to is this one.
A transpose Ax equals A
transpose b.
That will be the central
equation in the chapter.
So I think why not tell it to
you.
Why not admit it right away.
OK.
I have to -- I should really
give x.
I want to sort of indicate that
this x isn't I mean this x was
the solution to that equation if
it existed, but probably didn't.
Now let me give this a
different name,
x hat.
Because I'm hoping this one
will have a solution.
And I'm saying that it's my
best solution.
I'll have to say what does best
mean.
But that's going to be my --
my plan.
I'm going to say that the best
solution solves this equation.
So you see right away why I'm
so interested in this matrix A
transpose A.
And in its invertibility.
OK.
Now, when is it invertible?
Let me take a case,
let me just do an example and
then --
I'll just pick a matrix here.
Just so we see what A transpose
A looks like.
So let me take a matrix A one,
one, one, one,
two, five.
Just to invent a matrix.
So there's a matrix A.
Notice that it has M equal
three rows and N equal two
columns.
Its rank is -- the rank of that
matrix is two.
Right, yeah,
the columns are independent.
Does Ax equal b?
If I look at Ax=b,
so x is just x1 x2,
and b is b1 b2 b3.
Do I expect to solve Ax=b?
What's -- no way,
right?
I mean linear algebra's great,
but solving three equations
with only two unknowns usually
we can't do it.
We can only solve it if this
vector is b is what?
I can solve that equation if
that vector b1 b2 b3 is in the
column space.
If it's a combination of those
columns then fine.
But usually it won't be.
The combinations just fill up a
plane and most vectors aren't on
that plane.
So what I'm saying is that I'm
going to work with the matrix A
transpose A.
And I just want to figure out
in this example what A transpose
A is.
So it's two by two.
The first entry is a three,
the next entry is an eight,
this entry is -- what's that
entry?
Eight, for sure.
We knew it had to be,
and this entry is,
what's that now,
getting out my trusty
calculator, thirty,
is that right?
Thirty.
And is that matrix invertible?
There's an A transpose A.
And it is invertible,
right?
Three, eight is not a multiple
of eight, thirty -- and it's
invertible.
And that's the normal,
that's what I expect.
So this is I want to show.
So here's the final -- here's
the key point.
The null space of A transpose A
-- it's not going to be always
invertible.
Tell me a matrix -- I have to
say that I can't say A transpose
A is always invertible.
Because that's asking too much.
I mean what could the matrix A
be, for example,
so that A transpose A was not
invertible?
Well, it even could be the zero
matrix.
I mean that's like extreme
case.
Suppose I make this rank --
suppose I change to that A.
Now I figure out A transpose A
again and I get -- what do I
get?
I get nine, I get nine of
course and here I get what's
that entry?
Twenty-seven.
And is that matrix invertible?
No.
And why do I -- I knew it
wouldn't be invertible anyway.
Because this matrix only has
rank one.
And if I have a product of
matrices of rank one,
the product is not going to
have a rank bigger than one.
So I'm not surprised that the
answer only has rank one.
And that's what I -- always
happens, that the rank of A
transpose A comes out to equal
the rank of A.
So, yes, so the null space of A
transpose A equals the null
space of A, the rank of A
transpose A equals the rank of
A.
So let's -- as soon as I can
why that's true.
But let's draw from that what
the fact that I want.
This tells me that this square
symmetric matrix is invertible
if -- so here's my conclusion.
A transpose A is invertible if
exactly when --
exactly if this null space is
only got the zero vector.
Which means the columns of A
are independent.
So A transpose A is invertible
exactly if A has independent
columns.
That's the fact that I need
about A transpose A.
And then you'll see next time
how A transpose A enters
everything.
Next lecture is actually a
crucial one.
Here I'm preparing for it by
getting us thinking about A
transpose A.
And its rank is the same as the
rank of A, and we can decide
when it's invertible.
OK.
So I'll see you Friday.
Thanks.