OK.
Uh this is the review lecture
for the first part of the
course, the Ax=b part of the
course.
And the exam will emphasize
chapter three.
Because those are the --0
chapter three was about the
rectangular matrices where we
had null spaces and null spaces
of A transpose,
and ranks, and all the things
that are so clear when the
matrix is square and invertible,
they became things to think
about for rectangular matrices.
So, and vector spaces and
subspaces and above all those
four subspaces.
OK, I'm thinking to start at
least I'll just look at old
exams, read out questions,
write on the board what I need
to and we can see what the
answers are.
The first one I see is one I
can just read out.
Well, I'll write a little.
Suppose u, v and w are nonzero
vectors in R^7.
What are the possible -- they
span a -- a vector space.
They span a subspace of R^7,
and what are the possible
dimensions?
So that's a straightforward
question, what are the possible
dimensions of the subspace
spanned by u,
v and w?
OK, one, two,
or three, right.
One, two or three.
Couldn't be more because we've
only got three vectors,
and couldn't be zero because --
because I told you the vectors
were nonzero.
Otherwise if I allowed the
possibility that those were all
the zero vector --
then the zero-dimensional
subspace would have been in
there.
OK.
Now can I jump to a more
serious question?
OK.
We have a five by three matrix.
And I'm calling it U.
I'm saying it's in echelon
form.
And it has three pivots,
r=3.
Three pivots.
OK.
First question,
what's the null space?
What's the null space of this
matrix U, so this matrix is five
by three, and I find it helpful
to just see visually what five
by three means,
what that shape is.
Three columns.
Three columns in U then,
five rows, three pivots,
and what's the null space?
Regis.
The null space of U is -- and
it asks for a spec-of course I'm
looking for an answer that isn't
just the definition of the null
space, but is the null space of
this matrix, with this
information.
And what is it?
It's only the zero vector.
Because we're told that the
rank is three,
so those three columns must be
independent, no combination --
of those columns is the zero
vector except -- so the only
thing in this null space is the
zero vector, and I --
I could even say what that
vector is, zero,
zero, zero.
That's OK.
So that's what's in the null
space.
All right?
let me go on with -- this
question has multiple parts.
What's the -- oh now it asks
you about a ten by three matrix,
B, which is the matrix U and
two U.
It actually -- I would probably
be writing R -- and maybe I
should be writing R here now.
This exam goes back a few years
when I emphasized U more than R.
Now, what's the echelon form
for that matrix?
So the echelon form,
what's the rank,
and what's the echelon form?
Let's suppose this is in
reduced echelon form,
so that I could be using the
letter R.
So I'll ask for the reduced row
echelon form so imagine that
these are --
U is in reduced row echelon
form but now I've doubled the
height of the matrix,
what will happen when we do row
reduction?
What row reduction will take us
to what matrix here?
So you start doing elimination.
You're doing elimination on
single rows.
But of course we're allowed to
think of blocks.
So what, well,
what's the answer look like?
U and z- or R -- let's -- I'll
stay with this letter U but I'm
really thinking it's in reduced
form, and zero.
OK.
Fine.
Then it asks oh,
further, it asks about this
matrix.
U, U, U, and zero.
OK, what's the echelon form of
this?
So it's just like practice in
thinking through what would row
elimination, what would row
reduction do.
Have I thought this through,
so what -- what are we -- if we
start doing elimination,
basically we're going to
subtract these rows from these
--
so it's going to take us to U,
U, zero, and minus U,
I guess, right?
Take the thing all the way to R
-- let's suppose U is really R.
Suppose that we're really going
for the reduced row echelon
form.
Then would we stop there?
No.
We would clean out,
we would -- we could use this
to -- is that right,
can I so I took this row --
these rows away from these to
get there.
Now I take these rows away from
these, so that gives me zero.
There.
there?1
And now what more would I do if
I'm really shooting for R,
the reduced row echelon form?
I would -- then I want plus
ones in the pivot,
so I would multiply through by
minus one to get plus there.
So essentially I'm seeing
reduced row echelon form there
and there, and there's just one
little twist still to go.
Do you see what that final
twist might be?
To have if -- if U is in
reduced row echelon form and now
I'm looking at U,
U, there's one little step to
take, this isn't like a big deal
at all, but -- but if I really
want this to be in reduced form,
what would I still -- might I
still have to do?
I might have some zero rows
here, I might have some zero
rows here that strictly should
move to the bottom.
Well, I'm not going to make a
project out of that.
first of all?
OK.
What's the rank of that matrix?
What's the rank of this matrix
C?
Given that I know that the
original U has rank three,
what's the rank of this guy?
Six, right.
That has rank six,
I can tell.
What was -- what's the rank of
this B, while -- while we're at
it?
The rank of B,
is that six or three?
Three is right.
Because we actually got it to
where we could just see three
pivots.
OK, and oh, now finally this
easy one, what's the dimension
of the null space -- of the null
space of C transpose?
Oh, boy.
OK, so what do I -- if I want
the dimension of a null space,
I want to know the size of the
matrix --
so what's the size of the
matrix C?
It looks like it's ten by six,
is it?
Ten by six, so C is ten by six,
so m is ten,
so C has ten rows,
C transpose has ten columns,
so there are ten columns there.
So how many free variables have
I got, once I --
There's quite a few trues,
shall I take a poll,
if I start with the ten columns
in C transpose,
that's the m for the original
C.
And what do I subtract off?
Six.
Because we said that was the
rank.
So I'm left with four.
Thanks.
OK.
If b is in the -- and what
would -- what does the exam say
So I think that's the right
answer --
the dimension of the null space
of C transpose would be four.
Right.
OK.
Yeah.
So that's one question,
at least it brought in some --
some of the dimension counts.
OK.
Here's another type of
question.
I give you an equation,
Ax equals two four two.
And I give you the complete
solution.
But I don't give you the
matrix.
And another -- there's another
vector, zero,
zero, one.
OK.
All right.
My first question is what's the
dimension of the row space?
Of the matrix A?
So the main thing that you want
to get from this question is
that a question could start this
way.
Sort of backward way.
so I guess I'm asking you what
is the column space for this
By giving you the answer and
not telling you what the problem
is.
But we can get a lot of
information, and sometimes we
can get complete information
about that matrix A.
OK.
So what's the dimension of the
row space of A?
What's the rank?
Tell me about what's the size
of the matrix,
yeah, just --
These are the things we want to
think about, what's the --
what's the shape of the matrix,
It certainly has three rows.
But is it a- is it three by
three?
So the (x)-s that it multiplies
have three components,
so that --1
does the matrix have three
columns also?
Yes.
So I'm seeing the same length
in b, three, and also in x.
So A is a three by three
matrix.
And what's its rank?
Its rank -- tell me something
about its null space,
I heard the right answer for
the rank, the rank is one in
this case.
Why?
Because the dimension of the
null space, so the dimension of
the null space of A is from
knowing that that's the complete
solution, it's two.
I'm seeing two vectors here,
and they're independent in the
null space of A,
because they have to be in the
null space of A if I'm allowed
to throw into the solution any
amount of those vectors,
that tells me that's the null
space part then.
So the dimension of the null
space is two,
and then I -- of course I know
the dimensions of all the --
four subspaces.
Now actually it asks what's the
matrix?
Well, what's the matrix in this
case?
Do we want to -- shall I try to
figure that out?
Sure.
Let's -- you'd like me to do
it, OK.
So what about the matrix,
or let me at least start it,
OK.
If A times this x gives two,
four, two, what does that tell
me about the matrix A?
If A times that x solves that
equation then it tells me that
the first column is -- the first
column of A is -- one,
two, one, right.
The first column of A has to be
one, two, one,
because if I multiply by x,
that's going to multiply just
matrix?
the first column,
and give me two,
four, two.
And then I've got two more
columns to find,
and what information have I got
to find them with?
A basis for the null space.
I've got the null space.
So the fact that this is in the
null space, what does that tell
me about the matrix?
A matrix that has zero,
zero, one in its null space?
That tells me that the last
column of the matrix is zeroes.
Because this is in the null
space, the last column has to be
zeroes.
And because this is in the null
space, what's the second column?
Well, this in the null space
means that if I multiply A by
that vector I must be getting
zeroes, so I think that better
be minus one,
minus two, and minus one.
OK.
That's a type of question that
just brings out the information
that's in that complete
solution.
OK.
And then actually I go on to
ask what vectors -- for what
vectors B can Ax=b be solved?
Ax=b can be solved if what --
so I'm looking for a condition
on b, if any.
Can it be solved for every
right-hand side b?
No.
Definitely not.
When could it be solved?
Well, what's the ---- I
actually say in this in the
exam, don't just tell me.
In the column space,
because I do know that it can
be solved exactly when B is in
the column space,
So what is if b has the form --
so I guess I'm asking what's
the column space of this matrix,
and what is it?
It's so the column space of
that matrix is all multiples b
-- b is a multiple of one,
two, one.
Right?
I can solve the thing if it's a
multiple of one,
two, one, and of course sure
enough --
yeah, that was a multiple of
one, two, one,
and so I had a solution.
So this is a case where we've
got lots of null space.
Let me just recall rank is big,
don't forget those cases,
don't forget the other cases
when r is as big as it can be,
r equal m or r equal n.
Those are -- we had a full
lecture on that,
the full rank,
full lecture,
and important -- important
case.
OK.
I'll just move on.
I think this is the best type
of review.
It's just brings these ideas
out.
Apologies to the camera while I
recover glasses and exam.
OK.
How about a few true-false
ones?
Actually there won't be a
true-false on the quiz.
But it gives us a moment of
quick review.
Here's one.
If the null space -- I have a
square matrix.
If its null space is just the
zero vector, what about the null
space of A transpose?
If the null space of A is just
the zero vector,
and the matrix is square,
what do I know about the null
space of A transpose?
Also the zero vector.
Good.
And that's a very very
important fact.
OK.
How about this?
These -- look at the space of
five by five matrices as a
vector space.
So it's actually a
twenty-five-dimensional vector
space.
All five by five matrices.
Look at the invertible
matrices.
Do they form a subspace?
So I have this five by --
a space of all five by five
matrices.
I can add them,
I can multiply by numbers.
But now I narrow down to the
invertible ones.
And I ask are they a subspace?
And you -- your answer is --
quiet, but nevertheless
definite, no.
Right?
No.
Because if I add two invertible
matrices I have no idea if the
answer is invertible.
If I multiply that invertible
-- well, it doesn't even have
the zero matrix in it,
it couldn't be a subspace.
I have to be able to multiply
by zero --
and stay in my subspace,
and the invertible ones
wouldn't work.
Well, the singular ones
wouldn't work either.
They have zero -- the zero
matrix is in the singular
matrices, but if I add two
singular matrices I don't know
if the answer is singular or
not.
OK.
So another true-false.
If b squared equals zero then b
equals zero.
True or false?
If b squared equals zero,
true, false?
b squared equals zero,
b has to be a square --
square matrix,
so that I can multiply it by
itself, does that imply that B
is zero?
Are there matrices whose square
could be the zero matrix?
Yes or no?
Yes there are.
There are matrices whose square
is the zero matrix.
So this statement is false.
If b squared is zero,
we don't know that b is zero.
For example -- the best example
is that matrix.
That matrix is a dangerous
matrix.
It will come up in later parts
of this course as an example of
what can go wrong.
And here is a real simple -- so
this -- so if I square that
matrix, I do get the zero
matrix,and it shows --
OK.
A system of m equations in m
unknowns is solvable for every
right-hand side if the columns
are independent.
OK.
So can I say that again,
I'm -- I'll write it down then
for short.
m by m matrix independent
columns then the question is
does Ax=b, is it always
solvable?
And the answer is -- yes or no
-- right.
OK, which -- did you watch that
quiz, there was a quiz program
on TV for a few weeks,
did you see that,
what was the name of that --2
winning a million dollars or
something?
How to be a millionaire?
It was some crazy guy,
what was his name?
It's -- Regis,
right.
OK.2
If you saw this,
like when you should have been
doing linear algebra of course
-- but I didn't have to do the
homework, so I was watching it,
so there were three -- the
interesting -- the novel point
was there were three ways that
you could get help,
right --
but you could only use each way
once, so you couldn't like use
them all the time.
So remember that?
You could -- so you could poll
the audience,
and that was a very -- that was
a hundred percent successful
way, so I'll poll the audience
on this.
If the other possibility --
another possibility you could
call your friend,
right, or he's your friend
until he gives you the wrong
answer, which -- that turned out
to be very unreliable,
you know, you'd call up your
brother or something and ask him
for the capital of whatever,
Bosnia.
What does he know,
he makes some guess,
matrix, independent columns,
is Ax=b always solvable?
Maybe just hands up for that?
A few.
And who says no?
Oh, gosh, this audience is not
reliable.
Fifty fifty.
I guess I'd say,
I'd vote yes.
Because independent columns,
that means that the rank is the
full size m, I have a matrix of
rank m.
That means it's -- I mean it's
square, so it's an invertible
matrix, and nothing could go
wrong.
Yes.
So that's the good case and we
always expect it in chapter two,
but of course chapter three is
-- only one of the
possibilities.
OK.
Let me move on to another
question from an old quiz.
OK.
Let's see.
I'm going to give you a matrix,
but I'm going to give it to you
as a product of a couple of
matrices, one,
one, zero, zero,
one, zero, one,
zero, one, times another
matrix, one, zero,
minus one, two,
zero, one, one,
minus one, and all zeroes.
OK.
I would like to ask you
questions about that matrix
without doing the multiplication
and finding the matrix b.
Can you tell me something -- so
I'll ask questions about this
matrix b and I'll answer them
without multiplying it out.2
For example,
I'm going to ask you for a
basis for the null space.
So I'm going to solve Bx equals
zero.
So give me a basis for --
for the null space of B.
Let's see, what dimension I in
-- the null space of B is a
subspace of R.
What size vectors I looking for
here?
Because if we don't know the
size, we aren't going to find
it, right?
the null -- this matrix is
three by four obviously.
So if we're looking for the
null space we're looking for
those vectors x in R^4.
OK.
So the null space of B is
certainly a subspace of R^4.
What do you think its dimension
is?
Of course once we find the
basis we would know the
dimension immediately,
but let's stop first,
what's the rank of this matrix
B?
Let's see, what -- is that
matrix invertible,
that square one there?
Let's say sure,
I think it is,
yes, that matrix B looks
invertible.
Is that pretty clear?
Yeah.
So I've gone wrong in this
course already,
but I'll still hope that that
matrix is invertible.
Yeah, yeah, because if I look
for a combination of those three
columns --
well, I couldn't use this
middle column because it would
have a one and in a position
that I -- column is otherwise
all zero, so a combination that
gives zero can't give us that
problem, and then the other two
are clearly independent sets --
so that matrix is invertible.
Later we could take a
determinant or other things.
OK.
What's the setup?
If I have an invertible matrix,
a nice invertible square
matrix, times this guy,
times this second factor,
and I'm looking for the null
space, does this have any
effect?
Is the null -- so what I'm
asking is is the null space of B
the same as the null space of
just this part?
I think so.
If Bx is zero,
then multiplying by that guy
I'll still have zero.
But also if this times some x
give zero, I could always
multiply on the left by the
inverse of that,
because it is invertible,
and I would discover that this
kind of Bx is zero.
You want me to write some of
that down --
if I have a product here,
C times -- times D,
say, and if C is invertible,
the null space of CD,
well, it will the same as the
null space of D.
If C is invertible.
Multiplying by an invertible
matrix on the left can't change
the null space.
OK.
So basically I'm asking you for
the null space of this.
so when do I know -- well,
I would say suppose the matrix
I don't have to do the
multiplication because I have C
is invertible.
That first factor C is
invertible.
It's not going to change the
null space.
OK.
So can we just write down a
basis now for the null space?
So what's the basis for the
null space of -- of that?
So basis for the null space I'm
looking for the two -- there are
two pivot columns obviously.
It clearly has rank two.
I'm looking for the two special
solutions.
They'll come from the third and
the fourth.
The free variables.
OK.
so if the third free variable
is a one, then I think probably
I need a minus one there and a
one there, it looks like.
Do you agree that if I then do
that multiplication I'll get
zero?
And if I have one in the fourth
variable, then maybe I need a
one in the second variable and
maybe a minus two in the third.
So I just reasoned that through
and then if I look back I see
sure enough that the free
variable part that I sometimes
call F, that up --
that two by two corner,
is sitting here with all its
signs reversed.
So that's -- here I'm seeing
minus F, and here I'm seeing the
identity in the null space
matrix.
OK, so that's the null space.
Another question is solve Bx
equal one, zero,
one.
OK.
So that's one question,
now solve complete solutions.
To Bx equal one,
zero, one.
OK.
Yeah, so I guess I'm seeing if
I wanted to get one,
zero, one -
What's our particular solution?
So I'm looking for a particular
solution and then the null space
part.
OK.
I-- actually the first column
of B, so what's the first column
of our matrix B?
It's the vector one,
zero, one.
The first column of our matrix
agrees with the right-hand side.
So I guess I'm thinking x
particular plus x null space
will be the particular solution,
since the first column of B is
exactly right,
that's great.
And then I have C times that
first null space vector and D
times the other null space
vector.
Right?
The two -- the null space part
of the solution,
as always has the arbitrary
constants, the particular
solution doesn't have any
arbitrary constants,
it's one particular solution,
and in this case it'll --
that one would do.
OK.
Fine.
so those are questions taken
from old quizzes,
any questions coming to mind?
Yeah.
Q: value.
OK.
Well, so that particular x
particular, it says that let's
see, when I multiply by this
guy, I'm going to get the first
column of B.
That --
if that's a solution,
I multiply B,
B times this x will be the
first column of B,
and so I'm saying that the
first column of this B agrees
with the right-hand side.
So I'm saying that look at the
first column of that matrix B.
If you do the multiplication,
it's -- so what's the first
column of that matrix?
Is that how you do that
multiplication?
I multiply that matrix by that
first column.
And it picks out one,
zero, one.
So the first column of B is
exactly that.
And therefore a particular
solution will be this guy.
Yeah.
OK.
Yes.
Q: particular solution.
Any of the solutions can be the
particular one that we pick out.
So like this plus -- plus this
would be another particular
solution.
It would be another solution.
The particular is just telling
us only take one.
But it's not telling us which
one we have to take.
We take the most convenient
one.
I guess in this -- in this
problem that was that one.
Good.
Other questions?
Yes.
And this pattern of particular
plus null space,
of course, that's going
throughout mathematics of linear
systems.
We're really doing mathematics
of linear systems here.
Our systems are discrete and
they're finite-dimensional --
and so it's linear algebra,
but this particular plus null
space goes -- that doesn't
depend on having finite matrices
-- that spreads much -- that
spreads everywhere.
OK, I'm going to just like to
encourage you to take problems
out of the book,
let me do the same myself.
OK well here's some easy true
or falses.
I don't know why the author put
these in here.
OK.
If m=n, then the row space
equals the column space.
So these are true or falses.
If m equals n,
so that means the matrix is
square, then the row space
equals the column space?
False, good.
Good, what is equal there?
What can I say is equal,
if M -- well,
yeah.
Yeah it -- so that's definitely
false --
the row space and the column
space, and this matrix is like
always a good example to
consider.
So there's a square matrix but
it's row space is the multiples
of zero, one,
and its column space is the
multiples of one,
zero.
Very different.
The row space and the column
space are totally different for
that matrix.
Now of course if the matrix was
symmetric, well,
then clearly the row space
equals the column space.
OK.
How about this question?
The matrices A and minus A
share the same four subspaces?
Do the matrices A and minus A
have the same column space,
do they have the same null
space, do they have the same row
space?
What's the answer on that?
Yes or no.
Yes.
Good.
OK.
How about this?
If A and B have the same four
subspaces, then A is a multiple
of B.
If -- suppose those subspaces
are the same.
Then is A a multiple of B?
OK.
How how do you answer a
question like that?
Of course if you want to answer
it yes, then I would --
then they'd have to think of a
reason why.
If you want to answer no way,
then you would -- and I would
sort of like first I would try
to think no, I would say can I
come up with an example where it
isn't true?
Let me repeat the question.
And then write the answer.
OK.
So I'll repeat that question.
If -- so true or false,
if A and B have the same four
subspaces, then A is some
multiple of B.
True or false,
how do you feel about it at
this instant?3
so how many think true?
OK.
I gave you every chance to
think about that.
Let's see.
So what -- I would just take
extreme cases if it was me,
is invertible --
suppose A is an invertible
matrix, then what -- suppose
it's six by six invertible
matrix, then what's its row
space, and its column space is
all of R^6, and the null space,
and the null space of A
transpose would be the zero
vector.
So every invertible matrix is
going to give that answer.
If I have a six by six
invertible matrix,
I know what those subspaces
are.
Heck, that was back in chapter
two, when I didn't even know
what subspaces were.
The row space and column space
are both all six-dimensional
space --
the whole space,
and the rank is six,
in other words,
and the null spaces have zero
dimension.
So do you see now the answer?
So A and B could be.
So A and B could be for example
any -- so I'm going to say
false.
Because A and B for example --
So an example:
A and B any invertible six by
six, six by six.
So those would have the same
four subspaces but they wouldn't
be the same.
Of course th- there should be
something about those matrices
that would be the same.
It's sort of a natural problem,
so now actually we're getting
to a math question.
The answer is this is not true.
One matrix doesn't have to be a
multiple of the other.
But there must be something
that's true.
And that would be sort of like
a natural question to ask.
If they have the same
subspaces, same four subspaces,
then what -- what could you --
instinct wasn't necessarily
right.
But I hope you now see that the
correct answer is false.
And then you might think OK,
well, they certainly do have
the same rank.
But do -- obviously if they
have the same four subspaces,
they have the same rank.
I might say if they have the
well, I could extend that
question and think about other
possibilities and finally come
up with something that was true.
But I won't press that one.
Let me keep going with practice
questions.
And these practice questions
are quite appropriate I think
for the exam.
OK.
let's see.
If I exchange two rows of A
which subspaces stay the same?
So I'm trying to take out
questions that we can answer
without you know we can answer
quickly.
If I have a matrix A,
and I exchange two of its rows,
which subspaces stay the same?
The row space does stay the
same.
And the null space stays the
Good.
Correct.
Column space would be a wrong
answer.
OK.
all right, here's a question.
Oh, this leads into the next
chapter.
Why can the vector one,
two, three not be a row and
also in the null space?
Fitting we close with this
question.
Close is --
so V equal this one,
two, three can't be in the null
space of a matrix and the row
space.
And my question is why not?
Why not?
So this is a question that we
can because it's sort of asked
in a straightforward way,
we can figure out an answer.
Well, actually yeah -- I'll
even pin it down,
it can't be in the null space
-- and be a row.
I'll even pin it down further.
Ask it to be a row of A.
Why not?
So I'm -- we know the
dimensions of these spaces.
But now I'm asking you sort of
like the overlap between -- so
the null space and the row
space, those are in the same
n-dimensional space.
Those are -- well,
those are both subspaces of
n-dimensional space,
and I'm basically saying they
can't overlap.
I can't have a vector like
this, a typical vector,
that's in the null space and
it's also a row of the matrix.
Why is that?
So that's a new sort of idea.
Let's just see what it would
mean.
I mean that A times this V,
why can this A times this V it
can't be zero.
Oh well, if it's zero,
so this is -- I'm getting it
into the null space here.
So this is -- now let's put
that vector's in the null space,
why can't the first row of a
matrix be one,
two, three?
I can fill out the matrix as I
like.
Why is that impossible?
Well, you're seeing it's
impossible, right?
That if that was a row of the
matrix and in the null space,
that number would not be zero,
it would be fourteen.
Right.
So now we actually are
beginning to get a more complete
picture of these four subspaces.
The two that are over in
n-dimensional space,
they actually only share the
zero vector.
The intersection of the null
space and the row space is only
the zero vector.
And in fact the null space is
perpendicular to the row space.
That'll be the first topic
let's see, we have a holiday
Monday --
and I'll see you Wednesday with
perpendiculars.
And I'll see you Friday.
So good luck on the quiz.