OK, when the camera says,
we'll start.
You want to give me a signal?
OK, this is lecture eight in
linear algebra,
and this is the lecture where
we completely solve linear
equations.
So Ax=b.
That's our goal.
If it has a solution.
It certainly can happen that
there is no solution.
We have to identify that
possibility by elimination.
And then if there is a solution
we want to find out is there
only one solution or are -- is
there a whole family of
solutions, and then find them
all.
OK.
Can I use as an example the
same matrix that I had last time
when we were looking for the
null space.
So the, the matrix has rows 1 2
2 2, 2 4 6 8,
and the third row -- you
remember the main point was the
third row, 3 6 8 10,
is the sum of row one plus row
two.
In other words,
if I add those left-hand sides,
I get the third left-hand side.
So you can tell me right away
what elimination is going to
discover about the right-hand
sides.
What's -- there is a condition
on b1, b2, and b3 for this
system to have a solution.
Most cases -- if I took these
numbers to be one --
5, and 17, there would not be a
solution.
In fact, if I took those first
numbers to be 1 and 5,
what is the only b3 that would
be OK?
Six.
If the left-hand -- if these
left-hand sides add up to that,
then B --
I need b1 plus b2 to equal b3.
Let's just see how elimination
discovers that.
But we can see it coming,
right?
That if -- let me say it in
other words.
If some combination on the
left-hand side gives all 0s then
the same combination on the
right-hand side must give 0.
OK.
So let me take that example and
write down instead of copying
out all the plus signs,
let me write down the matrix.
1 2 2 2, 2 4 6 8,
and that 6 3 8 10,
where the third row is the sum
of the first two rows.
Now how do we deal with the
right-hand side?
That's -- we want to do the
same thing to the right-hand
side that we're doing to these
rows on the left side,
so we just tack on the
right-hand side as another
vector, another column.
So this is the augmented
matrix.
It's, it's the matrix A with
the vector b tacked on.
In Matlab, that's all you would
need to type.
OK.
So we do elimination on that.
Can we just do elimination
quickly?
The first pivot is fine,
I subtract two of this away
from this, three of this away
from this, so I have 1 2 2 2 b1.
Two of those away will give me
0 0 2 and 4, and that was b2
minus two b1.
I, I have to do the same thing
to that third,
that last column.
And then three of these away
from this gave me 0 0 2 4 b3
minus three b1s.
So that's the,
that's elimination with the
first column completed.
We move on.
There's the first pivot still.
Here is the second pivot.
We're always remembering,
now, these are then going to be
the pivot columns.
And let me get the final result
-- well, let me -- can I do it
by eraser?
We're capable of subtracting
this row from this row,
just by -- that'll knock this
out completely and give me the
row of 0s, and on the right-hand
side, when I subtract this away
from this, what do I have?
I think I have b3 minus a b2,
and I had minus three b1s.
This is going to,
it's going to be a minus a b1.
Oh yeah that's exactly what I
expect.
So now the -- what's the last
equation?
The last equation,
this represented by this zero
row, that last equation is,
says 0 equals b3 minus b2 minus
b1.
So that's the condition for
solvability.
That's the condition on the
right-hand side that we
expected.
It says that b1+b2 has to match
b3, and if our numbers happen to
have been 1, 5,
and 6 -- so let me take,
suppose b is 1 5 6.
That's an OK b.
And when I do this elimination,
what will I have?
The b1 will still be a 1.
b2 would be 5 minus 2,
this would be a 3.
5 -- my 6 minus 5 minus 1,
this will be -- this is the
main point -- this will be a 0,
thanks.
OK.
So the last equation is OK now.
And I can proceed to solve the
two equations that are really
there with four unknowns.
OK, I, I, I want to do that,
so this, this b is OK.
It allows a solution.
We're going to be,
naturally, interested to keep
track what are the conditions on
b that make the equation
solvable.
So let me write down what we
already see before I continue to
solve it.
Let me first -- solvability,
solvability.
So which -- so this is the
condition on the right-hand
sides.
And what is that condition?
This is solvability always of
Ax=b.
So Ax=b is solvable --
well, actually,
we had an answer in the
language of the column space.
Can you remind me what that
answer is?
That, that was like our answer
from earlier lecture.
b had to be in the column
space.
Solvable if -- when -- exactly
when b is in the column space of
A.
Right?
That just says that b has to be
a combination of the columns,
and of course that's exactly
what the equation is looking
for.
So that -- now I want to answer
it -- the same answer but in
different language.
Another way to answer this --
if a combination of the rows of
A gives the zero row,
and this was an example where
it happened, some combination of
the rows of A produced the zero
row -- then what's the
requirement on b?
Since we're going to do the
same thing to both sides of all
equations --
the same combination of the
components of b has to give 0.
Right?
That's -- so if there's a
combination of the rows that
gives the zero row,
then the same combination of
the entries of b must give 0.
And this isn't the zero row,
that's the zero number.
OK.
Tthis is another way of saying
-- and it is not immediate,
right, that these two
statements are equivalent.
But somehow they must be,
because they're both equivalent
to the solvability of the
system.
OK.
So we've got this,
this sort of -- like question
zero is, does the system have a
solution?
OK, I'll come back to discuss
that further.
Let's go forward when it does.
When there is a solution.
And so what's our job now?
Abstractly we sit back and we
say, OK, there's a solution,
finished.
It exists.
But we want to construct it.
So what's the algorithm,
the sequence of steps to find
the solution?
That's what I -- and of course
the quiz and the final,
I'm going to give you a system
Ax=b and I'm going to ask you
for the solution,
if there is one.
And so this algorithm that you
want to follow.
OK, let's see.
So what's the -- so now to find
the complete solution to Ax=b.
OK.
Let me start by finding one
solution, one particular
solution.
I'm expecting that I can,
because my system of equations
now, that last equation is zero
equals zero, so that's all fine.
I really have two equations --
actually I've got four unknowns,
so I'm expecting to find not
only a solution but a whole
bunch of them.
But let's just find one.
So step one,
a particular solution,
x particular.
How do I find one particular
solution?
Well, let me tell you how I,
how I find it.
So this is -- since there are
lots of solutions,
you could have your own way to
find a particular one.
But this is a pretty natural
way.
Set all free variables to zero.
Since those free variables are
the guys that can be anything,
the most convenient choice is
zero.
And then solve Ax=b for the
pivot variables.
So what does that mean in this
example?
Which are the free variables?
Which, which are the variables
that we can assign freely and
then there's one and only one
way to find the pivot variables?
They're x2 and -- so x2 is
zero, because that's in a column
without a pivot,
the second column has no pivot.
And the -- what's the other
one?
The fourth, x4 is zero.
Because that,
those are the,
the free ones.
Those are in the columns with
no pivots.
So you see what my -- so when I
knock -- when x2 and x4 are
zero, I'm left with the -- what
I left with here?
I'm just left with -- see,
now I'm not using the two free
columns.
I'm only using the pivot
So I'm really left with x1 --
the first equation is just x1
and two x3s should be the
right-hand side,
which we picked to be a one.
And the second equation is two
x3s, as it happened,
turned out to be,
three.
I just write it again here with
the x2 and the x4 knocked out,
since we're set them to zero.
And you see that we're back in
the normal case of having back
-- where back substitution will
do it.
So x3 is three halves,
and then we go back up and x1
is one minus two x3.
That's probably minus two.
Good.
So now we have the solution,
x particular is the vector
minus two zero three halves
zero.
OK, good.
That's one particular solution,
and we should and could plug it
into the original system.
Really if -- on the quiz,
please, it's a good thing to
do.
So we did all this,
these, row operations,
but this is supposed to solve
the original system,
and I think it does.
OK.
So that's x particular which
we've got.
So that's like what's new
today.
The particular solution comes
-- first you check that you have
zero equals zero,
so you're OK on the last
equations.
And then you set the free
variables to zero,
solve for the pivot variables,
and you've got a particular
solution, the particular
solution that has zero free
variables.
OK.
Now -- but that's only one
solution, and now I'm looking
for all.
So how do I find the rest?
The point is I can add on x --
anything out of the null space.
We know how to find the vectors
in the null space --
because we did it last time,
but I'll remind you what we
got.
And then I'll add.
So the final result will be
that the complete solution --
this is now the complete guy --
the complete solution is this
one particular solution plus
any, any vector,
all different vectors out of
the null space.
xn, OK.
Well why, why this pattern,
because this pattern shows up
through all of mathematics,
because it shows up everywhere
we have linear equations.
Let me just put here the,
the reason.
A xp, so that's x particular,
so what does Ax particular
give?
That gives the correct
right-hand side b.
And what does A times an x in
the null space give?
Zero.
So I add, and I put in
parentheses.
So xp plus xn is b plus zero,
which is b.
So -- oh, what I saying?
Let me just say it in words.
If I have one solution,
I can add on anything in the
null space, because anything in
the null space has a zero
right-hand side,
and I still have the correct
right-hand side B.
So that's my system.
That's my complete solution.
Now let me write out what that
will be for this example.
So in this example,
x general, x complete,
the complete solution,
is x particular,
which is minus two zero three
halves zero, with those zeroes
in the free variable,
plus --
you remember there were the
special solutions in the null
space that had a one in the free
variables -- or one and zero in
the free variables,
and then we filled in to find
the others?
I've forgotten what they were,
but maybe it was that.
That was a special solution,
and then there was another
special solution that had that
free variable zero and this free
variable equal one,
and I have to fill those in.
Let's see, can I remember how
those fill in?
Maybe this was a minus two and
this was a two,
possibly?
I think probably that's right.
I'm not -- yeah.
Does that look write to you?
I would have to remember what
are my equations.
Can I, rather than go way back
to that board,
let me remember the first
equation was two x3 plus two x4
equaling zero now,
because I'm looking for the
guys in the null space.
So I set x4 to be one and the
second equation,
that I didn't copy again,
gave me minus two for this and
then -- yeah,
so I think that's right.
Two minus four and two gives
zero, check.
OK.
Those were the special
solutions.
What do we do to get the
complete solution?
How do I get the complete
solution now?
I multiply this by anything,
c1, say, and I multiply this by
anything -- I take any
combination.
Remember that's how we
described the null space?
The null space consists of all
combinations of --
so this is xn -- all
combinations of the special
solutions.
There were two special
solutions because there were two
free variables.
And we want to make that count
-- carefully now.
Just while I'm up here.
So there's, that's what the --
that's the kind of answer I'm
looking for.
Is there a constant multiplying
this guy?
Is there a free constant that
multiplies x particular?
No way.
Right?
x particular solves A xp=b.
I'm not allowed to multiply
that by three.
But Axn, I'm allowed to
multiply xn by three,
or add to another xn,
because I keep getting zero on
the right.
OK.
So, so again,
xp is one particular guy.
xn is a whole subspace.
Right?
It's one guy plus,
plus anything from a subspace.
Let me draw it.
Let me try to -- oh.
I want to draw,
I want to graph all this -- I
want to, I want to plot all
solutions.
Now x.
So what dimension I in?
This is a unfortunate point.
How many components does x
have?
Four.
There are four unknowns.
So I have to draw a four
dimensional picture on this MIT
cheap blackboard.
OK.
So here we go.
x1 -- Einstein could do it,
but, this, this is -- those are
four perpendicular axes in --
representing four dimensional
space.
OK.
Where are my solutions?
Do my solutions form a
subspace?
Does the set of solutions to
Ax=b form a subspace?
No way.
What does it actually look
like, though?
A subspace is in this picture.
This part is a subspace,
right?
That part is some,
like, two dimensional,
because I've got two
parameters, so it's -- I'm
thinking of this null space as a
two dimensional subspace inside
R^4.
Now I have to tell you and will
tell you next time,
what does it mean to say a
subspace, what's the dimension
of a subspace.
But you see what it's going to
be.
It's the number of free
independent constants that we
can choose.
So somehow there'll be a two
dimensional subspace,
not a line, and not a three
dimensional plane,
but only a two dimensional guy.
But it's doesn't go through the
origin because it goes through
this point.
So there's x particular.
x particular is somewhere here.
x particular.
So it's somehow a subspace --
can I try to draw it that way?
It's a two dimensional subspace
that goes through x particular
and then onwards by -- so
there's x particular,
and I added on xn,
and there's x.
There's x=xp+xn.
But the xn was anywhere in this
subspace, so that filled out a
plane.
It's a subspace -- it's not a
subspace, what I saying?
It's like a flat thing,
it's like a subspace,
but it's been shifted,
away from the origin.
It doesn't contain zero.
OK.
Thanks.
That's the picture,
and that's the algorithm.
So the algorithm is just go
through elimination and,
find the particular solution,
and then find those special
solutions.
You can do that.
Let me take our time here in
the lecture to think,
about the bigger picture.
So let me think about -- so
this is my pattern.
Now I want to think -- I want
to ask you about a question -- I
want to ask you some questions.
So when I mean think bigger,
I mean I'll think about an m by
n matrix A of rank r.
OK.
What's our definition of rank?
Our current definition of rank
is number of pivots.
OK.
First of all,
how are these numbers related?
Can you tell me a relation
between r and m?
If I have m rows in the matrix
and R pivots,
--
then I certainly know,
always -- what relation do I
know between r and m?
r is less or equal,
right?
Because I've got m rows,
I can't have more than m
pivots, I might have m and I
might have fewer.
Also, I've got n columns.
So what's the relation between
r and n?
It's the same,
less or equal,
because a column can't have
more than one pivot.
So I can't have more than n
pivots altogether.
OK, OK.
So I have an m by n matrix of
rank r.
And I always know r less than
or equal to m,
r less than or equal to n.
Now I'm specially interested in
the case of full rank,
when the rank r is as big as it
can be.
Well, I guess I've got two
separate possibilities here,
depending on what these numbers
m and n are.
So let me talk about the case
of full column rank.
And by that I mean r=n.
And I want to ask you,
what does that imply about our
solutions?
What does that tell us about
the null space?
What does that tell us about,
the complete solution?
OK, so what does that mean?
So I want to ask you,
well, OK, if the rank is n,
what does that mean?
That means there's a pivot in
every column.
So how many pivot variables are
there?
n.
All the columns have pivots in
this case.
So how many free variables are
there?
None at all.
So no free variables.
r=n, no free variables.
So what does that tell us about
what's going to happen then in
our, in our little algorithms?
What will be in the null space?
The null space of A has got
what in it?
Only the zero vector.
There are no free variables to
give other values to.
So the null space is only the
zero vector.
And what about our solution to
Ax=b?
Solution to Ax=b?
What, what's the story on that
one?
So now that's coming from
today's lecture.
The solution x is -- what's the
complete solution?
It's just x particular,
right?
If, if, if there is an x,
if there is a solution.
It's x equal x particular.
There's nothing -- you know,
there's just one solution.
If there's one at all.
So it's unique solution --
unique means only one -- unique
solution if it exists,
if it exists.
In other words,
I would say -- let me put it a
different way.
There're either zero or one
solutions.
This is all in this case r=n.
So I'm -- because many,
many applications in reality,
the columns will be what I'll
later call independent.
And we'll have,
nothing to look for in the null
space, and we'll only have
particular solutions.
OK.
Everybody see that possibility?
But I need an example,
right?
So let me create an example.
What sort of a matrix --
what's the shape of a matrix
that has full column rank?
So can I squeeze in an,
an example here?
If it exists.
Let me put in an example,
and it's just the right space
to put in an example.
Because the example will be
like tall and thin.
It will have -- well,
I mean, here's an example,
one two six five,
three one one one.
Brilliant example.
OK.
So there's a matrix A,
and what's its rank?
What's the rank of that matrix?
How many pivots will I find if
I do elimination?
Two, right?
Two.
I see a pivot there -- oh
certainly those two columns are
headed off in different
directions.
When I do elimination,
I'll certainly get another
pivot here, fine,
and I can use those to clean
out below and above.
So the -- actually,
tell me what its row reduced
row echelon form would be.
Can you carry that,
that elimination process to the
bitter end?
So what do, what does that
mean?
I subtract a multiple of this
row from these rows.
So I clean up,
all zeros there.
Then I've got some pivot here.
What do I do with that?
I go subtract it below and
above, and then I divide
through, and what's R for that
example?
Maybe I can -- you'll allow me
to put that just here in the
next board.
What's the row reduced echelon
form, just out of practice,
for that matrix?
It's got ones in the pivots.
It's got the identity matrix,
a little two by two identity
matrix, and below it all zeros.
That's a matrix that really has
two independent rows,
and they're the first two,
actually.
The first two rows are
independent.
They're not in the same
direction.
But the other rows are
combinations of the first two,
so -- is there always a
solution to Ax=b?
Tell me what's the picture
here?
For this matrix A,
this is a case of full column
rank.
The two columns are -- give two
pivots.
There's nothing in the null
space.
There's no combination of those
columns that gives the zero
column except the zero zero
combination.
So there's nothing in the null
space.
But is there always a solution
to A X equal B?
What's up with A X equal B?
I've got four,
four equations here,
and only two Xs.
So the answer is certainly no.
There's not always a solution.
I may have zero solutions,
and if I make a random choice,
I'll have zero solutions.
Or if I make a great particular
choice of the right-hand side,
which just happens to be a
combination of those two guys --
like tell me one right-hand side
that would have a solution.
Tell me a right-hand side that
would have a solution.
Well, 0 0 0 0,
OK.
No prize for that one.
Tell me another one.
Another right-hand side that
has a solution would be 4 3 7 6.
I could add the two columns.
Right?
What would be the total
complete solution if the
right-hand side was 4 3 7 6?
There would be the particular
solution one one,
one of that column plus one of
that, and that would be the only
solution.
So there would be -- x
particular would be one one in
the case when the right side is
the sum of those two columns,
and that's it.
So that would be a case with
one solution.
OK.
That, this is the typical setup
with full column rank.
Now I go to full row rank.
You see the sort of natural
symmetry of this discussion.
Full row rank means r=m.
So this is what I'm interested
in now, r=m.
OK, what's up with that?
How many pivots?
m.
So what happens when we do
elimination in that case?
I'm going to get m pivots.
So every row has a pivot,
right?
Every row has a pivot.
Then what about solvability?
What about this business of --
for which right-hand sides can
I solve it?
So that's my question.
I can solve Ax=b for which
right-hand sides?
Do you see what's coming?
I do elimination,
I don't get any zero rows.
So there aren't any
requirements on b.
I can solve Ax=b for every b.
I can solve Ax=b for every
right-hand side.
So this is the existence,
exists a solution.
Now tell me,
so the, u- u- so every row has
a pivot in it.
So how many free variables are
there?
How many free variables in this
case?
If I had n variables to start
with, how many are used up by
pivot variables?
r, which is m.
So I'm left with,
left with n-r free variables.
OK.
So this case of full row rank I
can always solve,
and then this tells me how many
variables are free,
and this is of course n-m.
This is n-m free variables.
Can I do an example?
You know, the best way for me
to do an example is just to
transpose that example.
So let me take,
let me take that matrix that
had column one two six five and
make it a row.
And let me take three one one
one as the second row.
And let me ask you,
this is my matrix A,
what's its rank?
What's the rank of that matrix?
Sorry to ask,
but not sorry really,
because we're just getting the
idea of rank.
What's the rank of that matrix?
Two, exactly,
two.
There will be two pivots.
What will the row reduced
echelon form be?
Anybody know that one?
Actually, tell me not only --
you have to tell me not only
the, there'll be two pivots but
which will be the pivot columns.
Which columns of this matrix
will be pivot columns?
So the first column is fine,
and then I go on to the next
column, and what do I get?
Do I get a second pivot out of
--
will I get a second pivot in
this position?
Yes.
So the pivots,
when I get all the way to R,
will be there.
And here will be some numbers.
This is the part that I
previously called F.
This is the part that --
the pivot columns in R will be
the identity matrix.
There are no zero rows,
no zero rows,
because the rank is two.
But there'll be stuff over
here.
And that will,
enter the special solutions and
the null space.
OK.
So this is a typical matrix
with r=m smaller than n.
Now finally I've got a space
here for r=m=n.
I'm off in the corner here with
the most important case of all.
So what's up with this matrix?
So let me give an example.
OK, brilliant example,
1 2 3 1.
Tell me what -- how do I
describe a matrix that has rank
r=m=n?
So the matrix is square,
right, it's a square matrix.
And if I know its rank is --
it's full rank,
now.
I don't have to say full column
rank or full row rank --
I just say full rank,
because the count,
column count and the row count
are the same,
and the rank is as big as it
can be.
And what kind of a matrix have
I got?
It's invertible.
So that's exactly the
invertible matrices.
r=m=n means the --
what's the row echelon form,
the reduced row echelon form,
for an invertible matrix?
For a square,
nice, square,
invertible matrix?
It's I.
Right.
So you see that the,
the good matrices are the ones
that kind of come out trivially
in R.
You reduce them all the way to
the identity matrix.
What's the null space for this,
for this matrix?
Can I just hammer away with
questions?
What's the null space for this
matrix?
The null space of that matrix
is the zero vector only.
The zero vector only.
What are the conditions to
solve Ax=b?
Which right-hand sides b are
OK?
If I want to solve Ax=b for
this example,
so A is this,
b is b1 b2, what are the
conditions on b1 and b2?
None at all,
right.
So this is the case,
this is the case where I can
solve -- so I've coming back
here, I can -- since the rank
equals m, I can solve for every
b.
And since the rank is also n,
there's a unique solution.
Let me summarize the whole
picture here.
Here's the whole picture.
I could have r=m=n.
This is the case where this is
the identity matrix.
And this is the case where
there is one solution.
That's the square invertible
chapter two case.
Now we're into chapter three.
We could have r=m smaller than
n.
Now that's what we had over
there, and the row echelon form
looked like the identity with
some zero rows.
And that was the case where
there are zero or one solution.
When I say solution I mean to
Ax=b.
So this case,
there's always one.
This case there's zero or one.
And now let me take the case of
full column rank,
but some, extra rows.
So now R has -- well,
the identity -- I'm almost
tempted to write the identity
matrix and then F,
but that isn't necessarily
right.
I have -- is that right?
Am I getting this correct here?
Oh, I'm not!
My God!
This is the case R equals n,
the columns,
the columns are,
are OK.
That's the case that was on
that board, r=n,
full column rank.
Now I want the case where m is
smaller than n and I've got
extra columns.
OK.
There we go.
So this is now the case of full
row rank, and it looks like I F
except that I can't be sure that
the pivot columns are the first
columns.
So the I and the F,
could be partly mixed into the
I.
Can I write that with just like
that?
So the F could be sort of
partly into the I if the first
columns weren't the pivot
columns.
Now how many solutions in this
case?
There's always a solution.
This is the existence case.
We're not getting any zero
rows.
There are no zero rows here.
So there's always either one or
infinitely many solutions.
OK.
Actually, I guess there's
always an infinite number,
because we always have some
null space to deal with.
Then the final case is where r
is smaller than m and smaller
than n.
OK.
Now that's the case where R is
the identity with some free
stuff but with some zero rows
too.
And that's the case where
there's either no solution --
because we didn't get a zero
equals zero for some bs,
or infinitely many solutions.
OK.
Do you -- this board really
summarizes the lecture,
and this sentence summarizes
the lecture.
The rank tells you everything
about the number of solutions.
That number,
the rank r, tells you all the
information except the exact
entries in the solutions.
For that you go to the matrix.
OK, good.
Have a great weekend,
and I'll see you on Monday.