OK, this is the lecture on
linear transformations.
Actually, linear algebra
courses used to begin with this
lecture, so you could say I'm
beginning this course again by
talking about linear
transformations.
In a lot of courses,
those come first before
matrices.
The idea of a linear
transformation makes sense
without a matrix,
and physicists and other --
some people like it better that
way.
They don't like coordinates.
They don't want those numbers.
They want to see what's going
on with the whole space.
But, for most of us,
in the end, if we're going to
compute anything,
we introduce coordinates,
and then every linear
transformation will lead us to a
matrix.
And then, to all the things
that we've done about null space
and row space,
and determinant,
and eigenvalues -- all will
come from the matrix.
But, behind it -- in other
words, behind this is the idea
of a linear transformation.
Let me give an example of a
linear transformation.
So, example.
Example one.
A projection.
I can describe a projection
without telling you any matrix,
anything about any matrix.
I can describe a projection,
say, this will be a linear
transformation that takes,
say, all of R^2,
every vector in the plane,
into a vector in the plane.
And this is the way people
describe, a mapping.
It takes every vector,
and so, by what rule?
So, what's the rule,
is, I take a -- so here's the
plane, this is going to be my
line, my line through my line,
and I'm going to project every
vector onto that line.
So if I take a vector like b --
or let me call the vector v for
the moment -- the projection --
the linear transformation is
going to produce this vector as
T(v).
So T -- it's like a function.
Exactly like a function.
You give me an input,
the transformation produces the
output.
So transformation,
sometimes the word map,
or mapping is used.
A map between inputs and
outputs.
So this is one particular map,
this is one example,
a projection that takes every
vector -- here,
let me do another vector v,
or let me do this vector w,
what is T(w)?
You see?
There are no coordinates here.
I've drawn those axes,
but I'm sorry I drew them,
I'm going to remove them,
that's the whole point,
is that we don't need axes,
we just need -- so guts -- get
it out of there,
I'm not a physicist,
so I draw those axes.
So the input is w,
the output of the projection
is, project on that line,
T(w).
OK.
Now, I could think of a lot of
transformations T.
But, in this linear algebra
course, I want it to be a linear
transformation.
So here are the rules for a
linear transformation.
Here, see, exactly,
the two operations that we can
do on vectors,
adding and multiplying by
scalars, the transformation does
something special with respect
to those operations.
So, for example,
the projection is a linear
transformation because --
for example,
if I wanted to check that one,
if I took v to be twice as
long, the projection would be
twice as long.
If I took v to be minus -- if I
changed from v to minus v,
the projection would change to
a minus.
So c equal to two,
c equal minus one,
any c is OK.
So you see that actually,
those combine,
I can combine those into one
statement.
What the transformation does to
any linear combination,
it must produce the same
combination of T(v) and T(w).
Let's think about some --
I mean, it's like,
not hard to decide,
is a transformation linear or
is it not.
Let me give you an example so
you can tell me the answer.
Suppose my transformation is --
here's another example two.
Shift the whole plane.
So here are all my vectors,
my plane, and every vector v in
the plane, I shift it over by,
let's say, three by some vector
v0.
Shift whole plane by v0.
So every vector in the plane --
this was v, T(v) will be v+v0.
There's T(v).
Here's v0.
There's the typical v.
And there's T(v).
You see what this
transformation does?
Takes this vector and adds to
it.
Adds a fixed vector to it.
Well, that seems like a pretty
reasonable, simple
transformation,
but is it linear?
The answer is no,
it's not linear.
Which law is broken?
Maybe both laws are broken.
Let's see.
If I double the length of v,
does the transformation produce
something double -- do I double
T(v)?
No.
If I double the length of v,
in this transformation,
I'm just adding on the same one
-- same v0, not two v0s,
but only one v0 for every
vector, so I don't get two times
the transform.
Do you see what I'm saying?
That if I double this,
then the transformation starts
there and only goes one v0 out
and doesn't double T(v).
In fact, a linear
transformation -- what is T of
zero?
That's just like a special
case, but really worth noticing.
The zero vector in a linear
transformation must get
transformed to zero.
It can't move,
because, take any vector V here
--
well, so you can see why T of
zero is zero.
Take v to be the zero vector,
take c to be three.
Then we'd have T of zero vector
equaling three T of zero vector,
the T of zero has to be zero.
OK.
So, this example is really a
non-example.
Shifting the whole plane is not
a linear transformation.
Or if I cooked up some formula
that involved squaring,
or the transformation that,
also non-example,
how about the transformation
that, takes any vector and
produces its length?
So there's a transformation
that takes any vector,
say, any vector in R^3,
let me just -- I'll just get a
chance to use this notation
again.
Suppose I think of the
transformation that takes any
vector in R^3 and produces this
number.
So that, I could say,
is a member of R^1,
for example,
if I wanted.
Or just real numbers.
That's certainly not linear.
It's true that the zero vector
goes to zero.
But if I double a vector,
it does double the length,
that's true.
But suppose I multiply a vector
by minus two.
What happens to its length?
It just doubles.
It doesn't get multiplied by
minus two.
So when c is minus two in my
requirement, I'm not satisfying
that requirement.
So T of minus v is not minus v
-- minus, the length,
it's just the length.
OK, so that's another
non-example.
Projection was an example,
let me give you another
example.
I can stay here and have a --
this will be an example that is
a linear transformation,
a rotation.
Rotation by -- what shall we
say?
By 45 degrees.
OK?
So again, let me choose this,
this will be a mapping,
from the whole plane of
vectors, into the whole plane of
vectors, and it just -- here is
the input vector v,
and the output vector foam this
45 degree rotation is just
rotate that thing by 45 degrees,
T(v).
So every vector got rotated.
You see that I can describe
this without any coordinates.
And see that it's linear.
If I doubled v,
the rotation would just be
twice as far out.
If I had v+w,
and if I rotated each of them
and added, the answer's the same
as if I add and then rotate.
That's what the linear
transformation is.
OK, so those are two examples.
Two examples,
projection and rotation,
and I could invent more that
are linear transformations where
I haven't told you a matrix yet.
Actually, the book has a
picture of the action of linear
transformations -- actually,
the cover of the book has it.
So, in this section seven point
one, we can think of a --
actually, here let's take this
linear transformation,
rotation, suppose I have,
as the cover of the book has,
a house in R^2.
So instead of this,
let me take a small house in
R^2.
So that's a whole lot of
points.
The idea is,
with this linear
transformation,
that I can see what it does to
everything at once.
I don't have to just take one
vector at a time and see what T
of V is, I can take all the
vectors on the outline of the
house, and see where they all
go.
In fact, that will show me
where the whole house goes.
So what will happen with this
particular linear
transformation?
The whole house will rotate,
so the result,
if I can draw it,
will be, the house will be
sitting there.
OK.
And, but suppose I give some
other examples.
Oh, let me give some examples
that involve a matrix.
Example three -- and this is
important -- coming from a
matrix at -- we always call A.
So the transformation will be,
multiply by A.
There is a linear
transformation.
And a whole family of them,
because every matrix produces a
transformation by this simple
rule, just multiply every vector
by that matrix,
and it's linear,
right?
Linear, I have to check that
A(v) -- A times v plus w equals
Av plus A w, which is fine,
and I have to check that A
times vc equals c A(v).
Check.
Those are fine.
So there is a linear
transformation.
And if I take my favorite
matrix A, and I apply it to all
vectors in the plane,
it will produce a bunch of
outputs.
See, the idea is now worth
thinking of, like,
the big picture.
The whole plane is transformed
by matrix multiplication.
Every vector in the plane gets
multiplied by A.
Let's take an example,
and see what happens to the
vectors of the house.
So this is still a
transformation from plane to
plane, and let me take a
particular matrix A -- well,
if I cooked up a rotation
matrix, this would be the right
picture.
If I cooked up a projection
matrix, the projection would be
the picture.
Let me just take some other
matrix.
Let me take the matrix one zero
zero minus one.
What happens to the house,
to all vectors,
and in particular,
we can sort of visualize it if
we look at the house --
so the house is not rotated any
more, what do I get?
What happens to all the vectors
if I do this transformation?
I multiply by this matrix.
Well, of course,
it's an easy matrix,
it's diagonal.
The x component stays the same,
the y component reverses sign,
so that like the roof of that
house, the point,
the tip of the roof,
has an x component which stays
the same, but its y component
reverses, and it's down here.
And, of course,
what we get is,
the house is,
like, upside down.
Now, I have to put -- where
does the door go?
I guess the door goes upside
down there, right?
So here's the input,
here's the input house,
and this is the output.
OK.
This idea of a linear
transformation is like kind of
the abstract description of
matrix multiplication.
And what's our goal here?
Our goal is to understand
linear transformations,
and the way to understand them
is to find the matrix that lies
behind them.
That's really the idea.
Find the matrix that lies
behind them.
Um, and to do that,
we have to bring in
coordinates.
We have to choose a basis.
So let me point out what's the
story -- if we have a linear
transformation -- so start with
-- start.
Suppose we have a linear
transformation.
Let -- from now on,
let T stand for linear
transformations.
I won't be interested in the
nonlinear ones.
Only linear transformations I'm
interested in.
OK.
I start with a linear
transformation T.
Let's suppose its inputs are
vectors in R^3.
OK?
And suppose its outputs are
vectors in R^2,
for example.
OK.
What's an example of such a
transformation,
just before I go any further?
Any matrix of the right size
will do this.
So what would be the right
shape of a matrix?
So, for example -- I'm wanting
to give you an example,
just because,
here, I'm thinking of
transformations that take
three-dimensional space to
two-dimensional space.
And I want them to be linear,
and the easy way to invent them
is a matrix multiplication.
So example, T of v should be
any A v.
Those transformations are
linear, that's what 18.06 is
about.
And A should be what size,
what shape of matrix should
that be?
I want V to have three
components, because this is what
the inputs have -- so here's the
input in R^3,
and here's the output in R^2.
So what shape of matrix?
So this should be,
I guess, a two by three matrix?
Right?
A two by three matrix.
A two by three matrix,
we'll multiply a vector in R^3
-- you see I'm moving to
coordinates so quickly,
I'm not a true physicist here.
A two by three matrix,
we'll multiply a vector in R^3
an produce an output in R^2,
and it will be a linear
transformation,
and OK.
So there's a whole lot of
examples, every two by three
matrix give me an example,
and basically,
I want to show you that there
are no other examples.
Every linear transformation is
associated with a matrix.
Now, let me come back to the
idea of linear transformation.
Suppose I've got this linear
transformation in my mind,
and I want to tell you what it
is.
Suppose I tell you what the
transformation does to one
vector.
OK.
You know one thing,
then.
All right.
So this is like the -- what I'm
speaking about now is,
how much information is needed
to know the transformation?
By knowing T,
I -- to know T of v for all v.
All inputs.
How much information do I have
to give you so that you know
what the transformation does to
every vector?
OK, I could tell you what the
transformation -- so I could
take a vector v1,
one particular vector,
tell you what the
transformation does to it --
fine.
But now you only know what the
transformation does to one
vector.
So you say, OK,
that's not enough,
tell me what it does to another
vector.
So I say, OK,
give me a vector,
you give me a vector v2,
and we see, what does the
transformation do to v2?
Now, you only know -- or do you
only know what the
transformation does to two
vectors?
Have I got to ask you -- answer
you about every vector in the
whole input space,
or can you, knowing what it
does to v1 and v2,
how much do you now know about
the transformation?
You know what the
transformation does to a larger
bunch of vectors than just these
two, because you know what it
does to every linear
combination.
You know what it does,
now, to the whole plane of
vectors, with bases v1 and v2.
I'm assuming v1 and v2 were
independent.
If they were dependent,
if v2 was six times v1,
then I didn't give you any new
information in T of v2,
you already knew it would be
six times T of v1.
So you can see what I'd headed
for.
If I know what the
transformation does to every
vector in a basis,
then I know everything.
So the information needed to
know T of v for all inputs is T
of v1, T of v2,
up to T of vm,
let's say, or vn,
for any basis -- for a basis v1
up to vn.
This is a base for any -- can I
call it an input basis?
It's a basis for the space of
inputs.
The things that T is acting on.
You see this point,
that if I have a basis for the
input space, and I tell you what
the transformation does to every
one of those basis vectors,
that is all I'm allowed to tell
you, and it's enough to know T
of v for all v-s,
because why?
Because every v is some
combination of these basis
vectors, c1v1+...+cnvn,
that's what a basis is,
right?
It spans the space.
And if I know what T does to
this, and what T does to v2,
and what T does to vn,
then I know what T does to V.
By this linearity,
it has to be c1 T of v1 plus O
one plus cn T of vn.
There's no choice.
So, the point of this comment
is that if I know what T does to
a basis, to each vector in a
basis, then I know the linear
transformation.
The property of linearity tells
me all the other vectors.
All the other outputs.
OK.
So now, we got -- so that light
we now see, what do we really
need in a linear transformation,
and we're ready to go to a
matrix.
OK.
What's the step now that takes
us from a linear transformation
that's free of coordinates to a
matrix that's been created with
respect to coordinates?
The matrix is going to come
from the coordinate system.
These are the coordinates.
Coordinates mean a basis is
decided.
Once you decide on a basis --
this is where coordinates come
from.
You decide on a basis,
then every vector,
these are the coordinates in
that basis.
There is one and only one way
to express v as a combination of
the basis vectors,
and the numbers you need in
that combination are the
coordinates.
Let me write that down.
So what are coordinates?
Coordinates come from a basis.
The coordinates of v,
the coordinates of v are these
numbers that tell you how much
of each basis vector is in v.
If I change the basis,
I change the coordinates,
right?
Now, we have always been
assuming that were working with
a standard basis,
right?
The basis we don't even think
about this stuff,
because if I give you the
vector v equals three two four,
you have been assuming
completely -- and probably
rightly -- that I had in mind
the standard basis,
that this vector was three
times the first coordinate
vector, and two times the
second, and four times the
third.
But you're not entitled -- I
might have had some other basis
in mind.
This is like the standard
basis.
And then the coordinates are
sitting right there in the
vector.
But I could have chosen a
different basis,
like I might have had
eigenvectors of a matrix,
and I might have said,
OK, that's a great basis,
I'll use the eigenvectors of
this matrix as my basis vectors.
Which are not necessarily these
three, but some other basis.
So that was an example,
this is the real thing,
the coordinates are these
numbers, I'll circle them again,
the amounts of each basis.
OK.
So, if I want to create a
matrix that describes a linear
transformation,
now I'm ready to do that.
OK, OK.
So now what I plan to do is
construct the matrix A that
represents, or tells me about,
a linear transformation,
linear transformation T.
OK.
So I really start with the
transformation --
whether it's a projection or a
rotation, or some strange
movement of this house in the
plane, or some transformation
from n-dimensional space to --
or m-dimensional space to
n-dimensional space.
n to m, I guess.
Usually, we'll have T,
we'll somehow transform
n-dimensional space to
m-dimensional space,
and the whole point is that if
I have a basis for n-dimensional
space -- I guess I need two
bases, really.
I need an input basis to
describe the inputs,
and I need an output basis to
give me coordinates -- to give
me some numbers for the output.
So I've got to choose two
bases.
Choose a basis v1 up to vn for
the inputs, for the inputs in --
they came from R^n.
So the transformation is taking
every n-dimensional vector into
some m-dimensional vector.
And I have to choose a basis,
and I'll call them w1 up to wn,
for the outputs.
Those are guys in R^m.
Once I've chosen the basis,
that settles the matrix -- I
now working with coordinates.
Every vector in R^n,
every input vector has some
coordinates.
So here's what I do,
here's what I do.
Can I say it in words?
I take a vector v.
I express it in its basis,
in the basis,
so I get its coordinates.
Then I'm going to multiply
those coordinates by the right
matrix A, and that will give me
the coordinates of the output in
the output basis.
I'd better write that down,
that was a mouthful.
What I want -- I want a matrix
A that does what the linear
transformation does.
And it does it with respecting
these bases.
So I want the matrix to be --
well, let's suppose -- look,
let me take an example.
Let me take the projection
example.
The projection example.
Suppose I take -- because we've
got that -- we've got that
projection in mind -- I can fit
in here.
Here's the projection example.
So the projection example,
I'm thinking of n and m as two.
The transformation takes the
plane, takes every vector in the
plane, and, let me draw the
plane, just so we remember it's
a plane -- and there's the thing
that I'm projecting onto,
that's the line I'm projecting
onto -- so the transformation
takes every vector in the plane
and projects it onto that line.
So this is projection,
so I'm going to do projection.
OK.
But, I'm going to choose a
basis that I like better than
the standard basis.
My basis -- in fact,
I'll choose the same basis for
inputs and for outputs,
and the basis will be -- my
first basis vector will be right
on the line.
There's my first basis vector.
Say, a unit vector,
on the line.
And my second basis vector will
be a unit vector perpendicular
to that line.
And I'm going to choose that as
the output basis,
also.
And I'm going to ask you,
what's the matrix?
What's the matrix?
How do I describe this
transformation of projection
with respect to this basis?
OK?
So what's the rule?
I take any vector v,
it's some combination of the
first basis ve- vector,
and the second basis vector.
Now, what is T of v?
Suppose the input is -- well,
suppose the input is v1.
What's the output?
v1, right?
The projection leaves this one
alone.
So we know what the projection
does to this first basis vector,
this guy, it leaves it.
What does the projection do to
the second basis vector?
It kills it,
sends it to zero.
So what does the projection do
to a combination?
It kills this part,
and this part,
it leaves alone.
Now, all I want to do is find
the matrix.
I now want to find the matrix
that takes an input,
c1 c2, the coordinates,
and gives me the output,
c1 0.
You see that in this basis,
the coordinates of the input
were c1, c2, and the coordinates
of the output are c1,
And of course,
not hard to find a matrix that
will do that.
The matrix that will do that is
the matrix one,
zero, zero, zero.
Because if I multiply input by
that matrix A -- this is A times
input coordinates -- and I'm
hoping to get the output
coordinates.
And what do I get from that
multiplication?
I get the right answer,
c1 and zero.
So what's the point?
So the first point is,
there's a matrix that does the
job.
If there's a linear
transformation out there,
coordinate-free,
no coordinates,
and then I choose a basis for
the inputs, and I choose a basis
for the outputs,
then there's a matrix that does
the job.
And what's the job?
It multiplies the input
coordinates and produces the
output coordinates.
Now, in this example -- let me
repeat, I chose the input basis
was the same as the output
basis.
The input basis and output
basis were both along the line,
and perpendicular to the line.
They're actually the
eigenvectors of the projection.
And, as a result,
the matrix came out diagonal.
In fact, it came out to be
lambda.
This is like,
the good basis.
So the good -- the eigenvector
basis is the good basis,
it leads to the matrix --
the diagonal matrix of
eigenvalues lambda,
and just as in this example,
the eigenvectors and
eigenvalues of this linear
transformation were along the
line, and perpendicular.
The eigenvalues were one and
zero, and that's the matrix that
we got.
OK.
So that's a,
like, the great choice of
matrix, that's the choice a
physicist would do when he had
to finally -- he or she had to
finally bring coordinates in
unwillingly, the coordinates to
be chosen, the good coordinates
are the eigenvectors,
because, if I did this
projection in the standard basis
-- which I could do,
right?
I could do the whole thing in
the standard basis -- I better
try, if I can do that.
What are we calling -- so I'll
have to tell you now which line
we're projecting on.
Say, the 45 degree line.
So say we're projecting onto 45
degree line, and we use not the
eigenvector basis,
but the standard basis.
The standard basis,
v1, is one, zero,
and v2 is zero,
one.
And again, I'll use the same
basis for the outputs.
Then I have to do this -- I can
find a matrix,
it will be the matrix that we
would always think of,
it would be the projection
matrix.
It will be, actually,
it's the matrix that we learned
about in chapter four,
it's what I call the matrix --
do you remember,
P was A, A transpose over A
transpose A?
And I think,
in this example,
it will come out,
one-half, one-half,
one-half, one-half.
I believe that's the matrix
that comes from our formula.
And that's the matrix that will
do the job.
If I give you this input,
one, zero, what's the output?
The output is one-half,
one-half.
And that should be the right
projection.
And if I give you the input
zero, one, the output is,
again, one-half,
one-half, again the projection.
So that's the matrix,
but not diagonal of course,
because we didn't choose a
great basis, we just chose the
handiest basis.
Well, so the course has
practically been about the
handiest basis,
and just dealing with the
matrix that we got.
And it's not that bad a matrix,
it's symmetric,
and it has this P squared equal
P property, all those things are
good.
But in the best basis,
it's easy to see that P squared
equals P, and it's symmetric,
and it's diagonal.
So that's the idea then,
is, do you see now how I'm
associating a matrix to the
transformation?
I'd better write the rule down,
I'd better write the rule down.
The rule to find the matrix A.
All right, first column.
So, a rule to find A,
we're given the bases.
Of course, we don't -- because
there's no way we could
construct the matrix until we're
told what the bases are.
So we're given the input basis,
and the output basis,
v1 to vn, w1 to wm.
Those are given.
Now, in the first column of A,
how do I find that column?
The first column of the matrix.
So that should tell me what
happens to the first basis
vector.
So the rule is,
apply the linear transformation
to v1.
To the first basis vector.
And then, I'll write it -- so
that's the output,
right?
The input is v1,
what's the output?
The output is in the output
space, it's some combination of
these guys, and it's that
combination that goes into the
first column -- so,
let me -- I'll put this word --
right, I'll say it in words
again.
How to find this matrix.
Take the first basis vector.
Apply the transformation,
then it's in the output space,
T of v1, so it's some
combination of these outputs,
this output basis.
So that combination,
the coefficients in that
combination will be the first
column -- so a1,
a row 2, column 1,
w2, am1, wm.
There are the numbers in the
first column of the matrix.
Let me make the point by doing
the second column.
Second column of A.
What's the idea,
now?
I take the second basis vector,
I apply the transformation to
it, that's in -- now I get an
output, so it's some combination
in the output basis --
and that combination is the
bunch of numbers that should go
in the second column of the
matrix.
OK.
And so forth.
So I get a matrix,
and the matrix I get does the
right job.
Now, the matrix constructed
that way, and following the
rules of matrix multiplication.
The result will be that if I
give you the input coordinates,
and I multiply by the matrix,
so the outcome of all this is A
times the input coordinates
correctly reproduces the output
coordinates.
Why is this right?
Let me just check the first
column.
Suppose the input coordinates
are one and all zeros.
What does that mean?
What's the input?
If the input coordinates are
one and other -- and the rest
zeros, then the input is v1,
right?
That's the vector that has
coordinates one and all zeros.
OK?
When I multiply A by the one
and all zeros,
I'll get the first column of A,
I'll get these numbers.
And, sure enough,
those are the output
coordinates for T of v1.
So we made it right on the
first column,
we made it right on the second
column, we made it right on all
the basis vectors,
and then it has to be right on
every vector.
OK.
So there is a picture of the
matrix for a linear
transformation.
Finally, let me give you
another -- a different linear
transformation.
The linear transformation that
takes the derivative.
That's a linear transformation.
Suppose the input space is all
combination c1 plus c2x plus c3
x squared.
So the basis is these simple
functions.
Then what's the output?
Is the derivative.
The output is the derivative,
so the output is c2+2c3 x.
And let's take as output basis,
the vectors one and x.
So we're going from a
three-dimensional space of
inputs to a two-dimensional
space of outputs by the
derivative.
And I don't know if you ever
thought that the derivative is
linear.
But if it weren't linear,
taking derivatives would take
forever, right?
We are able to compute
derivatives of functions exactly
because we know it's a linear
transformation,
so that if we learn the
derivatives of a few functions,
like sine x and cos x and e to
the x, and another little short
list, then we can take all their
combinations and we can do all
the derivatives.
OK, now what's the matrix?
What's the matrix?
So I want the matrix to
multiply these input vectors --
input coordinates,
and give these output
coordinates.
So I just think,
OK, what's the matrix that does
it?
I can follow my rule of
construction,
or I can see what the matrix
is.
It should be a two by three
matrix, right?
And the matrix -- so I'm just
figuring out,
what do I want?
No, I'll -- let me write it
here.
What do I want from my matrix?
What should that matrix do?
Well, I want to get c2 in the
first output,
so zero, one,
zero will do it.
I want to get two c3,
so zero, zero,
two will do it.
That's the matrix for this
linear transformation with those
bases and those coordinates.
You see, it just clicks,
and the whole point is that the
inverse matrix gives the inverse
to the linear transformation,
that the product of two
matrices gives the right matrix
for the product of two
transformations --
matrix multiplication really
came from linear
transformations.
I'd better pick up on that
theme Monday after Thanksgiving.
And I hope you have a great
holiday.
I hope Indian summer keeps
going.
OK, see you on Monday.