OK, this is quiz review day.
The quiz coming up on Wednesday
will before this lecture the
quiz will be this hour one
o'clock Wednesday in Walker,
top floor of Walker,
closed book,
all normal.
I wrote down what we've covered
in this second part of the
course, and actually I'm
impressed as I
write it.
so that's chapter four on
orthogonality and you're
remembering these -- what this
is suggesting,
these are those columns are
orthonormal vectors,
and then we call that matrix Q
and the -- what's the key -- how
do we state the fact that those
v- those columns are orthonormal
in
terms of Q, it means that Q
transpose Q is the identity.
So that's the matrix statement
of the -- of the property that
the columns are orthonormal,
the dot products are either one
or zero, and then we computed
the projections onto lines and
onto
subspaces, and we used that to
solve problems Ax=b in -- in the
least square sense,
when there was no solution,
we found the best solution.
And then finally this
Graham-Schmidt idea,
which takes independent vectors
and lines them up,
takes -- subtracts off the
projections of the part you've
already done,
so that the new part is
orthogonal and so it takes a
basis to an orthonormal basis.
And you -- those calculations
involve square roots a lot
because you're making things
unit vectors,
but you should know that step.
OK,
for determinants,
the three big -- the big
picture is the properties of the
determinant, one to three d-
properties one,
two and three,
d- that define the determinant,
and then four,
five, six through ten were
consequences.
Then the big formula that has n
factorial terms,
half of them have plus signs
and half minus signs,
and then the cofactor formula.
So and which led us to a
formula for the inverse.
And finally,
just so you know what's covered
in from chapter three,
it's section six point one and
two, so that's the basic idea of
eigenvalues and eigenvectors,
the equation for the
eigenvalues, the mechanical
step, this is really Ax equal
lambda x for all n eigenvectors
at once, if we have n
independent eigenvectors,
and then using that to compute
powers of a matrix.
So you notice the differential
equations not on this list,
because that's six point three,
that that's for the third quiz.
OK.
Shall I what I usually do for
review is to take an old exam
and just try to pick out
questions that are significant
and write them quickly on the
board, shall I -- shall I
proceed that way
again?
This -- this exam is really
old.
November nineteen -- nineteen
eighty-four, so that was before
the Web existed.
So not only were the lectures
not on the Web,
nobody even had a Web page,
my God.
OK, so can I nevertheless
linear algebra was still as
great as ever.
So may I and that wasn't meant
to be a joke,
OK, all right,
so let me just take these
questions as they come.
All right.
OK.
So the first question's about
projections.
It says we're given the line,
the -- the vector a is the
vector two, one,
two, and I want to find the
projection matrix P that
projects onto the line through
a.
So my picture is,
well I'm in three dimensions,
of course, so there's a vector,
two -- there's the vector a,
two, one, two,
let me draw the whole line
through it, and I want to
project
any vector b onto that line,
and I'm looking for the
projection matrix.
So -- so this -- the projection
matrix is the matrix that I
multiply b by to get here.
And I guess this first part,
this is just part one a,
I'm really asking you the --
the quick way to answer,
to find P, is just to remember
what
the formula is.
And -- and we're in -- we're
projecting onto a line,
so our formula,
our -- our usual formula is AA
transpose A inverse A transpose,
but now A is just a column,
one-column matrix,
so it'll be just a,
so I'll just call it little a,
little a transpose,
and this is just
a number now,
one by one, so I can put it in
the denominator,
so there's our -- that's really
what we want to remember,
and -- and using that two,
one, two, what will I get?
I'm dividing by -- what's the
length squared of that vector?
So what's a transpose a?
Looks like nine,
and what's the matrix,
well, I'm -- I'm doing two,
one, two against two,
one, two, so it's one-ninth of
this matrix four,
two, four, two,
one, two, four,
two, four.
Now the next part asked about
eigenvalues.
So you see we're -- since we're
learning, we know a lot more
now, we can make connections
between these chapters,
so what's the eigenvector,
what are the eigenvalues of P?
I could ask what's the rank of
P.
What's the rank of that matrix?
Uh -- one.
Rank is one.
What's the column space?
If I apply P to all vectors
then I fill up the column space,
it's combinations of the
columns, so what's the column
space?
Well, it's just this line.
The column space is the line
through two, one,
two.
And now what's the
eigenvalue?
So, or since that matrix has
rank one, so tell me the
eigenvalues of this matrix.
It's a singular matrix,
so it certainly has an
eigenvalue zero.
Actually, the rank is only one,
so that means that there like
going to be t- a
two-dimensional null space,
there'll be at least two,
this lambda equals zero will be
repeated twice because I can
find two independent
eigenvectors with lambda equals
zero, and then of course since
it's got three eigenvalues,
what's the third one?
It's one.
How do I know it's one?
Either from the trace,
which is nine over nine,
which is one,
or by remembering what -- what
is the eigenvector,
and actually now it's going to
ask for the eigenvector,
so what's the eigenvector for
that eigenvalue?
What's the eigenvector for that
eigenvalue?
It's the -- it's the vector
that doesn't move,
eigenvalue one,
so the vector that doesn't move
is a.
This a is the -- is -- is also
the eigenvector with lambda
equal one, because if I apply
the projection matrix to a,
I get a again.
Everybody sees that if I apply
that matrix to a,
can I do it in little letters,
if I apply that matrix to a,
then I have a transpose a
canceling a transpose a and I
get a again.
So sure enough,
Pa equals a.
And the eigenvalue is one.
OK.
Good.
now, actually it asks you
further to solve
this difference equation,
so this will be -- this is --
this is solve u(k+1)=Puk,
starting from u0 equal nine,
nine, zero.
And find uk.
So -- so what's up?
Shall we find u1 first of all?
So just to get started.
So what is u1?
It's Pu0 of course.
So if I do the projection of --
of this vector onto the line,
so this is like my vector b now
that I'm projecting onto the
line, I get a times a transpose
u0 over a transpose a.
Well, one way or another I just
do this multiplication.
but maybe this is the easiest
way to do it.
a transpose,
can I remember what a is on
this board?
Two, one, two,
so I'm projecting onto the line
through there.
This is the projection,
it's P times the vector u0,
so what do I have for a
transpose u0 looks like
eighteen, looks like
twenty-seven,
and a transpose a we figured
was nine,
so it's three a,
so that this is the -- this is
the x hat, the -- the multiple
of a, in -- in our formulas,
and of course that's six,
three, six.
So that's u1.
Computed out directly.
That's on the line through a
and it's the closest point to
u0, and it's just Pu0.
You just
straightforward multiplication
produces that.
OK.
Now, what's u2?
Well, u2 is Pu1,
I agree.
Do I need to compute that
again?
No, because once I'm already on
the line through A,
uk will be, I could do the
projection k times,
but it's enough just to do it
once.
It's the same,
it's the same,
six, three, six.
So this is a case where I could
and -- and actually on the quiz
if you see one of these,
which could very well be there,
and it could very well be not a
projection matrix,
then we would use all the
eigenvalues and eigenvectors.
Let's think for a moment,
how do
you do those?
M - the point of this small
part of a question was that when
P is a projection matrix,
so that P squared equals P and
P cubed equals P,
then -- then we don't need to
get into the mechanics of all
knowing all the other
eigenvalues and eigenvectors.
We just
can go directly.
But if P was now some other
matrix, can you just -- let's
just remember from these very
recent lectures how you would
proceed.
from these very recent lectures
we know that uk we would -- we
would expand u0 as a combination
of eigenvectors.
Let me leave -- yeah,
as a combination of
eigenvectors,
c1x1, some multiple of the
second eigenvector,
some multiple of the third
eigenvector, and then A to the
ku0 would be c1,
so this -- we have to find
these numbers here,
that's the work actually.
The work
is find the eigenvalues,
find the eigenvectors and find
the c-s because they all come
into the formula.
We have -- so -- so to do this,
you can see what you have to
compute.
You have to compute the
eigenvalues, you have to compute
the eigenvectors,
and then to match u0 you
compute the c-s,
and
then you've got it.
So it's -- it's just that's a
formula that shows what pieces
we need.
And what would actually happen
in the case of this projection
matrix?
If this A is a projection
matrix, then a couple of
eigenvalues are zero.
That's why we just throw those
away.
The other eigenvalue was a one,
so that we got the same thing
every time, c3x3.
From the first time,
second time,
third, all iterations pro- left
us with this constant,
left us right here at six,
three, six.
But maybe I take -- I'm taking
this chance to remind you
of what to do for other
matrices.
OK.
So that's part way through.
The next question in nineteen
eighty-four is fitting a
straight line to points.
And actually a straight line
through the origin.
A straight line through the
origin.
So can I go to question two?
So this is fitting a straight
line to
these points,
can I -- I'll just give you the
points at t=1 the y is four,
at t=2, y is five,
at t=3, y is eight.
So we've got points one,
two, three, four,
five, and eight.
And I'm trying to fit a
straight line through the origin
to
these three values.
OK, so my equation that I'm
allowing myself is just y equal
Dt.
So I have only one unknown.
One degree of freedom.
One parameter D.
So I'm expecting to end up my
matrix so my -- my -- when I try
to -- when I try to fit a
straight line,
that goes through the origin,
that's because it goes through
the origin, I've lost the
constant c here,
so I have just this should be a
quick calculation.
and I can write down the three
equations that -- that -- that
would -- I'd like to solve if
the line went through the
points, that's a good start.
Because that displays the
matrix.
So can I continue that problem?
We would like to solve-- so y
is Dt, so I'd like to solve D
times one times D equals four,
two times D equals five and
three times D equals eight.
That would be perfection.
If I could find such a D,
then the line y equal Dt would
satisfy all three equations,
would go through all three
points, but it doesn't exist.
So -- so I have to solve this
-- so the -- my matrix is now
you can see my matrix,
it just has one column.
Multiplying a scalar D.
And you can see the right-hand
side.
This is my Ax=b.
I don't need three equals signs
now because I've got vectors.
OK.
There's Ax=b and you take it
from there.
You the -- the best x will be
-- will come from -- so what's
the -- the key equation?
So this is the A,
this is the Ax hat equal b
equation.
Well, Ax=b.
And what's the equation
for x hat?
The best D, so to find the best
D, the best x,
the equation is A transpose A,
the best D, is A transpose
times the right-hand side.
This is all coming from
projection on a line,
our -- our matrix only has one
column.
So A transpose A would be maybe
fourteen, D hat,
and A transpose b I'm getting
four, ten, and twenty-four.
Is that right?
Four, ten and twenty-four.
So thirty-eight.
So that tells me the best D hat
is D hat is thirty-eight over
fourteen.
OK.
Fine.
All right.
so we found the best line.
And now here's a -- here's the
next question.
What vector did I just project
onto what line?
See in this section on least
squares here's the key point,
I'm -- I'm asking you to think
of the least squares problem in
two
ways.
Two different pictures.
Two different graphs.
One graph is this.
This is a graph in the -- in
the b -- in the tb plane,
ty plane.
The -- the -- the line itself.
The other picture I'm asking
you to think of is like my
projection picture.
What -- what projection --
what -- what vector I -- I
projecting onto what line or
what subspace when I -- when I
do this?
So the -- my second picture is
a projection picture that --
that sees the whole thing with
vectors.
Here's my vector of course that
I'm projecting.
I'm projecting that vector b
onto the column space of A.
Of if you like -- it's just a
line onto that's the line it's
just a line, of course.
That's what this calculation is
doing.
This is computing the best D,
which is -- this is the x hat.
So -- so seeing it as a
projection means I don't see the
projection in this figure,
right?
In this figure I'm not
projecting
those points onto that line or
anything of the sort.
The projection s-picture for --
for least squares is in the --
in the space where b lies,
the whole vector b,
and the columns of A.
And then the x is the best
combination that gives the
projection.
OK.
So that's a chance to tell me
that.
OK.
I'll go -- OK now finally in
orthogonality there's the
Graham-Schmidt idea.
So that's problem two D here.
It asks me if I have two
vectors, a1 equal one,
two, three, and a2 equal one,
one, one, find two orthogonal
vectors in that plane.
So those two vectors give a
plane, they give a plane.
Which is of course the -- the
column space of the -- of the
matrix.
And I'm looking for an
orthogonal basis for that plane.
So I'm looking for two
orthogonal vectors.
And of course there are lots of
--
I mean, I've got a plane there.
If I get one orthogonal pair,
I can rotate it.
There's not just one answer
here.
But Graham-Schmidt says OK,
start with the first vector,
and let that be -- and keep
that one.
And then take the second one
orthogonal to this.
So -- so Graham-Schmidt says
start
with this one and then make a
second vector B,
can I call that second vector
B, this is going to be
orthogonal to,
so perpendicular to a1.
If I can with my chalk create
the key equation.
This vector B is going to be
this one, one,
one, but that one,
one --
one, one, one is not
perpendicular to a1,
so I have to subtract off its
projection, I have to subtract
off the B, the -- the B trans-
ye the B -- the -- the I should
say the a1 transpose b over a1
transpose a1,
that multiple of a1,
I've got to remove.
So I just have
to compute what that is,
and I get ano- I get a vector B
that's orthogonal to a1.
It's the -- it's -- it's the
original vector minus its
projection.
Oh, so what is -- I mean this
to be a2.
Yeah.
So I'm projecting a2 onto the
line through a1.
That's the part that I don't
want
because that's in the direction
I already have,
so I subtract off that
projection and I get the part I
want, the orthogonal part.
OK.
So that's the Graham-Schmidt
thing and we can put numbers in.
one, one, one take away a1
transpose a2 is six,
a1 transpose a1 is
fourteen,multiplying a1.
And that gives us the new
orthogonal vector B.
Because I only ask for
orthogonal right now,
I don't have to divide by the
length which will involve a
square root.
OK.
Third question.
All right,
let me -- I'll move this board
up.
third question will probably be
about eigenvalues.
OK.
Three.
This is a four-by-four matrix.
Its eigenvalues are lambda one,
lambda two, lambda three,
lambda four.
Question one.
What's the condition on the
lambdas so that the matrix is
invertible?
OK.
So under what conditions on the
lambdas will the matrix be
invertible?
So that's easy.
Invertible if what's the
condition on the lambdas?
None of them are zero.
A zero eigenvalue would mean
something in the null space
would mean a solution to Ax=0x,
but we're invertible,
so none of
them is zero,
the product -- however you want
to say, no -- no zero
eigenvalues.
Good.
OK, what's the determinant of A
inverse?
The determinant of A inverse?
So where is that going to come
from?
Well, if we knew the
eigenvalues of A inverse,
we could multiply them together
to find the determinant.
And we do know the eigenvalues
of A inverse.
What are they?
They're just one over lambda
one times one over lambda two,
that's the second eigenvalue,
the third eigenvalue and the
fourth.
So the product of the four
eigenvalues of the inverse
will give us the determinant of
the inverse.
Fine.
OK.
And what's the trace of A plus
I?
So what do we know about trace?
It's the sum down the diagonal,
but we don't know what our
matrix is.
The trace is also the sum of
the eigenvalues,
and we do know the eigenvalues
of A
plus I.
So we just add them up.
So what -- what's the first
eigenvalue of A plus I?
When the matrix A has
eigenvalues lambda one,
two, three and four,
then the eigenvalues if I add
the identity,
that moves all the eigenvalues
by one,
so I just add up lambda one
plus one, lambda two plus one,
and so on, lambda three plus
one, lambda four plus one,
so it's lambda one plus lambda
two plus lambda three plus
lambda four plus four.
Right.
That movement by the identity
moved all the eigenvalues by
one, so it moved
the whole trace by four.
So it was the trace of A plus
four more.
OK.
Let's see.
We may be finished this quiz
twenty minutes early.
No.
There's another question.
Oh, God, OK.
How did this class ever do it?
Well, you'll see.
you'll be able to do it.
OK.
this has got to be a
determinant question.
All right.
More determinants and cofactors
and big formula question.
OK.
Let me do that.
So it's about a matrix,
a -- a whole family of
matrices.
Here's the four-by-four one.
The four-by-four one is,
and -- and all the matrices in
this family are tridiagonal with
-- with ones.
Otherwise zeroes.
So that's the pattern,
and we've seen this matrix.
OK.
So the -- it's tridiagonal with
ones on the diagonal,
ones above and ones below,
and you see the general formula
An, so I'll use Dn for the
determinant
of An.
OK.
All right.
So I'm going to do a -- the
first question is use cofactors
to show that Dn is something
times D(n-1) plus something
times D(n-2).
And find those somethings.
OK.
So this -- the fact that it's
tridiagonal with
these constant diagonals means
that there is such a recurrence
formula.
And so the first question is
find it.
Well, what's the recurrence
formula?
OK, how does it go?
So I'll use cofactors along the
first row.
So I take that number times its
cofactor.
So it's one times its cofactor
and what is its cofactor?
D(n-1), right,
exactly, the cofactor is this
-- is this guy uses up row one
and column one,
so the cofactor is down here,
so it's one of those.
OK, that's the first cofactor
term.
Now the other cofactor term is
this guy.
Which uses up row one and
column two and what's surprising
about that?
When you use row one and column
two that brings in a minus.
There'll be a minus because the
-- the cofactor is this
determinant times minus one.
The the one-two cofactor
is that determinant with its
sign changed.
OK.
So I have to look at that
determinant and I have to
remember in my head a sign is
going to get changed.
OK.
Now how do I do that
determinant?
How do I make that one clear?
I -- the --
the neat way to do is -- is
here I see I -- I'll use
cofactors down the first column.
Because the first column is all
zeroes except for that one,
so this one is now -- and
what's its cofactor?
Within this three-by-three its
cofactor will be two-by-two,
and what is it?
It's this, right?
So -- so that part is all gone,
so I'm taking that times its
cofactor, then zero times
whatever its cofactor is,
so it's really just one times
and what's this in the general
n-by-n case?
It's Dn minus two.
But now so is this a plus or
sign or a minus sign,
it's -- it's just a one,
because there's a one from
there and a one from there.
And is it a plus or a minus?
It's minus I guess because
there was a minus the first time
and then the second time
it's a plus,
so it's overall it's a minus.
So there's my a and b were one
and minus one.
Those constants.
Th- that's the -- that's the
recurrence.
OK.
And oh, then it asks you to
then it asks you to solve this
thing first by
writing it as a -- as a system.
So now I'd like to know the
solution.
I -- I better know how it
starts, right?
It starts with D1,
what was D1,
that's just the one-by-one
case, so D1 is one,
and what is D2?
Just to get us started and then
this would give us D3,
D4, and forever.
D2 is this two-by-two that I'm
seeing here and that determinant
is obviously zero.
So those little ones will start
the recurrence and then we take
off.
And then the idea is to write
this recurrence as --
as a Dn, D(n-1) is some matrix
times the one before,
the D(n-1), D(n-2).
What's the matrix?
You see, you remember this step
of taking a single second order
equation and by introducing a
vector unknown to make it into a
--
to a first order system.
OK.
So Dn is one of Dn minus one
minus one, I think that -- that
goes in the first row,
right?
From the equation above?
And the second one is this is
the same as this,
so one and zero are fine.
So there's the matrix.
OK.
So now how do I proceed?
We can guess what this
examiner's got in his little
mind.
well, find the eigenvalues.
And actually it tells us that
the sixth power of these
eigenvalues turns out to be one.
Uh, well, can -- can we get the
equation for the eigenvalues?
Let's do it and let's get a
formula for them.
OK.
So what are the eigenvalues?
I look at the -- the matrix,
this determinant one minus
lambda and zero minus lambda,
and these guys are still there,
I compute that determinant,
I get lambda squared minus
lambda
and then plus one.
And I set that to zero.
OK.
So we're not Fibonacci here.
We're -- we're not seeing
Fibonacci numbers.
Because the sign -- we had a
sign change there.
And it's not clear right away
whether these -- whether this --
is it clear?
Is this matrix stable or
unstable?
When we take -- when we go
further and further out?
Are these Ds increasing?
Are they going to zero?
Are they bouncing around
periodically?
the answers have to be here.
I would like to know how big
these lambdas are,
right?
And the point is probably these
-- let's -- let's see,
what's lambda?
From the quadratic formula
lambda is one,
I switch the sign of that,
plus or minus the square root
of one minus 4ac,
I getting a minus three there?
Over two.
What's up?
They're complex.
The -- the eigenvalues are one
plus square root of three I over
two and one minus square root of
three I over two.
What's the magnitude of lambda?
That's the key point for
stability.
These are two numbers in the
complex plane.
One plus some --
somewhere here,
and its complex conjugate
there.
I want to know how far from the
origin are those numbers.
What's the magnitude of lambda?
And do you see what it is?
Do you recognize this -- a
number like that?
Take the real part squared and
the imaginary part squared and
add.
What do you get?
So the real part squared is a
quarter.
The imaginary part squared is
three-quarters.
They add to one.
That's a number with -- that's
on the unit circle.
That's an e to the i theta.
That's a
cos(theta)+isin(theta).
And what's theta?
This -- this is like a complex
number that's worth knowing,
it's not totally obvious but
it's nice.
That's -- I should see that as
cos(theta)+isin(theta),
and the angle that would do
that is
sixty degrees,
pi over three.
So that's a -- let me improve
my picture.
So those -- that's e to the i
pi over six -- pi over three.
This is -- this number is e to
the i pi over three and e to the
minus i pi over three.
We'll be doing more complex
numbers
briefly but a little more in
the next two days.
next two lectures.
Anyway, the -- so what's the
deal with stability,
what do the Dn-s do?
Well, look, if -- if I take the
sixth power I'm around at one,
the problem actually told me
this.
The sixth power of those
eigenvalues brings me around to
one.
What does that tell you about
the matrix, by the way?
Suppose you know -- this was a
great quiz question,
so I should never have just
said it, but popped out.
Suppose lambda one to the sixth
and
lambda two to the sixth are --
are one, which they are.
What does that tell me about a
m- a matrix?
About my matrix A here.
Well, what -- what matrix is
connected with lambda one to the
sixth and lambda two to the
sixth?
It's got to be the matrix
A to the sixth.
So what is A to the sixth for
that matrix?
It's got eigenvalues one and
one.
Because when I take the sixth
power, actually,
ye, if I take the sixth power
b- all the sixth power of that
is one and the sixth power of
that
is one, the sixth power of this
is e to the two pi i,
that's one, the sixth power of
this is e to the minus two pi i,
that's one.
So the sixth powers,
the -- the sixth power of that
matrix has eigenvalues one and
one, so what is it?
It's the identity,
right.
So if I operate this -- if I
run this thing six times,
I'm back where I was.
The sixth power of that matrix
is the identity.
Good.
OK.
So it'll loop around,
it's -- it doesn't go to zero,
it doesn't blow up,
it just periodically goes
around with period six.
OK.
let's just see if there's a --
all right.
I'll -- let's see.
Could I also look at a -- at a
final exam from nineteen
ninety-two.
I think that's yeah,
let me do that on this last
board.
It starts -- a lot of the
questions in this exam are about
a family of matrices.
Let me give you the fourth,
the fourth guy in the family is
-- has a one,
so it's zeroes on the diagonal,
but these are going one,
two, three and so on.
One, two, three,
and so on.
But, for the four-by-four case
I'm stopping at four.
You see the pattern?
It's a family of matrices which
is growing, and actually the
numbers -- it's symmetric,
right, it's equal to A4
transpose.
And we can ask all sorts of
questions about its
null space, its range,
r- its column space find the
projection matrix onto the
column space of A3,
for example,
is in here.
So -- so one -- so A3 is zero,
one, zero, one,
zero, two, zero,
two, zero.
OK, find the projection matrix
onto
the column space.
By the way, is that matrix
singular or invertible?
Singular.
Why do we know it's singular?
I see that column three is a
multiple of column one.
Or we could take its
determinant.
So it's certainly singular.
The projection
will be matrix will be
three-by-three but it will
project onto the column space,
it'll project onto this plane.
The column space of A3,
and I guess I would find it
from the formula AA -- AA
transpose A inverse,
I would have to -- I would -- I
guess I would do all
this.
There may be a better way,
perhaps I could think there
might be a slightly quicker way,
but that would come out pretty
fast.
OK.
So that's be the projection
matrix.
Next question.
Find the eigenvalues and
eigenvectors of that matrix.
OK.
There's a three-by-three
matrix, oh, yeah,
so what are its eigenvalues and
eigenvectors,
we haven't done any
three-by-threes.
Let's do one.
I want to find,
so how do I find eigenvalues?
I take the determinant of A3
minus lambda I.
So this is you just have to --
so I'm subtracting lambda from
the diagonal,
and I have a one,
one, zero, zero,
two, two there,
and I just have to find that
determinant.
OK, since it's three-by-three
I'll just go for it.
This way gives me minus lambda
cubed and a zero and zero.
Then in this direction which
has the minus sign,
that's a zero,
four lambdas,
I mean minus four lambdas,
and minus another lambda,
so that's minus five lambdas,
but that direction goes with a
minus sign, so I think it's plus
five lambda.
That looks like the determinant
of A3 minus lambda I,
so I set it to zero.
So what are the eigenvalues?
Well, lambda equals zero --
lambda factors out of this,
times minus lambda
squared plus four,
so the eigenvalues are five,
thanks, thanks,
so the eigenvalues are zero,
square root of five,
and minus square root of five.
And I would never write down
those three eigenvalues without
checking the trace to tell the
truth.
Because -- because we did
a bunch of calculations here
but then I can quickly add up
the eigenvalues to get zero,
add up the trace to get zero,
and feel that I'm -- well,
I guess that wouldn't have
caught my error if I'd made it
-- if -- if that had been
a four I wouldn't have
noticed,the determinant isn't
anything greatly useful here,
right, because the determinant
is just zero.
And so I never would know
whether that five was right or
wrong, but thanks for making it
right.
OK.
Ha.
Question two c,
whoever wrote this,
probably me,
said this is not difficult.
I don't know why I put that in.
just -- it asks for the
projection matrix onto the
column space of A4.
How could I have thought that
wasn't difficult?
It looks extremely difficult.
what's the projection matrix
onto the column space of A4?
I don't know whether that --
this is not difficult is just
like helpful or -- or insulting.
Uh, what do you think?
The -- what's the column space
of A4 here?
Well, what's our first question
is
is the matrix singular or
invertible?
If the answer is invertible,
then what's the column space?
If -- if this matrix A4 is
invertible, so that's my guess,
if this problem's easy it has
to be because this matrix is
probably invertible.
Then its column space is R^4,
good, the column space is the
whole space, and the answer to
this easy question is the
projection matrix is the
identity, it's the four-by-four
identity matrix.
If this matrix is invertible.
Shall we check invertibility?
How would you find its
determinant?
Can we just like take the
determinant of that matrix?
I could ask you how -- so there
-- there are twenty-four terms,
do we want to write all
twenty-four terms down?
not in the remaining ten
seconds.
Better to use cofactors.
So I go along row one,
I see one -- the only nonzero
is this guy, so I should take
that one times the cofactor.
Now so I'm down to this
determinant.
OK.
So now I'm -- look at this
first column,
I see one times this,
there's the
cofactor of the one,
so I'm using up row one -- row
one and column one of this
three-by-three matrix,
I'm down to this cofactor,
and by the way,
those were both plus signs,
right?
No, they weren't.
That was a minus sign.
That was a --
that was a minus,
and then that was a plus,
and then this,
so what's the determinant?
Nine.
Determinant is nine.
Determinant of A4 is nine.
OK.
Where A3, so my guess is I'll
put that on the final this year,
the -- probably the odd-
numbered ones are singular and
the even-numbered ones are
invertible.
And I don't know what the
determinants are but I'm betting
that they have some nice
formula.
OK.
So, recitations this week will
also be quiz review and then the
quiz is Wednesday at one
o'clock.
Thanks.