OK.
So this is the first lecture on
eigenvalues and eigenvectors,
and that's a big subject that
will take up most of the rest of
the course.
It's, again,
matrices are square and we're
looking now for some special
numbers,
the eigenvalues,
and some special vectors,
the eigenvectors.
And so this lecture is mostly
about what are these numbers,
and then the other lectures are
about how do we use them,
why do we want them.
OK, so what's an eigenvector?
Maybe I'll start with
eigenvector.
What's an eigenvector?
So I have a matrix A.
OK.
What does a matrix do?
It acts on vectors.
It multiplies vectors x.
So the way that matrix acts is
in goes a vector x and out comes
a vector Ax.
It's like a function.
With a function in calculus,
in goes a number x,
out comes f(x).
Here in linear algebra we're up
in more dimensions.
In goes a vector x,
out comes a vector Ax.
And the vectors I'm specially
interested in are the ones the
come out in the same direction
that they went in.
That won't be typical.
Most vectors,
Ax is in -- points in
some different direction.
But there are certain vectors
where Ax comes out parallel to
x.
And those are the eigenvectors.
So Ax parallel to x.
Those are the eigenvectors.
And what do I mean by parallel?
Oh, much easier to just state
it in an equation.
Ax is some multiple -- and
everybody calls that multiple
lambda -- of x.
That's our big equation.
We look for special vectors --
and remember most vectors won't
be eigenvectors -- that -- for
which Ax is in the same
direction as x,
and by same direction I allow
it to
be the very opposite direction,
I allow lambda to be negative
or zero.
Well, I guess we've met the
eigenvectors that have
eigenvalue zero.
Those are in the same
direction, but they're -- in a
kind of very special way.
So this --
the eigenvector x.
Lambda, whatever this
multiplying factor is,
whether it's six or minus six
or zero or even some imaginary
number, that's the eigenvalue.
So there's the eigenvalue,
there's the eigenvector.
Let's just take a second on
eigenvalue zero.
From the point of view of
eigenvalues, that's no special
deal.
That's, we have an eigenvector.
If the eigenvalue happened to
be zero, that would mean that Ax
was zero x, in other words zero.
So what would x,
where would we look for -- what
are the x-s?
What are the eigenvectors with
eigenvalue zero?
They're the guys in the null
space, Ax equals zero.
So if our matrix is singular,
let me write this down.
If, if A is singular,
then that -- what does singular
mean?
It means that it takes some
vector x into zero.
Some non-zero vector,
that's why -- will be the
eigenvector into zero.
Then lambda equals zero is an
eigenvalue.
But we're interested in all
eigenvalues now,
lambda equals zero is not,
like, so special anymore.
OK.
So the question is,
how do we find these x-s and
lambdas?
And notice -- we don't have
an equation Ax equal B anymore.
I can't use elimination.
I've got two unknowns,
and in fact they're multiplied
together.
Lambda and x are both unknowns
here.
So, we need to,
we need a good idea of how to
find them.
But before I,
before I
do that, and that's where
determinant will come in,
can I just give you some
matrices?
Like here you go.
Take the matrix,
a projection matrix.
OK.
So suppose we have a plane and
our matrix P is -- what I've
called A, now I'm going to call
it P for the
moment, because it's -- I'm
thinking OK, let's look at a
projection matrix.
What are the eigenvalues of a
projection matrix?
So that's my question.
What are the x-s,
the eigenvectors,
and the lambdas,
the eigenvalues,
for -- and now let me say a
projection matrix.
My,
my point is that we -- before
we get into determinants and,
and formulas and all that
stuff, let's take some matrices
where we know what they do.
We know that if we take a
vector b, what this matrix does
is it projects it down to Pb.
So is b an eigenvector in,
in that picture?
Is that vector b an
eigenvector?
No.
Not so, so b is not an
eigenvector c- because Pb,
its projection,
is in a different direction.
So now tell me what vectors are
eigenvectors of P?
What vectors do get projected
in the same direction that they
start?
So, so answer,
tell me some x-s.
In this picture,
where could I start with a
vector b or x,
do its projection,
and end up in the same
direction?
Well, that would happen if the
vector was right in that plane
already.
If the vector x was -- so let
the vector x -- so any vector,
any x in the plane will be an
eigenvector.
And what will happen when I
multiply by P,
when I project a vector x -- I
called it b here,
because this is our familiar
picture, but now I'm going to
say that b was no good for,
for the, for our purposes.
I'm interested in a vector x
that's actually in the plane,
and I project it,
and what do I get back?
x, of course.
Doesn't move.
So any x in the plane is
unchanged by P,
and what's that telling me?
That's telling me that x is an
eigenvector,
and it's also telling me what's
the eigenvalue,
which is -- just compare it
with that.
The eigenvalue,
the multiplier,
is just one.
Good.
So we have actually a whole
plane of eigenvectors.
Now I ask, are there any other
eigenvectors?
And I expect the answer to be
yes, because I would like to get
three, if I'm in three
dimensions, I would like to hope
for three independent
eigenvectors,
two of them in the plane and
one not in the plane.
OK.
So this guy b that I drew there
was
not any good.
What's the right eigenvector
that's not in the plane?
The, the good one is the one
that's perpendicular to the
plane.
There's an, another good x,
because what's the projection?
So these are eigenvectors.
Another guy here would be
another eigenvector.
But now here is another one.
Any x that's perpendicular to
the plane, what's Px for that,
for that, vector?
What's the projection of this
guy
perpendicular to the plane?
It is zero, of course.
So -- there's the null space.
Px and n- for those guys are
zero, or zero x if we like,
and the eigenvalue is zero.
So my answer to the question
is, what are the eigenvalues for
a
projection matrix?
There they are.
One and zero.
OK.
We know projection matrices.
We can write them down as that
A, A transpose,
A inverse, A transpose thing,
but without doing that
from the picture we could see
what are the eigenvectors.
OK.
Are there other matrices?
Let me take a second example.
How about a permutation matrix?
What about the matrix,
I'll call it A now.
Zero one, one zero.
A equals zero one one zero,
that had eigenvalue one and
Can you tell me a vector x --
see, we'll have a system soon
enough, so I,
I would like to just do these
e- these couple of examples,
just to see the picture before
we, before we let it all,
go into a system where
that, matrix isn't anything
special.
Because it is special.
And what, so what vector could
I multiply by and end up in the
same direction?
Can you spot an eigenvector for
this guy?
That's a matrix that permutes
x1 and x2,
right?
It switches the two components
of x.
How could the vector with its
x2 x1, with -- permuted turn out
to be a multiple of x1 x2,
the vector we start with?
Can you tell me an eigenvector
here for this guy?
x equal -- what is -- actually,
can you tell me one vector that
has eigenvalue one?
So what, what vector would have
eigenvalue one,
so that if I,
if I permute it it doesn't
change?
right?
There, that could be one one,
thanks.
One one.
OK, take that vector one one.
That will be an eigenvector,
because if I do Ax I get one
one.
So that's the eigenvalue is
Great.
That's one eigenvalue.
But I have here a two by two
matrix, and I figure there's
going to be a second eigenvalue.
And eigenvector.
Now, what about that?
What's a vector,
OK, maybe we can just,
like, guess it.
A vector that the other --
actually, this one that I'm
thinking of is going to be a
vector that has eigenvalue minus
one.
That's going to be my other
eigenvalue for this matrix.
It's a -- notice the nice
positive or not negative matrix,
but an eigenvalue is going to
come out negative.
And can you guess,
spot the x that will work for
that?
So I want a,
a vector.
When I multiply by A,
which reverses the two
components, I want the thing to
come out minus the original.
So what shall I send in in that
case?
If I send in negative one one.
Then when I apply A,
I get I do that multiplication,
and I get one negative one,
so it reversed sign.
So Ax is -x.
Lambda is minus one.
Ax -- so Ax was x there and Ax
is minus x here.
Can I just mention,
like, jump ahead,
and point out a special little
fact about eigenvalues.
n by n matrices will have n
eigenvalues.
And it's not like -- suppose n
is three or four or more.
It's not so easy to find them.
We'd have a third degree or a
fourth degree or an n-th degree
equation.
But here's one nice fact.
There, there's one pleasant
fact.
That the sum of the eigenvalues
equals the sum down the
diagonal.
That's called the trace,
and I put that in the lecture
content specifically.
So this is a neat fact,
the fact that sthe sum of the
lambdas, add up the lambdas,
equals the sum -- what would
you like me to,
shall I write that down?
What I'm want to say in words
is the sum down
the diagonal of A.
Shall I write a11+a22+...+ ann.
That's add up the diagonal
entries.
In this example,
it's zero.
In other words,
once I found this eigenvalue of
one, I knew the other one had to
be minus
one in this two by two case,
because in the two by two case,
which is a good one to,
to, play with,
the trace tells you right away
what the other eigenvalue is.
So if I tell you one
eigenvalue, you can tell me the
other one.
We'll,
we'll have that -- we'll,
we'll see that again.
OK.
Now can I -- I could give more
examples, but maybe it's time to
face the, the equation,
Ax equal lambda x,
and figure how are we going to
find x and lambda.
OK.
So this, so the question now is
how to find eigenvalues and
eigenvectors.
How to solve,
how to solve Ax equal lambda x
when we've got two unknowns both
in the equation.
OK.
Here's the trick.
Simple idea.
Bring this onto the
same side.
Rewrite.
Bring this over as A minus
lambda times the identity x
equals zero.
Right?
I have Ax minus lambda x,
so I brought that over and I've
got zero left on the,
on the right-hand side.
OK.
I don't know lambda and I don't
know x, but I do know something
here.
What I know is if I,
if I'm going to be able to
solve this thing,
for some x that's not the zero
vector, that's not,
that's a useless eigenvector,
doesn't count.
What I know now is that
this matrix must be what?
If I'm going to be -- if there
is an x -- I don't -- right now
I don't know what it is.
I'm going to find lambda first,
actually.
And -- but if there is an x,
it tells me that this matrix,
this special combination,
which is like the matrix A with
lambda -- shifted by lambda,
shifted by lambda I,
that it has to be singular.
This matrix must be singular,
otherwise the only x would be
the zero x, and zero matrix.OK.
So this is singular.
And what do I now know about
singular matrices?
Their determinant is zero.
So I've -- so from the fact
that that has to be singular,
I know that the determinant of
A minus lambda I has to be zero.
And that, now I've got x out of
it.
I've got an equation for
lambda, that the key equation --
it's called the characteristic
equation or the eigenvalue
equation.
And that -- in other words,
I'm now in a position to find
lambda first.
So -- the idea will be to find
And actually,
I won't find one lambda,
I'll find N different lambdas.
Well, n lambdas,
maybe not n different
ones.
A lambda could be repeated.
A repeated lambda is the source
of all trouble in 18.06.
So, let's hope for the moment
that they're not repeated.
There, there they were
different, right?
One and minus one in that,
in that, for that permutation.
OK.
So and after I found this
lambda, can I just look ahead?
How I going to find x?
After I have found this lambda,
the lambda being this -- one of
the numbers that makes this
matrix singular.
Then of course finding x is
just by elimination.
Right?
It's just -- now I've got a
singular matrix,
I'm looking for the null space.
We're experts at finding the
null space.
You know, you do elimination,
you identify the,
the, the pivot columns and so
on,
you're -- and,
give values to the free
variables.
Probably there'll only be one
free variable.
We'll give it the value one,
like there.
And we find the other variable.
OK.
So let's -- find the x second
will be a doable job.
Let's go, let's look at the
first job of finding lambda.
OK.
Can I take another example?
And let's, let's work that one
out.
OK.
So let me take the example,
say, let me make it easy.
it's just sitting there.
Three
three one and one.
what do you know about the
complex numbers?
So I've made it easy.
I've made it two by two.
I've made it symmetric.
And I even made it constant
down the diagonal.
That a matrix,
a perfectly real matrix could
So that -- so the more,
like, special properties I
stick into the matrix,
the more special outcome I
get for the eigenvalues.
For example,
this symmetric matrix,
I know that it'll come out with
real eigenvalues.
The eigenvalues will turn out
to be nice real numbers.
And up in our previous example,
that was a symmetric matrix.
Actually, while we're at it,
Its eigenvalues were nice real
numbers, one and minus one.
And do you notice anything
about its eigenvectors?
Anything particular about those
two vectors, one one and minus
And now comes that thing that I
wanted to be reminded of.
one one?
They just happen to be -- no,
I can't say they just happen to
be, because that's the whole
point, is that they had to be --
what?
What are they?
They're perpendicular.
The vector, when I -- if I see
a vector one one and a one --
and a minus one one,
my mind immediately takes that
dot product.
It's zero.
what's the determinant of that
matrix?
Those vectors are
perpendicular.
That'll happen here too.
Well, let's find the
eigenvalues.
Actually, oh,
my example's too easy.
My example is too easy.
Let me tell you in advance
what's going to happen.
May I?
Or shall I do the determinant
of A minus lambda,
and then point out at the end?
Will you remind me at the --
after I've found the
eigenvalues to say why they
were -- why they were easy from
the, from the example we did?
OK, let's do the job here.
Let's compute determinant of A
minus lambda I.
So that's a determinant.
And what's,
what is this thing?
It's the matrix A with lambda
removed from the diagonal.
So the diagonal matrix is
shifted, and then I'm taking the
determinant.
OK.
So I multiply this out.
So what is that determinant?
Do you notice,
I didn't take lambda away from
all the entries.
It's lambda I,
so it's lambda along the
diagonal.
So I get three minus lambda
squared and then minus one,
right?
And I want that to be zero.
Well, I'm going to simplify it.
And what will I get?
So if I multiply this out,
I get lambda squared minus six
lambda plus what?
Plus eight.
But it's out there.
And that I'm going to set to
zero.
And I'm
going to solve it.
So and it's,
it's a quadratic equation.
I can use factorization,
I can use the quadratic
formula.
I'll get two lambdas.
Before I do it,
tell me what's that number six
that's showing up in this
equation?
It's the trace.
That number six is three plus
three.
And while we're at it,
what's the number eight that's
showing up in this equation?
It's the determinant.
That our matrix has determinant
eight.
So in a two by two case,
it's really nice.
It's lambda squared minus the
trace times lambda -- the trace
is the linear coefficient -- and
plus the determinant,
the constant term.
OK.
So let's -- can,
can we find the roots?
I guess the easy way is to
factor that as something times
something.
If we couldn't factor it,
then we'd have to use the old
b^2-4ac formula,
but I, I think we can factor
that into lambda minus what
times lambda minus what?
Can you do that factorization?
Four and two?
Lambda minus four times lambda
minus two.
So the, the eigenvalues are
four and two.
So the eigenvalues are -- one
eigenvalue, lambda one,
let's say, is four.
Lambda two, the other
eigenvalue, is two.
The eigenvalues are four and
two.
And then I can go for the
eigenvectors.
Suppose I have a matrix A,
and Ax equal lambda x.
You see I got the eigenvalues
first.
Four and two.
Now for the eigenvectors.
So what are the eigenvectors?
They're these guys in the null
space when I take away,
when I make the matrix singular
by
taking four I or two I away.
So we're -- we got to do those
separately.
I'll -- let me find the
eigenvector for four first.
So I'll subtract four,
so A minus four I is -- so
taking four away will put minus
ones there.
And what's the point
about that matrix?
If four is an eigenvalue,
then A minus four I had better
be a what kind of matrix?
Singular.
If that matrix isn't singular,
the four wasn't correct.
But we're OK,
that matrix is singular.
And what's the x now?
The x is in the null
space.
So what's the x1 that goes
with, with the lambda one?
eigenvalue, eigenvector,
eigenvalue for this,
So that A -- so this is -- now
I'm doing A x1 is lambda one x1.
So I took A minus lambda one I,
that's this matrix,
and now I'm looking for the x1
in its null space,
and who is he?
What's the vector x in the null
space?
Of course it's one one.
So that's the eigenvector that
goes with that eigenvalue.
Now how about the eigenvector
that goes with the other
eigenvalue?
Can I do that with,
with erasing?
I take A minus two I.
So now I take two away from the
diagonal, and that leaves me
with a one and a one.
So A minus two I has again
produced a singular matrix,
as it had to.
I'm looking for the null space
of that guy.
What vector is in its null
space?
Well, of course,
a whole line of vectors.
So when I say the eigenvector,
I'm not speaking correctly.
There's a whole line of
eigenvectors,
and you just -- I just want a
basis.
And for a line I just want one
vector.
But -- You could,
you're -- there's some freedom
in choosing that one,
but choose a reasonable one.
What's a vector in the null
space of that?
Well, the natural vector to
pick as the eigenvector with,
with lambda two is minus one
one.
If I did elimination on that
vector and set that,
the free variable to be one,
I would get minus one and get
that eigenvector.
So you see then that
I've got eigenvector,
for this matrix?
What's the relation between
that problem and -- let me write
just above what we2
found here.
minus one and eigenvectors one
one and eigenvector minus one
one.
And what do you notice?
What's -- how is this matrix
related to that matrix?
How are those two matrices
related?
Well, one is just three I more
than the other one,
right?
two.
I just took that matrix and I
-- I took this matrix and I
added three I.
So my question is,
what happened to the
eigenvalues and
eigenvectors?
That's the, that's like the
question we keep asking now in
this chapter.
If I, if I do something to the
matrix, what happens if I -- or
I know something about the
matrix, what's the what's the
conclusion for its eigenvectors
and
eigenvalues?
Because -- those eigenvalues
and eigenvectors are going to
tell us important information
about the matrix.
And here what are we seeing?
What's happening to these
eigenvalues, one and minus one,
when I add three
I?
It just added three to the
eigenvalues.
I got four and two,
three more than one and minus
one.
What happened to the
eigenvectors?
Nothing at all.
One one is -- and minus -- and
one -- and minus
one one are -- is still the
eigenvectors.
In other words,
simple but useful observation.
If I add three I to a matrix,
its eigenvectors don't change
and its eigenvalues are three
bigger.
Let's, let's just see why.
Let me keep all
this on the same board.
Now I add three I to that
matrix.
Do you see what3
so it's if Ax equals lambda x,
then this, this other new
matrix, I just have an Ax,
which is lambda x,
and I have a three x,
from the three x,
so it's just I mean,
Lambda plus three x.
So if they, if this had
eigenvalue lambda,
this has eigenvalue lambda plus
three.
And x, the eigenvector,
is the same x for both
matrices.
OK.
So that's, great.
Of course, it's special.
We got the new matrix by adding
three I.
Suppose I had added another
matrix.
Suppose I know the eigenvalues
and eigenvectors of A.
So this is, this,
this little board here is going
to be not so great.
Suppose I have a matrix A and
it has an eigenvector x with
an eigenvalue lambda.
You remember,
I solve A minus lambda I x
And now I add on some other
matrix.
So, so what I'm asking you is,
if you know the eigenvalues of
A and you know the eigenvalues
of B, let me say suppose B -- so
this is if -- let me put an if
here.
If Ax equals lambda x,
fine, and B has,
eigenvalues,
has eigenvalues -- what shall
we call them?
Alpha, alpha one and alpha --
let's say -- I'll use alpha for
the eigenvalues of B for no good
reason.
What a- you see what I'm going
to ask is, how about A plus B?
Let me, let me give you the,
let me give you,
what you might think first.
OK.
If Ax equals lambda x and if B
has an eigenvalue alpha,
then I allowed to say -- what's
the matter with this argument?
It's wrong.
What I'm going to write up is
wrong.
I'm going to say Bx is alpha x.
Add those up,
and you get A plus B x equals
lambda plus alpha x.
So you would think that if you
know the eigenvalues of A and
you knew the eigenvalues of B,
then if you added you would
know the eigenvalues of A plus
B.
But that's false.
A plus B -- well,
when B was three I,
that worked great.
But this is not so great.
And what's the matter with that
argument there?
We have no reason to believe
that x is also an eigenvector of
B.
B has some
eigenvalues,
but it's got some different
eigenvectors normally.
It's a different matrix.
I don't know anything special.
If I don't know anything
special, then as far as I know,
it's got some different
eigenvector y,
and when I add I
get just rubbish.
I mean, I get -- I can add,
but I don't learn anything.
So not so great is A plus B.
Or A times B.
Normally the eigenvalues of A
plus B or A times B are not
eigenvalues of A plus
eigenvalues of B.
Ei- eigenvalues are not,
like, linear.
Or -- and they don't multiply.
Because, eigenvectors are
usually different and,
and there's just no way to find
out what A plus B does to affect
it.
OK.
So that's, like,
a caution.
Don't, if B is a multiple of
the identity,
great, but if B is some general
matrix, then for A plus B you've
got to find -- you've got to
solve the eigenvalue problem.
OK.
Now I want to do another
example that brings out a,
another point about
eigenvalues.
Let me make this example a
rotation matrix.
OK.
So here's another example.
So a rotate -- oh,
I'd better call it Q.
I often use Q for,
for, rotations because those
are the, like,
very important examples of
orthogonal matrices.
Let me make it a ninety degree
rotation.
So -- my matrix is going to be
the one that rotates every
vector by ninety degrees.
So do you remember
that matrix?
It's the cosine of ninety
degrees, which is zero,
the sine of ninety degrees,
which is one,
minus the sine of ninety,
the cosine of ninety.
So that matrix deserves the
letter Q.
It's an orthogonal matrix,
very, very orthogonal matrix.
Now I'm interested in its
eigenvalues and eigenvectors.
Two by two, it can't be that
tough.
We know that the eigenvalues
add to zero.
Actually, we know something
already here.
The eigen- what's the sum of
the two eigenvalues?
Just tell
me what I just said.
Zero, right.
From that trace business.
The sum of the eigenvalues is,
is going to come out zero.
And the product of the
eigenvalues, did I tell you
about the determinant
being the product of the
eigenvalues?
No.
But that's a good thing to
know.
We pointed out how that eight
appeared in the,
in the quadratic equation.
So let me just say this.
The trace is zero plus zero,
obviously.
And that's the sum,
that's lambda one plus lambda
Now the other neat fact is that
the determinant,
One.
And that is lambda one times
lambda3
two.
In our example,
the one we worked out,
we -- the eigenvalues came out
four and two.
Their product was eight.
That -- it had to be eight,
because we factored into lambda
minus four times lambda minus
two.
That gave us the constant term
eight.
And that was the determinant.
OK.
What I'm leading up to with
this example is that something's
going to go wrong.
Something goes wrong for
rotation because what vector can
come out parallel to itself
after a rotation?
If this matrix rotates every
vector by ninety degrees,
what could be an eigenvector?
Do you see we're,
we're, we're going to have
trouble.
eigenvectors are -- Well.
Our, our picture of
eigenvectors,
of, of coming out in the same
direction that they went in,
there won't be it.
And with, and with eigenvalues
we're going to have trouble.
From these equations.
Let's see.
Why I expecting trouble?
The, the first equation says
that the
eigenvalues add to zero.
So there's a plus and a minus.
But then the second equation
says that the product is plus
one.
We're in trouble.
But there's a way out.
So how -- let's do the usual
stuff.
Look at determinant of Q minus
lambda I.
So I'll just follow the rules,
take the determinant,
subtract lambda from the
diagonal, where I had zeros,
the rest is the same.
Rest of Q is just copied.
Compute that determinant.
OK, so what does that
determinant equal?
Lambda squared minus minus one
plus what?
What's up?
There's my equation.
My equation for the eigenvalues
is lambda squared plus one
equals zero.
What are the eigenvalues lambda
one
and lambda two?
They're I, whatever that is,
and minus it,
right.
Those are the right numbers.
To be real numbers even though
the matrix was perfectly real.
So this can happen.
Complex numbers are going to --
have to enter eighteen oh six at
this moment.
Boo, right.
All right.
If I just choose good
matrices that have real
eigenvalues, we can postpone
that evil day,
but just so you see -- so I'll
try to do that.
have, give a perfectly
innocent-looking quadratic
thing,4
but the roots of that quadratic
can be complex numbers.
And of course you -- everybody
knows that they're -- what,
So, so now -- Let's just spend
one more minute on this bad
possibility of complex numbers.
We do know a little information
about the, the two complex
numbers.
They're complex conjugates of
each other.
If, if lambda is an eigenvalue,
then when I change,
when I go -- you remember what
complex conjugates are?
You switch the sign of the
imaginary part.
Well, this was only imaginary,
had no real part,
so we just switched its sign.
So that eigenvalues come in
pairs like that,
but they're complex.
A complex conjugate pair.
And that can happen
with a perfectly real matrix.
And as a matter of fact -- so
that was my, my point earlier,
that if a matrix was symmetric,
it wouldn't happen.
So if we stick to matrices that
are symmetric or,
like, close to symmetric,
then the eigenvalues will stay
real.
But if we move far away
from symmetric -- and that's as
far as you can move,
because that matrix is -- how
is Q transpose related to Q for
that matrix?
That matrix is anti-symmetric.
Q transpose is minus Q.
That's the very opposite of
symmetry.
When I flip across the diagonal
I get -- I reverse all the
signs.
Those are the guys that have
pure imaginary eigenvalues.
So they're the extreme case.
And in between are,
are matrices that are not
symmetric or anti-symmetric but,
but they have partly a
symmetric
part and an anti-symmetric
part.
OK.
So I'm doing a bunch of
examples here to show the
possibilities.
The good possibilities being
perpendicular eigenvectors,
real eigenvalues.
The bad possibilities being
complex eigenvalues.
We could say that's bad.
There's another even worse.
I'm getting through the,
the bad things here today.
Then, then the next lecture
can, can, can be like pure
happiness.
OK.
Here's one more bad thing
that could happen.
So I, again,
I'll do it with an example.
Suppose my matrix is,
suppose I take this three three
one and I change that guy to
zero.
What are the eigenvalues of
that matrix?
What are the eigenvectors?
This is
always our question.
Of course, the next section
we're going to show why are,
why do we care.
But for the moment,
this lecture is introducing
them.
And let's just find them.
OK.
What are the eigenvalues of
that matrix?
Let me tell you -- at a glance
we could answer that question.
Because the matrix is
triangular.
It's really useful to know --
if you've got properties like a
triangular matrix.
It's very useful to know you
can read the eigenvalues
off.
They're right on the diagonal.
So the eigenvalue is three and
also three.
Three is a repeated eigenvalue.
But let's see that happen.
Let me do it right.
The determinant of A minus
lambda I, what I always have to
do is this
determinant.
I take away lambda from the
diagonal.
I leave the rest.
I compute the determinant,
so I get a three minus lambda
times a three minus lambda.
And nothing.
So that's where the triangular
part came in.
Triangular part,
the one thing we know about
triangular matrices is the
determinant is just the product
down the diagonal.
And in this case,
it's this same,
repeated -- so lambda one is
one -- sorry,
lambda one is three and lambda
two is three.
That was easy.
I mean, no -- why should I be
pessimistic about a matrix whose
eigenvalues can be read off
right away?
The problem with this matrix is
in the eigenvectors.
So let's go to the
eigenvectors.
So how do I find the
eigenvectors?
I'm looking for a couple of
eigenvectors.
So I take the eigenvalue.
What do I do now?
equals zero.
And what is A minus lambda I x?
So, so take three away.
And I get this matrix4
zero zero zero one,
Times x is supposed to give me
zero, right?
That's my big equation for x.
Now I'm looking for x,
the eigenvector.
So I took A minus lambda I x,
and what kind of a matrix I
supposed to have here?
Singular, right?
It's supposed to be singular.
And then it's got some vectors
-- which it is.
So it's got some vector x in
the null space.
And what, what's the,
what's -- give me a basis for
the null space for that guy.
Tell me, what's a vector x in
the null space,
so that'll be the,
the eigenvector that goes with
lambda one equals three.
The eigenvector is -- so what's
in the null space?
One zero, is it?
Great.
Now, what's the other
eigenvector?
What's, what's the eigenvector
that goes with lambda two?
Well, lambda two is three
again.
So I get the same thing again.
Give me another vector -- I
want it to be independent.
If I'm going to write
down an x2, I'm never going to
let it be dependent on x1.
I'm looking for independent
eigenvectors,
and what's the conclusion?
There isn't one.
This is a degenerate matrix.
It's only got one line of
eigenvectors instead of two.
It's this possibility of a
repeated eigenvalue opens this
further possibility of a
shortage of eigenvectors.
And so there's no second
independent eigenvector x2.
So it's a matrix,
it's a two by two matrix,
but with
only one independent
eigenvector.
So that will be -- the matrices
that -- where eigenvectors are
-- don't give the complete
story.
OK.
My lecture on Monday will give
the complete story for all the
other matrices.
Thanks.
Have a good weekend.
A real New England weekend.