OK, here is lecture ten in
linear algebra.
Two important things to do in
this lecture.
One is to correct an error from
lecture nine.
So the blackboard with that
awful error is still with us.
And the second,
the big thing to do is to tell
you about the four subspaces
that come with a matrix.
We've seen two subspaces,
the column space and the null
space.
There's two to go.
OK.
First of all,
and this is a great way to
recap and correct the previous
lecture -- so you remember I was
just doing R^3.
I couldn't have taken a simpler
example than R^3.
And I wrote down the standard
basis.
That's the standard basis.
The basis -- the obvious basis
for the whole three dimensional
space.
And then I wanted to make the
point that there was nothing
special, nothing about that
basis that another basis
couldn't have.
It could have linear
independence,
it could span a space.
There's lots of other bases.
So I started with these
vectors, one one two and two two
five, and those were
independent.
And then I said three three
seven wouldn't do,
because three three seven is
the sum of those.
So in my innocence,
I put in three three eight.
I figured probably if three
three seven is on the plane,
is -- which I know,
it's in the plane with these
two, then probably three three
eight sticks a little bit out of
the plane and it's independent
and it gives a basis.
But after class,
to my sorrow,
a student tells me,
"Wait a minute,
that ba- that third vector,
three three eight,
is not independent." And why
did she say that?
She didn't actually take the
time, didn't have to,
to find w- w- what combination
of this one and this one gives
three three eight.
She did something else.
In other words,
she looked ahead,
because she said,
wait a minute,
if I look at that matrix,
it's not invertible.
That third column can't be
independent of the first two,
because when I look at that
matrix, it's got two identical
rows.
I have a square matrix.
Its rows are obviously
dependent.
And that makes the columns
So there's my error.
When I look at the matrix A
that has those three columns,
those three columns can't be
independent because that matrix
is not invertible because it's
got two equal rows.
And today's lecture will reach
the conclusion,
the great conclusion,
that connects the column space
with the row space.
So those are -- the row space
is now going to be another one
of my fundamental subspaces.
The row space of this matrix,
or of this one -- well,
the row space of this one is
OK, but the row space of this
one, I'm looking at the rows of
the matrix -- oh,
anyway, I'll have two equal
rows and the row space will be
only two dimensional.
The rank of the matrix with
these columns will only be two.
So only two of those columns,
columns can be independent too.
The rows tell me something
about the columns,
in other words,
something that I should have
noticed and I didn't.
OK.
So now let me pin down these
four fundamental subspaces.
So here are the four
fundamental subspaces.
This is really the heart of
this approach to linear algebra,
to see these four subspaces,
how they're related.
So what are they?
The column space,
C of A.
The null space,
N of A.
And now comes the row space,
something new.
The row space,
what's in that?
It's all combinations of the
rows.
That's natural.
We want a space,
so we have to take all
combinations,
and we start with the rows.
So the rows span the row space.
Are the rows a basis for the
row space?
Maybe so, maybe no.
The rows are a basis for the
row space when they're
independent, but if they're
dependent, as in this example,
my error from last time,
they're not -- those three rows
are not a basis.
The row space wouldn't -- would
only be two dimensional.
I only need two rows for a
basis.
So the row space,
now what's in it?
It's all combinations of the
rows of A.
All combinations of the rows of
A.
But I don't like working with
row vectors.
All my vectors have been column
vectors.
I'd like to stay with column
How can I get to column vectors
out of these rows?
I transpose the matrix.
So if that's OK with you,
I'm going to transpose the
matrix.
I'm, I'm going to say all
combinations of the columns of A
transpose.
And that allows me to use the
convenient notation,
the column space of A
transpose.
Nothing, no mathematics went on
there.
We just got some vectors that
were lying down to stand up.
But it means that we can use
this column space of A
transpose, that's telling me in
a nice matrix notation what the
row space is.
OK.
And finally is another null
space.
The fourth fundamental space
will be the null space of A
transpose.
The fourth guy is the null
space of A transpose.
And of course my notation is N
of A transpose.
That's the null space of A
transpose.
Eh, we don't have a perfect
name for this space as a --
connecting with A,
but our usual name is the left
null space, and I'll show you
why in a moment.
So often I call this the --
just to write that word -- the
left null space of A.
So just the way we have the row
space of A and we switch it to
the column space of A transpose,
so we have this space of guys
l- that I call the left null
space of A, but the good
notation is it's the null space
of A transpose.
OK.
Those are four spaces.
Where are those spaces?
What, what big space are they
in for -- when A is m by n?
In that case,
the null space of A,
what's in the null space of A?
Vectors with n components,
solutions to A x equals zero.
So the null space of A is in
R^n.
What's in the column space of
A?
Well, columns.
How many components dothose
columns have?
m.
So this column space is in R^m.
What about the column space of
A transpose, which are just a
disguised way of saying the rows
of A?
The rows of A,
in this three by six matrix,
have six components,
n components.
The column space is in R^n.
And the null space of A
transpose, I see that this
fourth space is already getting
second, you know,
second class citizen treatment
and it doesn't deserve it.
It's, it should be there,
it is there,
and shouldn't be squeezed.
The null space of A transpose
--
well, if the null space of A
had vectors with n components,
the null space of A transpose
will be in R^m.
I want to draw a picture of the
four spaces.
OK.
Here are the four spaces.
OK, Let me put n dimensional
space over on this side.
Then which were the subspaces
in R^n?
The null space was and the row
space was.
So here we have the -- can I
make that picture of the row
space?
And can I make this kind of
picture of the null space?
That's just meant to be a
sketch, to remind you that
they're in this --
which you know,
how -- what type of vectors are
in it?
Vectors with n components.
Over here, inside,
consisting of vectors with m
components, is the column space
and what I'm calling the null
space of A transpose.
Those are the ones with m
components.
OK.
To understand these spaces is
our, is our job now.
Because by understanding those
spaces, we know everything about
this half of linear algebra.
What do I mean by understanding
those spaces?
I would like to know a basis
for those spaces.
For each one of those spaces,
how would I create -- construct
a basis?
What systematic way would
produce a basis?
And what's their dimension?
OK.
So for each of the four spaces,
I have to answer those
questions.
How do I produce a basis?
And then -- which has a
somewhat long answer.
And what's the dimension,
which is just a number,
so it has a real short answer.
Can I give you the short answer
first?
I shouldn't do it,
but here it is.
I can tell you the dimension of
the column space.
Let me start with this guy.
What's its dimension?
I have an m by n matrix.
The dimension of the column
space is the rank,
r.
We actually got to that at the
end of the last lecture,
but only for an example.
So I really have to say,
OK, what's going on there.
I should produce a basis and
then I just look to see how many
vectors I needed in that basis,
and the answer will be r.
Actually, I'll do that,
before I get on to the others.
What's a basis for the columns
space?
We've done all the work of row
reduction, identifying the pivot
columns, the ones that have
pivots, the ones that end up
with pivots.
But now I -- the pivot columns
I'm interested in are columns of
A, the original A.
And those pivot columns,
there are r of them.
The rank r counts those.
Those are a basis.
So if I answer this question
for the column space,
the answer will be a basis is
the pivot columns and the
dimension is the rank r,
and there are r pivot columns
and everything great.
OK.
So that space we pretty well
understand.
I probably have a little going
back to see that -- to prove
that this is a right answer,
but you know it's the right
answer.
Now let me look at the row
space.
OK.
Shall I tell you the dimension
of the row space?
Yes.
Before we do even an example,
let me tell you the dimension
of the row space.
Its dimension is also r.
The row space and the column
space have the same dimension.
That's a wonderful fact.
The dimension of the column
space of A transpose --
that's the row space -- is r.
That, that space is r
dimensional.
Snd so is this one.
OK.
That's the sort of insight that
got used in this example.
If those --
are the three columns of a
matrix -- let me make them the
three columns of a matrix by
just erasing some brackets.
OK, those are the three columns
of a matrix.
The rank of that matrix,
if I look at the columns,
it wasn't obvious to me anyway.
But if I look at the rows,
now it's obvious.
The row space of that matrix
obviously is two dimensional,
because I see a basis for the
row space, this row and that
row.
And of course,
strictly speaking,
I'm supposed to transpose those
guys, make them stand up.
But the rank is two,
and therefore the column space
is two dimensional by this
wonderful fact that the row
space and column space have the
same dimension.
And therefore there are only
two pivot columns,
not three, and,
those, the three columns are
dependent.
OK.
Now let me bury that error and
talk about the row space.
Well, I'm going to give you the
dimensions of all the spaces.
Because that's such a nice
answer.
OK.
So let me come back here.
So we have this great fact to
establish, that the row space,
its dimension is also the rank.
OK.
What about the null space?
What's a basis for the null
space?
What's the dimension of the
null space?
Let me, I'll put that answer up
here for the null space.
Well, how have we constructed
the null space?
We took the matrix A,
we did those row operations to
get it into a form U or,
or even further.
We got it into the reduced form
R.
And then we read off special
solutions.
Special solutions.
And every special solution came
from a free variable.
And those special solutions are
in the null space,
and the great thing is they're
a basis for it.
So for the null space,
a basis will be the special
solutions.
And there's one for every free
variable, right?
For each free variable,
we give that variable the value
one, the other free variables
zero.
We get the pivot variables,
we get a vector in the -- we
get a special solution.
So we get altogether n-r of
them, because that's the number
of free variables.
If we have r -- this is the
dimension is r,
is the number of pivot
variables.
This is the number of free
So the beauty is that those
special solutions do form a
basis and tell us immediately
that the dimension of the null
space is n --
I better write this well,
because it's so nice -- n-r.
And do you see the nice thing?
That the two dimensions in this
n dimensional space,
one subspace is r dimensional
-- to be proved,
that's the row space.
The other subspace is n-r
dimensional, that's the null
space.
And the two dimensions like
together give n.
The sum of r and n-R is n.
And that's just great.
It's really copying the fact
that we have n variables,
r of them are pivot variables
and n-r are free variables,
and n altogether.
OK.
And now what's the dimension of
this poor misbegotten fourth
subspace?
It's got to be m-r.
The dimension of this left null
space, left out practically,
is m-r.
Well, that's really just saying
that this -- again,
the sum of that plus that is m,
and m is correct,
it's the number of columns in A
transpose.
A transpose is just as good a
matrix as A.
It just happens to be n by m.
It happens to have m columns,
so it will have m variables
when I go to A x equals 0 and m
of them, and r of them will be
pivot variables and m-r will be
free variables.
A transpose is as good a matrix
as A.
It follows the same rule that
the this plus the dimension --
this dimension plus this
dimension adds up to the number
of columns.
And over here,
A transpose has m columns.
OK.
So I gave you the easy answer,
the dimensions.
Now can I go back to check on a
basis?
We would like to think that --
say the row space,
because we've got a basis for
the column space.
The pivot columns give a basis
for the column space.
Now I'm asking you to look at
the row space.
And I -- you could say,
OK, I can produce a basis for
the row space by transposing my
matrix, making those columns,
then doing elimination,
row reduction,
and checking out the pivot
columns in this transposed
matrix.
But that means you had to do
all that row reduction on A
transpose.
It ought to be possible,
if we take a matrix A -- let me
take the matrix -- maybe we had
this matrix in the last lecture.
1 1 1, 2 1 2,
3 2 3, 1 1 1.
OK.
That, that matrix was so easy.
We spotted its pivot columns,
one and two,
without actually doing row
reduction.
But now let's do the job
properly.
So I subtract this away from
this to produce a zero.
So one 2 3 1 is fine.
Subtracting that away leaves me
minus 1 -1 0,
right?
And subtracting that from the
last row, oh,
well that's easy.
OK?
I'm doing row reduction.
Now I've -- the first column is
all set.
The second column I now see the
pivot.
And I can clean up,
if I -- actually,
OK.
Why don't I make the pivot into
a 1.
I'll multiply that row through
by by -1, and then I have 1 1.
That was an elementary
operation I'm allowed,
multiply a row by a number.
And now I'll do elimination.
Two of those away from that
will knock this guy out and make
this into a 1.
So that's now a 0 and that's a
OK.
Done.
That's R.
I'm seeing the identity matrix
here.
I'm seeing zeros below.
And I'm seeing F there.
OK.
What about its row space?
What happened to its row space
-- well, what happened -- let me
first ask, just because this is,
is -- sometimes something does
happen.
Its column space changed.
The column space of R is not
the column space of A,
right?
Because 1 1 1 is certainly in
the column space of A and
certainly not in the column
space of R.
I did row operations.
Those row operations preserve
the row space.
So the row, so the column
spaces are different.
Different column spaces,
different column spaces.
But I believe that they have
the same row space.
Same row space.
I believe that the row space of
that matrix and the row space of
this matrix are identical.
They have exactly the same
vectors in them.
Those vectors are vectors with
four components,
right?
They're all combinations of
those rows.
Or I believe you get the same
thing by taking all combinations
of these rows.
And if true,
what's a basis?
What's a basis for the row
space of R, and it'll be a basis
for the row space of the
original A, but it's obviously a
basis for the row space of R.
What's a basis for the row
space of that matrix?
The first two rows.
So a basis for the row -- so a
basis is, for the row space of A
or of R, is, is the first R rows
of R.
Not of A.
Sometimes it's true for A,
but not necessarily.
But R, we definitely have a
matrix here whose row space we
can, we can identify.
The row space is spanned by the
three rows, but if we want a
basis we want independence.
So out goes row three.
The row space is also spanned
by the first two rows.
This guy didn't contribute
anything.
And of course over here this 1
2 3 1 in the bottom didn't
contribute anything.
We had it already.
So this, here is a basis.
1 0 1 1 and 0 1 1 0.
I believe those are in the row
space.
I know they're independent.
Why are they in the row space?
Why are those two vectors in
the row space?
Because all those operations we
did, which started with these
rows and took combinations of
them --
I took this row minus this row,
that gave me something that's
still in the row space.
That's the point.
When I took a row minus a
multiple of another row,
I'm staying in the row space.
The row space is not changing.
My little basis for it is
changing, and I've ended up
with, sort of the best basis.
If the columns of the identity
matrix are the best basis for
R^3 or R^n, the rows of this
the row space.
Best in the sense of being as
clean as I can make it.
Starting off with the identity
and then finishing up with
whatever has to be in there.
OK.
Do you see then that the
dimension is r?
For sure, because we've got r
pivots, r non-zero rows.
We've got the right number of
vectors, r.
They're in the row space,
they're independent.
That's it.
They are a basis for the row
space.
And we can even pin that down
further.
How do I know that every row of
A is a combination?
How do I know they span the row
space?
Well, somebody says,
I've got the right number of
them, so they must.
But -- and that's true.
But let me just say,
how do I know that this row is
a combination of these?
By just reversing the steps of
row reduction.
If I just reverse the steps and
go from A -- from R back to A,
then what do I,
what I doing?
I'm starting with these rows,
I'm taking combinations of
them.
After a couple of steps,
undoing the subtractions that I
did before, I'm back to these
rows.
So these rows are combinations
of those rows.
Those rows are combinations of
those rows.
The two row spaces are the
same.
The bases are the same.
And the natural basis is this
guy.
Is that all right for the row
space?
The row space is sitting there
in R in its cleanest possible
form.
OK.
Now what about the fourth guy,
the null space of A transpose?
First of all,
why do I call that the left
null space?
So let me save that and bring
that down.
OK.
So the fourth space is the null
space of A transpose.
So it has in it vectors,
let me call them y,
so that A transpose y equals 0.
If A transpose y equals 0,
then y is in the null space of
A transpose, of course.
So this is a matrix times a
column equaling zero.
And now, because I want y to
sit on the left and I want A
instead of A transpose,
I'll just transpose that
equation.
Can I just transpose that?
On the right,
it makes the zero vector lie
down.
And on the left,
it's a product,
A, A transpose times y.
If I take the transpose,
then they come in opposite
order, right?
So that's y transpose times A
transpose transpose.
But nobody's going to leave it
like that.
That's -- A transpose transpose
is just A, of course.
When I transposed A transpose I
got back to A.
Now do you see what I have now?
I have a row vector,
y transpose,
multiplying A,
and multiplying from the left.
That's why I call it the left
null space.
But by making it --
putting it on the left,
I had to make it into a row
instead of a column vector,
and so my convention is I
usually don't do that.
I usually stay with A transpose
y equals 0.
OK.
And you might ask,
how do we get a basis --
or I might ask,
how do we get a basis for this
fourth space,
this left null space?
OK.
I'll do it in the example.
As always -- not that one.
The left null space is not
jumping out at me here.
I know which are the free
variables --
the special solutions,
but those are special solutions
to A x equals zero,
and now I'm looking at A
transpose, and I'm not seeing it
here.
So -- but somehow you feel that
the work that you did which
simplified A to R should have
revealed the left null space
too.
And it's slightly less
immediate, but it's there.
So from A to R,
I took some steps,
and I guess I'm interested in
what were those steps,
or what were all of them
together.
I don't -- I'm not interested
in what particular ones they
were.
I'm interested in what was the
whole matrix that took me from A
to R.
How would you find that?
Do you remember Gauss-Jordan,
where you tack on the identity
matrix?
Let's do that again.
So I, I'll do it above,
here.
So this is now,
this is now the idea of -- I
take the matrix A,
which is m by n.
In Gauss-Jordan,
when we saw him before --
A was a square invertible
matrix and we were finding its
inverse.
Now the matrix isn't square.
It's probably rectangular.
But I'll still tack on the
identity matrix,
and of course since these have
length m it better be m by m.
And now I'll do the reduced row
echelon form of this matrix.
And what do I get?
The reduced row echelon form
starts with these columns,
starts with the first columns,
works like mad,
and produces R.
Of course, still that same
size, m by n.
And we did it before.
And then whatever it did to get
R, something else is going to
show up here.
Let me call it E,
m by m.
It's whatever -- do you see
that E is just going to contain
a record of what we did?
We did whatever it took to get
A to become R.
And at the same time,
we were doing it to the
identity matrix.
So we started with the identity
matrix, we buzzed along.
So we took some -- all this row
reduction amounted to
multiplying on the left by some
matrix, some series of
elementary matrices that
altogether gave us one matrix,
and that matrix is E.
So all this row reduction stuff
amounted to multiplying by E.
How do I know that?
It certainly amounted to
multiply it by something.
And that something took I to E,
so that something was E.
So now look at the first part,
E A is R.
No big deal.
All I've said is that the row
reduction steps that we all know
--
well, taking A to R,
are in a, in some matrix,
and I can find out what that
matrix is by just tacking I on
and seeing what comes out.
What comes out is E.
Let's just review the
invertible square case.
What happened then?
Because I was interested in it
in chapter two also.
When A was square and
invertible, I took A I,
I did row, row elimination.
And what was the R that came
out?
It was I.
So in chapter two,
in chapter two,
R was I.
The row the,
the reduced row echelon form of
a nice invertible square matrix
is the identity.
So if R was I in that case,
then E was -- then E was A
inverse, because E A is I.
Good.
That's, that was good and easy.
Now what I'm saying is that
there still is an E.
It's not A inverse any more,
because A is rectangular.
It hasn't got an inverse.
But there is still some matrix
E that connected this to this --
oh, I should have figured out in
advanced what it was.
Shoot.
I didn't -- I did those steps
and sort of erased as I went --
and, I should have done them to
the identity too.
Can I do that?
I'll keep the identity matrix,
like I'm supposed to do,
and I'll do the same operations
on it, and see what I end up
with.
OK.
So I'm starting with the
identity --
which I'll write in light,
light enough,
but -- OK.
What did I do?
I subtracted that row from that
one and that row from that one.
OK, I'll do that to the
identity.
So I subtract that first row
from row two and row three.
Good.
Then I think I multiplied --
Do you remember?
I multiplied row two by minus
one.
Let me just do that.
Then what did I do?
I subtracted two of row two
away from row one.
I better do that.
Subtract two of this away from
this.
That's minus one,
two of these away leaves a plus
2 and 0.
I believe that's E.
The way to check is to see,
multiply that E by this A,
just to see did I do it right.
So I believe E was -1 2 0,
1 -1 0, and -1 0 1.
OK.
That's my E,
that's my A,
and that's R.
All right.
All I'm struggling to do is
right, the reason I wanted this
blasted E was so that I could
figure out the left null space,
not only its dimension,
which I know -- actually,
what is the dimension of the
left null space?
So here's my matrix.
What's the rank of the matrix?
And the dimension of the null
-- of the left null space is
supposed to be m-r.
It's 3 -2, 1.
I believe that the left null
space is one dimensional.
There is one combination of
those three rows that produces
the zero row.
There's a basis -- a basis for
the left null space has only got
one vector in it.
And what is that vector?
It's here in the last row of E.
But we could have seen it
earlier.
What combination of those rows
gives the zero row?
-1 of that plus one of that.
So a basis for the left null
space of this matrix -- I'm
looking for combinations of rows
that give the zero row if I'm
looking at the left null space.
For the null space,
I'm looking at combinations of
columns to get the zero column.
Now I'm looking at combinations
of these three rows to get the
zero row, and of course there is
my zero row, and here is my
vector that produced it.
-1 of that row and one of that
row.
Obvious.
OK.
So in that example --
and actually in all examples,
we have seen how to produce a
basis for the left null space.
I won't ask you that all the
time, because -- it didn't come
out immediately from R.
We had to keep track of E for
that left null space.
But at least it didn't require
us to transpose the matrix and
start all over again.
OK, those are the four
subspaces.
Can I review them?
The row space and the null
space are in R^n.
Their dimensions add to n.
The column space and the left
null space are in R^m,
and their dimensions add to m.
OK.
So let me close these last
minutes by pushing you a little
bit more to a new type of vector
space.
All our vector spaces,
all the ones that we took
seriously, have been subspaces
of some real three or n
dimensional space.
Now I'm going to write down
another vector space,
a new vector space.
Say all three by three
matrices.
My matrices are the vectors.
Is that all right?
I'm just naming them.
You can put quotes around
vectors.
Every three by three matrix is
one of my vectors.
Now how I entitled to call
those things vectors?
I mean, they look very much
like matrices.
But they are vectors in my
vector space because they obey
the rules.
All I'm supposed to be able to
do with vectors is add them -- I
can add matrices -- I'm supposed
to be able to multiply them by
scalar numbers like seven --
well, I can multiply a matrix by
And that --
and I can take combinations of
matrices, I can take three of
one matrix minus five of another
matrix.
And those combinations,
there's a zero matrix,
the matrix that has all zeros
in it.
If I add that to another
matrix, it doesn't change it.
All the good stuff.
If I multiply a matrix by one
it doesn't change it.
All those eight rules for a
vector space that we never wrote
down, all easily satisfied.
So now we have a different --
now of course you can say you
can multiply those matrices.
I don't care.
For the moment,
I'm only thinking of these
matrices as forming a vector
space --
so I only doing A plus B and c
times A.
I'm not interested in A B for
now.
The fact that I can multiply is
not relevant to th- to a vector
space.
OK.
So I have three by three
matrices.
And how about subspaces?
What's -- tell me a subspace of
this matrix space.
Let me call this matrix space
M.
That's my matrix space,
my space of all three by three
matrices.
Tell me a subspace of it.
OK.
What about the upper triangular
matrices?
So subspaces.
Subspaces of M.
All, all upper triangular
matrices.
Another subspace.
All symmetric matrices.
The intersection of two
subspaces is supposed to be a
subspace.
We gave a little effort to the
proof of that fact.
If I look at the matrices that
are in this subspace --
they're symmetric,
and they're also in this
subspace, they're upper
triangular, what do they look
like?
Well, if they're symmetric but
they have zeros below the
diagonal, they better have zeros
above the diagonal,
so the intersection would be
diagonal matrices.
That's another subspace,
smaller than those.
How can I use the word smaller?
Well, I'm now entitled to use
the word smaller.
I mean, well,
one way to say is,
OK, these are contained in
those.
These are contained in those.
But more precisely,
I could give the dimension of
these spaces.
So I could -- we can compute --
let's compute it next time,
the dimension of all upper --
of the subspace of upper
triangular three by three
matrices.
The dimension of symmetric
three by three matrices.
The dimension of diagonal three
by three matrices.
Well, to produce dimension,
that means I'm supposed to
produce a basis,
and then I just count how many
vecto- how many I needed in the
basis.
Let me give you the answer for
this one.
What's the dimension?
The dimension of this --
say, this subspace,
let me call it D,
all diagonal matrices.
The dimension of this subspace
is -- as I write you're working
it out -- three.
Because here's a matrix in this
-- it's a diagonal matrix.
Here's another one.
Better make it diagonal,
let me put a seven there.
That was not a very great
choice, but it's three diagonal
matrices, and I believe that
they're a basis.
I believe that those three
matrices are independent and I
believe that any diagonal matrix
is a combination of those three.
So they span the subspace of
diagonal matrices.
Do you see that idea?
It's like stretching the idea
from R^n to R^(n by n),
three by three.
But the -- we can still add,
we can still multiply by
numbers, and we just ignore the
fact that we can multiply two
matrices together.
OK, thank you.
That's lecture ten.