OK, this is the second lecture
on determinants.
There are only three.
With determinants it's a
fascinating, small topic inside
linear algebra.
Used to be determinants were
the big thing,
and linear algebra was the
little thing,
but they --
those changed,
that situation changed.
Now determinants is one
specific part,
very neat little part.
And my goal today is to find a
formula for the determinant.
It'll be a messy formula.
So that's why you didn't see it
right away.
But if I'm given this n by n
matrix
then I use those entries to
create this number,
the determinant.
So there's a formula for it.
In fact, there's another
formula, a second formula using
something called cofactors.
So you'll -- you have to know
what cofactors are.
And then I'll apply those
formulas for some,
some matrices that have a
lot of zeros away from the
three diagonals.
OK.
So I'm shooting now for a
formula for the determinant.
You remember we started with
these three properties,
three simple properties,
but out of that we got all
these amazing facts,
like the determinant of A B
equals determinant of A times
determinant of B.
But the three facts were -- oh,
how about I just take two by
twos.
I know, because everybody here
knows, the determinant of a two
by two matrix,
but let's get it out of
these three formulas.
OK, so here's my,
my two by two matrix.
I'm looking for a formula for
this determinant.
a b c d, OK.
So property one,
I know what to do with the
identity.
Right?
Property two allows me to
exchange
rows, and I know what to do
then.
So I know that that determinant
is one.
Property two allows me to
exchange rows and know that this
determinant is minus one.
And now I want to use property
three to get everybody,
to get everybody.
And how will I do that?
OK.
So remember that if I keep the
second row the same,
I'm allowed to use linearity in
the first row.
And I'll just use it in a
simple way.
I'll write this vector a b as a
0 + 0 b.
So that's one step using
property three,
linearity in the first row
when the second row's the same.
OK.
But now you can guess what I'm
going to do next.
I'll -- because I'd like to --
if I can make the matrices
diagonal, then I'm clearly
there.
So I'll take this one.
Now I'll keep the first row
fixed and split the second row,
so that'll be an a 0 and I'll
split that into a c 0 and,
keeping that first row the
same, a 0 d.
I used, for this part,
linearity.
And now I'll -- whoops,
that's plus because I've got
more coming.
This one I'll do the same.
I'll keep this first row the
same
and I'll split c d into c 0 and
0 d.
OK.
Now I've got four easy
determinants,
and two of them are -- well,
all four are extremely easy.
Two of them are so easy as to
turn into zero,
right?
Which two of these determinants
are zero right away?
The first guy is zero.
Why is he zero?
Why is that determinant
nothing, forget him?
Well, it has a column of zeros.
And by the -- well,
so one way to think is,
well, it's a singular matrix.
Oh, for, for like forty-eight
different reasons,
that
determinant is zero.
It's a singular matrix that has
a column of zeros.
It's, it's dead.
And this one is about as dead
too.
Column of zeros.
OK.
So that's leaving us with this
one.
Now what do I -- how do I know
its determinant,
following the rules?
Well, I guess one of the
properties that we actually got
to was the determinant of that
-- diagonal matrix,
then -- so I,
I'm finally getting to that
determinant is the a d.
And this determinant is what?
What's this one?
Minus -- because I would use
property two to do a flip to
make it c b, then property three
to factor out the b,
property c to factor out the c
-- the property again to factor
out the c, and that minus,
and of course finally I got the
answer that we knew we would
get.
But you see the method.
You see the method,
because it's method I'm looking
for here, not just a two by two
answer but the method of doing
-- now I can do three by threes
and four by fours and any size.
So if you can see the method of
taking each row at a time -- so
let's -- what would happen with
three by threes?
Can we mentally do it rather
than I write everything on the
board for three by threes?
So what would we do if I had
three by threes?
I would keep rows two and three
the same and I would split the
first row into how many pieces?
Three pieces.
I'd have an A zero zero and a
zero B
zero and a zero zero C or
something for the first row.
So I would instead of going
from one piece to two pieces to
four pieces, I would go from one
piece to three pieces to -- what
would it be?
Each of those three,
would, would it be nine?
Or twenty-seven?
Oh yeah, I've actually
got more steps,
right.
I'd go to nine but then I'd
have another row to straighten
out, twenty-seven.
Yes, oh God.
OK, let me say this again then.
If I -- if it was three by
three, I would -- separating out
one row into three pieces would
give me three,
separating out the second row
into three pieces,
then I'd be up to nine,
separating out the third row
into its three pieces,
I'd be up to twenty-seven,
three cubed,
pieces.
But a lot of them would be
zero.
So now when would they not be
zero?
Tell me the pieces that would
not be zero.
Now I will write the non-zero
ones.
OK, so I have this matrix.
I think I have to use these,
start using these double
symbols here because otherwise I
could never do n by n.
OK.
So I split this up like crazy.
A bunch of pieces are zero.
Whenever I have a column of
zeros, I know I've got zero.
When do I not have zero?
When do I have -- what is it
that's like these guys?
These are the survivors,
two survivors there.
So my question for three by
three is going to be what are
the survivors?
How many survivors are there?
What are they?
And when do I get a survivor.
Well, I would get a survivor --
for example, one survivor will
be that one times that one times
that one, with all zeros
everywhere else.
That would be one survivor.
a one one zero zero zero a two
two zero zero zero a three
three.
That's like the a d survivor.
Tell me another survivor.
What other thing -- oh,
now here you see the clue.
Now can -- shall I just say the
whole clue?
That I'm having -- the
survivors have one entry from
each row and each column.
One entry from each row and
column.
Because if some column is
missing,
then I get a singular matrix.
And that, that's one of these
guys.
See, you see what happened with
-- this guy?
Column one never got used in 0
b 0 d.
So its determinant was zero and
I forget it.
So I'm going to forget those
and
just put -- so tell me one more
that would be a survivor?
Well -- well,
here's another one.
a one one zero zero -- now OK,
that's used up row -- row one
is used.
Column one is already used so
it better be zero.
What else could I have?
Where could I pick the guy --
which column shall I use in row
two?
Use column three,
because here if I use column --
here I used column one and row
one.
This was like the column --
numbers were one two three,
right in order.
Now the column numbers are
going to
be one three,
column three,
and column two.
So the row numbers are one two
three, of course.
The column numbers are some --
OK, some permutation of one two
three, and here they come in the
order one three two.
It's just like having a
permutation matrix with,
instead of the ones,
with numbers.
And actually,
it's very close to having a
permutation matrix,
because I, what I do eventually
is I factor out these numbers
and then I have got.
So what is that determinant
equal?
I factor those numbers out and
I've
got a one one times a two two
times a three three.
And what does this determinant
equal?
Yeah, now tell me the,
this -- I mean,
we're really getting to the
heart of these formulas now.
What is that determinant?
By the laws of -- by,
by our three properties,
I can factor these out,
I can factor out the a one one,
the a two three,
and the a three two.
They're in separate rows.
I can do each row separately.
And then I just have to decide
is that plus sign or is that a
minus sign?
And the answer is it's a minus.
Why minus?
Because these is one row
exchange to get it back to the
identity.
So that's a minus.
Now I through?
No, because there are other
ways.
What I'm really through with,
what I've done,
what I've, what I've completed
is only the part where the a one
one is there.
But now I've got parts
where it's a one two.
And now if it's a one two that
row is used, that column is
used.
You see that idea?
I could use this row and
column.
Now that column is used,
that column is used,
and this guy has to be here,
a three three.
And what's that determinant?
That's an a one two times an a
two one times an a three three,
and does it have a plus or a
minus?
A minus is right.
It has a minus.
Because it's one flip away from
an id- from the,
regular, the right order,
the diagonal order.
And now what's the other guy
with a --
with, a one two up there?
I could have used this row.
I could have put this guy here
and this guy here.
Right?
You see the whole deal?
Now that's an a one two,
a two three,
a three one,
and does that go with a plus or
a minus?
Yeah, now that takes a minute
of thinking, doesn't it,
because one row exchange
doesn't get it in line.
So what is the answer for this?
Plus or minus?
Plus, because it takes two
exchanges.
I could exchange rows one and
three and then two and three.
Two exchanges makes this thing
a plus.
OK.
And then finally we have --
we're going to have two more.
Zero zero a one three,
a two one zero zero,
zero a three two zero.
And one more guy.
Zero zero a one three,
zero a two two zero,
A three one zero zero.
And let's put down what we get
from those.
An a one three,
an a two one,
and an a three two,
and I think that one is a plus.
And this guys is a minus
because one exchange would put
it -- would order it.
And that's a minus.
All right, that has taken one
whole board just to do the three
by three.
But do you agree that we now
have a formula for the
determinant which came from the
three properties?
And it must be it.
And I'm going to keep that
formula.
That's a famous --
that three by three formula is
one that if, if the cameras will
follow me back to the beginning
here, I, I get the ones with the
plus sign are the ones that go
down like down this way.
And the ones with the minus
signs are sort of the ones that
go this way.
I won't make that precise.
For two reasons,
one, it would clutter up the
board, and second reason,
it wouldn't be right for four
by fours.
For four by four,
let me just say right away,
four by four matrix -- the,
the cross diagonal,
the wrong diagonal happens to
come out with a plus sign.
Why is that?
If I have a four by four matrix
with ones coming on the counter
diagonal, that determinant is
plus.
Why?
Why plus for that guy?
Because if I exchange rows one
and four and then I exchange
rows two and three,
I've got the identity,
and I did two exchanges.
So this down to this,
like, you know,
down toward Miami and down
toward LA stuff is,
like, three by three only.
OK.
But I do want to get now -- I
don't want to go through this
for a four by four.
I do want to get now
the general formula.
So this is what I refer to in
the book as the big formula.
So now this is the big formula
for the determinant.
I'm asking you to make a jump
from two by two and three by
three to n by n.
OK, so this will be the big
formula.
That the determinant of A is
the sum
of a whole lot of terms.
And what are those terms?
And, and is it a plus or a
minus sign, and I have to tell
you which, which it is,
because this came in -- in the
three by three case,
I had how many terms?
Six.
And half were plus and half
were minus.
How many terms are you figuring
for four by four?
If I get two terms in the two
by two case, three -- six terms
in the three by three case,
what's that pattern?
How many terms in the four by
four case?
Twenty-four.
Four factorial.
Why four factorial?
This will be a sum of n
factorial terms.
Twenty-four,
a hundred and twenty,
seven hundred and twenty,
whatever's after that.
OK.
Half plus and half minus.
And where do those n factorial
--
terms come from?
This is the moment to listen to
this lecture.
Where do those n factorial
terms come from?
They come because the first,
the guy in the first row can be
chosen n ways.
And after he's chosen,
that's used up that,
that column.
So the one in the second row
can be chosen n minus one ways.
And after she's chosen,
that second column has been
used.
And then the one in the third
row can be chosen n minus two
ways, and after it's chosen --
notice how I'm getting these
personal pronouns.
But I've run out.
And I'm not willing to stop
with three by three,
so I'm just going to write the
formula down.
So the one in the first row
comes from some column alpha.
I don't know what alpha is.
And the one in the -- I
multiply that by somebody in the
second row that comes from some
different column.
And I multiply that by somebody
in the third row who comes from
some yet different column.
And then in the n-th row,
I don't know what -- I don't
know how to draw.
Maybe omega,
for last.
And the whole point is then
that -- that those column
numbers are different,
that alpha, beta,
gamma, omega,
that set of column numbers is
some permutation,
permutation of one to n.
It, it, the n column numbers
are each used once.
And that gives us n factorial
terms.
And when I choose a term,
that means I'm choosing
somebody
from every row and column.
And then I just -- like the way
I had this from row and column
one, row and column two,
row and column three,
so that -- what was the alpha
beta stuff in that,
for that term here?
Alpha was one,
beta was two,
gamma was three.
The permutation was,
was the trivial permutation,
one two three,
everybody in the right order.
You see that formula?
It's -- do you see why I didn't
want to start with that the
first day, Friday?
I'd rather we understood the
properties.
Because out of this formula,
presumably I could figure out
all these properties.
How would I know that the
determinant of the identity
matrix was one,
for example,
out of this formula?
Why is -- if A is the identity
matrix, how does this formula
give me a plus one?
You see it, right?
Because, because almost all the
terms are zeros.
Which term isn't zero,
if, if A is the identity
matrix?
Almost all the terms are zero
because almost all the As are
zero.
It's only, the only time I'll
get something is if it's a one
one times a two two times a
three three.
Only, only the,
only the permutation that's in
the right order will,
will give me something.
It'll come with a plus sign.
And the determinant of the
identity is one.
So, so we could go back from
this formula and prove
everything.
We could even try to prove that
the
determinant of A B was the
determinant of A times the
determinant of B.
But like next week we would
still be working on it,
because it's not -- clear from
-- if I took A B,
my God.
You know --.
The entries of A B would
be all these pieces.
Well, probably,
it's probably -- historically
it's been done,
but it won't be repeated in
eighteen oh six.
OK.
It would be possible probably
to see, why the determinant of A
equals the
determinant of A transpose.
That was another,
like, miracle property at the
end.
That would, that would,
that's an easier one,
which we could find.
OK.
Is that all right for the big
formula?
I could take you then a,
a typical -- let me do an
example.
Which I'll just create.
I'll take a four by four
matrix.
I'll put some,
I'll put some ones in and some
zeros in.
OK.
Let me -- I don't know how many
to
put in, to tell the truth.
I've never done this before.
I don't know the determinant of
that matrix.
So like mathematics is being
done for the first time in,
in front of your eyes.
What's the determinant?
Well, a lot of -- there are
twenty-four terms,
because it's four by four.
Many of them will be zero,
because I've got all those
zeros there.
Maybe the whole determinant is
zero.
I mean, I -- is that a singular
matrix?
That possibility definitely
exists.
I could, I could,
So one way to do it would be
elimination.
Actually, that would probably
be a fairly reasonable way.
I could use elimination,
so I could use -- go back to
those properties,
that -- and use elimination,
get down, eliminate it down,
do I have a row of zeros at the
end of elimination?
The answer is zero.
I was thinking,
shall I try this big formula?
OK.
Let's try the big formula.
How -- tell me one way I can go
down the matrix,
taking a one,
taking a one from
every row and column,
and make it to the end?
So it's -- I get something that
isn't zero.
Well, one way to do it,
I could take that times that
times that times that times
that.
That would be one and,
and, and I just said,
that comes in with what sign?
Plus.
That comes with a plus sign.
Because, because that
permutation -- I've just written
the permutation about four three
two one, and one exchange and a
second exchange,
two exchanges puts it in the
correct order.
Keep walking away,
don't....
OK, we're executing a
determinant
formula here.
Uh as long as it's not
periodic, of course.
If he comes back I'm in -- no.
All right, all right.
OK, so that would give me a
plus one.
All right.
Are there any others?
Well, of course we see
another one here.
This times this times this
times this strikes us right
away.
So that's the order three,
the order -- let me make a
little different mark here.
Three two one four.
And is that a plus or a minus,
three two one four?
Is that, is that permutation a
plus
or a minus permutation?
It's a minus.
How do you see that?
What exchange shall I do to get
it in the right order?
If I exchange the one and the
three I'm in the right orders,
took one exchange to do it,
so that would be a plus -- that
would be a minus one.
And now I don't know if
there're any more here.
Let's see.
Let me try again starting with
this.
Now I've got to pick somebody
from -- oh yeah,
see, you see what's happening.
If I I start there,
OK, column three is used.
So then when I go to next row,
I can't use that,
I must use that.
Now columns two and three are
used.
When I come to this row I must
use that.
And then I must use that.
So if I start there,
this is the only one I get.
And similarly,
if I start there,
that's the only one I get.
So what's the determinant?
What's the determinant?
Zero.
The determinant is zero for
that case.
Because we, we were able to
check the
twenty-four terms.
Twenty-two of them were zero.
One of them was plus one.
One of them was minus one.
Add up the twenty-four terms,
zero is the answer.
OK.
Well, I didn't know it would be
zero, I -- because I wasn't,
like, thinking ahead.
I was a little scared,
actually.
I said, that,
apparition went by.
So and I don't know if the
camera caught that.
So whether the rest of the
world will realize that I was in
danger or not,
we don't know.
But anyway, I guess he just
wanted to be sure
that we got the right answer,
which is determinant zero.
And then that makes me think,
OK, the matrix must be,
the matrix must be singular.
And then if the matrix is
singular, maybe there's another
way to see that it's singular,
like find something in its null
space.
Or find a combination of the
rows that gives zero.
And like what d- what,
what combination of those rows
does give zero.
Suppose I add rows one and rows
three.
If I add rows one and rows
three, what do I get?
I get a row of all ones.
Then if I add rows two and rows
four I get a row of all ones.
So row one minus row two plus
row three minus row four is
probably the zero row.
It's a singular matrix.
And I could find something in
its null space the same way.
That would be a combination of
columns that gives zero.
OK, there's an example.
All right.
So that's, well,
that shows two things.
That shows how we get the
twenty-four terms and it shows
the great advantage of having a
lot of zeros in there.
OK.
So we'll use this big formula,
but I want to pick -- I want to
go onward now to cofactors.
Onward to cofactors.
Cofactors is a way of breaking
up this big formula that
connects this n by n -- this is
an n by n determinant that we've
just have a formula for,
the big formula.
So cofactors is a way to
connect this n by n determinant
to,
determinants one smaller.
One smaller.
And the way we want to do it is
actually going to show up in
this.
Since the three by three is the
one that we wrote out in full,
let's, let me do this three by
-- so I'm talking about
cofactors, and I'm going to
start again with three by three.
And I'm going to take the,
the exact formula,
and I'm just going to write it
as a one one -- this is the
determinant I'm writing.
I'm just going to say a one one
times what?
A one one times what?
And it's a one one times a two
two a three three minus a two
three a three two.
Then I've got the a one two
stuff times something.
And I've got the a one three
Do you see what I'm doing?
I'm taking our big formula and
I'm saying, OK,
choose column -- out of the
first row,
choose column one.
And take all the possibilities.
And those extra factors will be
what we'll call the cofactor,
co meaning going with a one
one.
So this in parenthesis are,
these are in,
the cofactors are in parens.
A one one times something.
And I figured out what that
something was by just looking
back -- if I can walk back here
to the, to the a one one,
the one that comes down the
diagonal minus the one that
comes that way.
That's, those are the two,
only two that used a one one.
So there they are,
one with a plus and one with a
minus.
And now I can write in the --
I could look back and see what
used a one two and I can see
what used a one three,
and those will give me the
cofactors of a one two and a one
three.
Before I do that,
what's this number,
what is this cofactor?
What is it there that's
multiplying a one one?
Tell me what a two two a three
three minus a two three a three
two is, for this -- do you
recognize that?
Do you recognize -- let's see,
I can -- and I'll put it here.
There's the a one one.
That's used column one.
Then there's --
the other factors involved
these other columns.
This row is used.
This column is used.
So this the only things left to
use are these.
And this formula uses them,
and what's the,
what's the cofactor?
Tell me what it is because you
see it, and then --
I'll be happy you see what the
idea of cofactors.
It's the determinant of this
smaller guy.
A one one multiplies the
determinant of this smaller guy.
That gives me all the a one one
part of the big formula.
You see that?
This, the determinant of this
smaller guy is a two two a
three three minus a two three a
three two.
In other words,
once I've used column one and
row one, what's left is all the
ways to use the other n-1
columns and n-1 rows,
one of each.
All the other -- and that's the
determinant of the smaller guy
of size n-1.
So that's the whole idea of
cofactors.
And we just have to remember
that with determinants we've got
pluses and minus signs to keep
straight.
Can we keep this next one
straight?
Let's do the next one.
OK, the next one will be when I
use a one two.
I'll have left --
so I can't use that column any
more, but I can use a two one
and a two three and I can use a
three one and a three three.
So this one gave me a one times
that determinant.
This will give me a one two
times this determinant,
a two one a three three minus a
two three a three one.
So that's all the stuff
involving a one two.
But have I got the sign right?
Is the determinant of that
correctly given by that or is
there a minus sign?
There is a minus sign.
I can follow one of these.
If I do that times that times
that, that was one that's
showing up
here, but it should have showed
-- it should have been a minus.
So I'm going to build that
minus sign into the cofactor.
So, so the cofactor -- so I'll
put, put that minus sign in
here.
So because the cofactor is
going to be strictly the thing
that multiplies the,
the factor.
The factor is a one two,
the cofactor is this,
is the parens,
the stuff in parentheses.
So it's got the minus sign
built in.
And if I did -- if I went on to
the third guy,
there w- there'll be this and
this, this and this.
And it would take its
determinant.
It would come out plus
the determinant.
So now I'm ready to say what
cofactors are.
So this would be a plus and a
one three times its cofactor.
And over here we had plus a one
one times this determinant.
But and there we had the a one
two times its cofactor,
but the -- so the point is the
cofactor is either plus or
minus the determinant.
So let me write that underneath
them.
What is the,
what are cofactors?
The cofactor if any number aij,
let's say.
This is, this is all the terms
in the,
in the big formula that involve
aij.
We're especially interested in
a1j, the first row,
that's what I've been talking
about, but any row would be all
right.
All right, so -- what terms
involve aij?
So --
it's the determinant of the n
minus one matrix -- with row i,
column j erased.
So it's the,
it's a matrix of size n-1 with
-- of course,
because I can't use this row or
this column again.
So I have the matrix all there.
But now it's multiplied
by a plus or a minus.
This is the cofactor,
and I'm going to call that cij.
Capital, I use capital c just
to, just to emphasize that these
are important and emphasize that
they're, they're,
they're different from the
(a)s.
OK.
So now is it a plus
or is it a minus?
Because we see that in this
case, for a one one it was a
plus, for a one two I -- this is
ij -- it was a minus.
For this ij it was a plus.
So any any guess on the rule
for plus or minus when we see
those examples,
ij equal one one or one three
was a plus?
It sounds very like i+j odd or
even.
That, that's doesn't surprise
us, and that's the right answer.
So it's a plus if i+j is even
and it's a minus if i+j is odd.
So if I go along row one and
look at the cofactors,
I just take those determinants,
those one smaller determinants,
and
they come in order plus minus
plus minus plus minus.
But if I go along row two and,
and, and take the cofactors of
sub-determinants,
they would start with a minus,
because the two one entry,
two plus one is odd,
so the -- like there's a
pattern plus minus plus minus
plus if it was five by
five, but then if I was doing a
cofactor then this sign would be
minus plus minus plus minus,
plus minus plus -- it's sort of
checkerboard.
OK.
Those are the signs that,
that are given by this rule,
i+j even or odd.
And those are built
into the cofactors.
The thing is called a minor
without th- before you've built
in the sign, but I don't care
about those.
Build in that sign and call it
a cofactor.
OK.
So what's the cofactor formula?
What's the cofactor formula
then?
Let me come back to this board
and
say, what's the cofactor
formula?
Determinant of A is -- let's go
along the first row.
It's a one one times its
cofactor, and then the second
guy is a one two times its
cofactor, and you just keep
going to the end of the row,
a1n times its cofactor.
So that's cofactor for --
along row one.
And if I went along row I,
I would -- those ones would be
Is.
That's worth putting a box
over.
That's the cofactor formula.
Do you see that -- actually,
this would give me another way
I could have started the whole
topic of determinants.
And some, some people might do
it
this -- choose to do it this
way.
Because the cofactor formula
would allow me to build up an n
by n determinant out of n-1
sized determinants,
build those out of n-2,
and so on.
I could boil all the way down
to one by ones.
So what's the cofactor formula
for
two by two matrices?
Yeah, tell me that.
What's the cofactor for us?
Here is the,
here is the world's smallest
example, practically,
of a cofactor formula.
OK.
Let's go along row one.
I take this first guy
times its cofactor.
What's the cofactor of the one
one entry?
d, because you strike out the
one one row and column and
you're left with d.
Then I take this guy,
b, times its cofactor.
What's the cofactor of b?
Is it c or it's --
minus c, because I strike out
this guy, I take that
determinant, and then I follow
the i+j rule and I get a minus,
I get an odd.
So it's b times minus c.
OK, it worked.
Of course it,
it worked.
And the three by three works.
So that's the cofactor formula,
and that is,
that's an -- that's a good
formula to know,
and now I'm feeling like,
wow, I'm giving you a lot of
algebra to swallow here.
Last lecture gave you ten
properties.
Now I'm giving you -- and by
the way, those ten
properties led us to a formula
for the determinant which was
very important,
and I haven't repeated it till
now.
What was that?
The, the determinant is the
product of the pivots.
So the pivot formula is,
is very important.
The pivots have all this
complicated
mess already built in.
As you did elimination to get
the pivots, you built in all
this horrible stuff,
quite efficiently.
Then the big formula with the n
factorial terms,
that's got all the horrible
stuff spread out.
And the cofactor formula is
like in between.
It's got easy stuff times
horrible stuff,
basically.
But it's, it shows you,
how to get determinants from
smaller determinants,
and that's the application that
I now want to make.
So may I do one more example?
So I remember the general idea.
But I'm going to use this
cofactor
formula for a matrix -- so here
is going to be my example.
It's -- I promised in the,
in the lecture,
outline at the very beginning
to do an example.
And let me do -- I'm going to
pick tri-diagonal matrix of
ones.
I could, I'm drawing here the
four by four.
So this will be the matrix.
I could call that A4.
But my real idea is to do n by
n.
To do them all.
So A -- I could -- everybody
understands what A1 and A2 are.
Yeah.
Maybe we should just do A1 and
A2 and A3 just for -- so this is
A4.
What's the determinant of A1?
So, so what's the matrix A1 in
this formula?
It's just got that.
So the determinant is one.
What's the determinant of A2?
So it's just got this two by
two,
and its determinant is -- zero.
And then the three by three.
Can we see its determinant?
Can you take the determinant of
that three by three?
Well, that's not quite so
obvious, at least not to me.
Being three by three,
I don't know -- so here's a,
here's a good example.
How would you do that three by
three determinant?
We've got, like,
n factorial different ways.
Well, three factorial.
So we've got six ways.
OK.
I mean, one way to do it --
actually the way I would
probably do it,
being three by three,
I would use the complete the
big formula.
I would say,
I've got a one from that,
I've got a zero from that,
a zero from that,
and this direction is a minus
one,
that direction's a minus one.
I believe the answer is minus
one.
Would you do it another way?
Here's another way to do it,
look.
Subtract row three from -- I'm
just looking at this three by
three.
Everybody's looking at the
three by three.
Subtract row three from row
two.
Determinant doesn't change.
So those become zeros.
OK, now use the cofactor
formula.
How's that?
How can, how -- if this was now
zeros and I'm looking at this
three by three,
use the cofactor formula.
Why not use the cofactor
formula along that row?
Because then I take that number
times its cofactor,
so I take this number -- let me
put a box around it -- times its
cofactor, which is the
determinant of that and that,
which is what?
That two by two matrix has
determinant one.
So what's the cofactor?
What's the cofactor of this guy
here?
Looking just at this three by
three.
The cofactor of that one is
this determinant,
which is one times negative.
So that's why the answer came
out minus one.
OK.
So I did the three by three.
I don't know if we want to try
the four by four.
Yeah, let's -- I guess that was
the point of my example,
of course, so I have to try it.
Sorry, I'm in a good mood
today, so you have to stand for
all the bad jokes.
OK.
So what was the matrix?
Ah.
OK, now I'm ready for four by
four.
Who wants to -- who wants to
guess the, the -- I don't know,
frankly, this four by four,
what's, what's the determinant.
I plan to use cofactors.
OK, let's use cofactors.
The determinant of A4 is -- OK,
let's use cofactors on the
first row.
Those are easy.
So I multiply this number,
which is a convenient one,
times this determinant.
So it's, it's one times the,
this three by three
determinant.
Now what is -- do you recognize
that matrix?
It's A3.
So it's one times the
determinant of A3.
Coming along this row is a one
times this determinant,
and it goes with a plus,
right?
And then we have this one.
And what is its cofactor?
Now I'm looking at,
now I'm looking at this three
by three, this three by three,
so I'm looking at the three by
three that I haven't X-ed out.
What is that -- oh,
now it, we did a plus or a --
is it plus this determinant,
this three by three
determinant, or minus it?
It's minus it,
right, because this is -- I'm
starting in a one two position,
and that's a minus.
So I want minus this
determinant.
But these guys are X-ed out.
OK.
So I've got a three by three.
Well, let's use cofactors
again.
Use cofactors of the column,
because actually we could use
cofactors of columns just as
well as rows,
because, because the transpose
rule.
So I'll take this one,
which is now sitting in the
plus position,
times its determinant -- oh!
Oh, hell.
What -- oh yeah,
I shouldn't have said hell,
because it's all right.
OK.
One times the determinant.
What is that matrix now that
I'm taking the,
this smaller one of?
Oh, but there's a minus,
right?
The minus came from,
from the fact that this was in
the one two position and that's
odd.
So this is a minus one times --
and what's -- and then this one
is the upper left,
that's the one one position in
its matrix, so plus.
And what's this matrix here?
Do you recognize that?
That matrix is -- yes,
please say it -- A2.
And we -- that's our formula
for any case.
A of any size n is equal to the
determinant of A n minus one,
that's what came from taking
the one in the upper corner,
the first cofactor,
minus the determinant of A n
minus two.
What we discovered there is
true for all n.
I didn't even mention it,
but I stopped taking cofactors
when I got this one.
Why did I stop?
Why didn't I take the cofactor
of this guy?
Because he's going to get
multiplied by zero,
and no, no use wasting time.
Or this one too.
The cofactor,
her cofactor will be whatever
that determinant is,
but it'll be multiplied by
zero, so I won't bother.
OK, there is the formula.
And that now tells us -- I
could figure out what A4 is now.
Oh yeah, finally I can get A4.
Because it's A3,
which is minus one,
minus A2, which is zero,
so it's minus one.
You see how we're getting kind
of numbers that you might not
have guessed.
So our sequence right now is
one zero minus one minus one.
What's the next one in the
sequence, A5?
A5 is this minus this,
so it is zero.
What's A6?
A6 is this minus this,
which is one.
What's A7?
I'm, I'm going to be stopped by
either the time runs out or the
board runs out.
OK, A7 is this minus this,
which is one.
I'll stop here,
because time is out,
but let me tell you what we've
got.
What -- these determinants have
this series, one zero minus one
minus one zero one,
and then it starts repeating.
It's pretty fantastic.
These determinants have period
six.
So the determinant of A
sixty-one
would be the determinant of A1,
which would be one.
OK.
I hope you liked that example.
A non-trivial example of a
tri-diagonal determinant.
Thanks.
See you on Wednesday.