OK.
This is lecture twelve.
We've reached twelve lectures.
And this one is more than the
others about applications of
linear algebra.
And I'll confess.
When I'm giving you examples of
the null space and the row
space, I create a little matrix.
You probably see that I just
invent that matrix as I'm going.
And I feel a little guilty
about it, because the truth is
that real linear algebra uses
matrices that come from
somewhere.
They're not just,
like, randomly invented by the
instructor.
They come from applications.
They have a definite structure.
And anybody who works with them
gets, uses that structure.
I'll just report,
like, this weekend I was at an
event with chemistry professors.
OK, those guys are row reducing
matrices, and what matrices are
they working with?
Well, their little matrices
tell them how much of each
element goes into the -- or each
molecule, how many molecules of
each go into a reaction and what
comes out.
And by row reduction they get a
clearer picture of a complicated
reaction.
And this weekend I'm going to
-- to a sort of birthday party
at Mathworks.
So Mathworks is out Route 9 in
Natick.
That's where Matlab is created.
It's a very,
very successful,
software, tremendously
successful.
And the conference will be
about how linear algebra is
used.
And so I feel better today to
talk about what I think is the
most important model in applied
math.
And the discrete version is a
graph.
So can I draw a graph?
Write down the matrix that's
associated with it,
and that's a great source of
matrices.
You'll see.
So a graph is just,
so a graph -- to repeat -- has
nodes and edges.
OK.
And I'm going to write down the
graph, a graph,
so I'm just creating a small
graph here.
As I mentioned last time,
we would be very interested in
the graph of all,
websites.
Or the graph of all telephones.
I mean -- or the graph of all
people in the world.
Here let me take just,
maybe nodes one two three --
well, I better put in an -- I'll
put in that edge and maybe an
edge to, to a node four,
and another edge to node four.
How's that?
So there's a graph with four
nodes.
So n will be four in my -- n
equal four nodes.
And the matrix will have m
equal the number -- there'll be
a row for every edge,
so I've got one two three four
five edges.
So that will be the number of
rows.
And I have to to write down the
matrix that I want to,
I want to study,
I need to give a direction to
every edge, so I know a plus and
a minus direction.
So I'll just do that with an
arrow.
Say from one to two,
one to three,
two to three,
one to four,
three to four.
That just tells me,
if I have current flowing on
these edges then I know whether
it's -- to count it as positive
or negative according as whether
it's with the arrow or against
the arrow.
But I just drew those arrows
arbitrarily.
OK.
Because I --
my example is going to come --
the example I'll -- the words
that I will use will be words
like potential,
potential difference,
currents.
In other words,
I'm thinking of an electrical
network.
But that's just one
possibility.
My applied math class builds on
this example.
It could be a hydraulic
network, so we could be doing,
flow of water,
flow of oil.
Other examples,
this could be a structure.
Like the -- a design for a
bridge or a design for a
Buckminster Fuller dome.
Or many other possibilities,
so many.
So l- but let's take potentials
and currents as,
as a basic example,
and let me create the matrix
that tells you exactly what the
graph tells you.
So now I'll call it the
incidence matrix,
incidence matrix.
OK.
So let me write it down,
and you'll see,
what its properties are.
So every row corresponds to an
edge.
I have five rows from five
edges, and let me write down
again what this graph looks
like.
OK, the first edge,
edge one, goes from node one to
two.
So I'm going to put in a minus
one and a plus one in th- this
corresponds to node one two
three and four,
That's a basis for the null
space.
the four columns.
The five rows correspond -- the
first row corresponds to edge
one.
Edge one leaves node one and
goes into node two,
and that --
and it doesn't touch three and
four.
Edge two, edge two goes -- oh,
I haven't numbered these edges.
I just figured that was
probably edge one,
but I didn't say so.
Let me take that to be edge
one.
Let me take this to be edge
two.
three.
This is edge four.
Ho, I'm discovering -- no,
wait a minute.
Did I number that twice?
Here's edge four.
And here's edge five.
OK?
All right.
So, so edge one,
as I said, goes from node one
to two.
Edge two goes from two to
three, node two to three,
so minus one and one in the
second and third columns.
Edge three goes from one to
three.
I'm, I'm tempted to stop for a
moment with those three edges.
Edges one two three,
those form what would we,
what do you call the,
the little, the little,
the subgraph formed by edges
one, two, and three?
That's a loop.
And the number of loops and the
position of the loops will be
crucial.
OK.
Actually, here's a interesting
point about loops.
If I look at those rows,
corresponding to edges one two
three, and these guys made a
loop.
You want to tell me -- if I
just looked at that much of the
matrix it would be natural for
me to ask, are those rows
independent?
Are the rows independent?
And can you tell from looking
at that if they are or are not
independent?
Do you see a,
a relation between those three
rows?
Yes.
If I add that row to that row,
I get this row.
So, so that's like a hint here
that loops correspond to
dependent, linearly dependent
column -- linearly dependent
rows.
OK, let me complete the
incidence matrix.
Number four,
edge four is going from node
one to node four.
And the fifth edge is going
from node three to node four.
OK.
There's my matrix.
It came from the five edges and
the four nodes.
And if I had a big graph,
I'd have a big matrix.
And what questions do I ask
about matrices?
Can I ask -- here's the review
now.
There's a matrix that comes
from somewhere.
If, if it was a big graph,
it would be a large matrix,
but a lot of zeros,
right?
Because every row only has two
non-zeros.
So the number of -- it's a very
sparse matrix.
The number of non-zeros is
exactly two times five,
it's two m.
Every row only has two
non-zeros.
And that's with a lot of
structure.
And -- that was the point I
wanted to begin with,
that graphs,
that real graphs from real --
real matrices from genuine
problems have structure.
OK.
We can ask, and because of the
structure, we can answer,
the, the main questions about
matrices.
So first question,
what about the null space?
So what I asking if I ask you
for the null space of that
matrix?
I'm asking you if I'm looking
at the columns of the matrix,
four columns,
and I'm asking you,
So there's a basis for it,
and here is the whole null
are those columns independent?
If the columns are independent,
then what's in the null space?
Only the zero vector,
right?
The null space contains --
tells us what combinations of
the columns -- it tells us how
to combine columns to get zero.
Can -- and is there anything in
the null space of this matrix
other than just the zero vector?
In other words,
are those four columns
independent or dependent?
What else is in the null space?
OK.
That's our question.
Let me, I don't know if you see
the answer.
Whether there's -- so let's
see.
I guess we could do it
properly.
We could solve Ax=0.
So let me solve Ax=0 to find
the null space.
OK.
What's Ax?
Can I put x in here in,
in little letters?
x1, x2, x3, x4,
that's -- it's got four
columns.
Ax now is that matrix times x.
And what do I get for Ax?
If the camera can keep that
matrix multiplication there,
I'll put the answer here.
Ax equal -- what's the first
component of Ax?
Can you take that first row,
minus one one zero zero,
and multiply by the x,
and of course you get x2-x1.
The second row,
I get x3-x2.
From the third row,
I get x3-x1.
From the fourth row,
I get x4-x1.
And from the fifth row,
I get x4-x3.
And I want to know when is the
thing zero.
This is my equation,
Ax=0.
Notice what that matrix A is
doing, what we've created a
matrix that computes the
differences across every edge,
the differences in potential.
differences are zero,
and that x is in the null
Let me even begin to give this
interpretation.
I'm going to think of this
vector x, which is x1 x2 x3 x4,
as the potentials at the nodes.
So I'm introducing a word,
potentials at the nodes.
And now if I multiply by A,
I get these -- I get these five
components, x2-x1,
et cetera.
And what are they?
They're potential differences.
That's what A computes.
If I have potentials at the
nodes and I multiply by A,
it gives me the potential
differences, the differences in
potential, across the edges.
OK.
When are those differences all
zero?
So I'm looking for the null
space.
Of course, if all the (x)s are
zero then I get zero.
That, that just tells me,
of course, the zero vector is
in the null space.
But w- there's more in the null
space.
Those columns are -- of A are
dependent, right --
because I can find solutions to
that equation.
Tell me -- the null space.
Tell me one vector in the null
space, so tell me an x,
it's got four components,
and it makes that thing zero.
So what's a good x to do that?
One one one one,
constant potential.
If the potentials are constant,
then all the potential
space.
If it -- yeah,
let me ask you just always,
give me a basis for the null
space.
A basis for the null space will
be just that.1
That's --, that's it.
The null space is actually one
dimensional, and it's the line
of all vectors through that one.
space.
Any multiple of one one one
one, it's the whole line in four
dimensional space.
Do you see that that's the null
space?
So the, so the dimension of the
null space of A is one.
And there's a basis for it,
and there's everything that's
in it.
Good.
And what does that mean
physically?
I mean, what does that mean in
the application?
That guy in the null space.
It means that the potentials
can only be determined up to a
constant.
Potential differences are what
make current flow.
That's what makes things
happen.
It's these potential
differences that will make
something move in the,
in our network,
between x2- between node two
and node one.
Nothing will move if all
potentials are the same.
If all potentials are c,
c, c, and c,
then nothing will move.
So we're, we have this one
parameter, this arbitrary
constant that raises or drops
all the potentials.
It's like ranking football
teams, whatever.
We have a, there's a,
there's a constant -- or
looking at temperatures,
you know, there's a flow of
heat from higher temperature to
lower temperature.
If temperatures are equal
there's no flow,
and therefore we can measure --
we can measure temperatures by,
Celsius or we can start at
absolute zero.
And that arbitrary -- it's the
same arbitrary constant that,
that was there in calculus.
In calculus,
right, when you took the
integral, the indefinite
integral, there was a plus c,
and you had to set a starting
point to know what that c was.
So here what often happens is
we fix one of the potentials,
like the last one.
So a typical thing would be to
ground that node.
To set its potential at zero.
And if we do that,
if we fix that potential so
it's not unknown anymore,
then that column disappears and
we have three columns,
and those three columns are
independent.
So I'll leave the column in
there, but we'll remember that
grounding a node is the way to
get it out.
And grounding a node is the way
to -- setting a node -- setting
a potential to zero tells us
the, the base for all
potentials.
Then we can compute the others.
OK.
But what's the --
now I've talked enough to ask
what the rank of the matrix is?
What's the rank then?
The rank of the matrix.
So we have a five by four
matrix.
We've located its null space,
one dimensional.
How many independent columns do
we have?
What's the rank?
It's three.
And the first three columns,
or actually any three columns,
will be independent.
Any three potentials are
independent, good variables.
The fourth potential is not,
we need to set,
and typically we ground that
node.
OK.
Rank is three.
Rank equals three.
OK.
Let's see, do I want to ask you
about the column space?
The column space is all
combinations of those columns.
I could say more about it and I
will.
Let me go to the null space of
A transpose, because the
equation A transpose y equals
zero is probably the most
fundamental equation of applied
mathematics.
All right, let's talk about
that.
That deserves our attention.
A transpose y equals zero.
Let's -- let me put it on here.
OK.
So A transpose y equals zero.
So now I'm finding the null
space of A transpose.
Oh, and if I ask you its
dimension, you could tell me
what it is.
What's the dimension of the
null space of A transpose?
We now know enough to answer
that question.
What's the general formula for
the dimension of the null space
of A transpose?
A transpose,
let me even write out A
transpose.
This A transpose will be n by
m, right?
n by m.
In this case,
it'll be four by five.
Those columns will become rows.
Minus one zero minus one minus
one zero is now the first row.
The second row of the matrix,
one minus one and three zeros.
The third column now becomes
the third row,
zero one one zero minus one.
And the fourth column becomes
the fourth row.
OK, good.
There's A transpose.
That multiplies y,
y1 y2 y3 y4 and y5.
OK.
Now you've had time to think
about this question.
What's the dimension of the
null space, if I set all those
-- wow.
Usually -- sometime during this
semester, I'll drop one of these
erasers behind there.
That's a great moment.
There's no recovery.
There's -- centuries of erasers
are back there.
OK.
OK, what's the dimension of the
null space?
Give me the general formula
first in terms of r and m and n.
This is like crucial,
you -- we struggled to,
to decide what dimension meant,
and then we figured out what it
equaled for an m by n matrix of
rank r, and the answer was m-r,
right?
There are m=5 components,
m=5 columns of A transpose.
And r of those columns are
pivot columns,
because it'll have r pivots.
It has rank r.
And m-r are the free ones now
for A transpose,
so that's five minus three,
so that's two.
And I would like to find this
null space.
I know its dimension.
Now I want to find out a basis
for it.
And I want to understand what
this equation is.
So let me say what A transpose
y actually represents,
why I'm interested in that
equation.
I'll put it down with those old
erasers and continue this.
Here's the great picture of
applied mathematics.
So let me complete that.
There's a matrix that I'll call
C that connects potential
differences to currents.
So I'll call these --
these are currents on the
edges, y1 y2 y3 y4 and y5.
Those are currents on the
edges.
And this relation between
current and potential difference
is Ohm's Law.
This here is Ohm's Law.
Ohm's Law says that the current
on an edge is some number times
the potential drop.
That's -- and that number is
the conductance of the edge,
one over the resistance.
This is the old current is,
is, the relation of current,
resistance, and change in
potential.
So it's a change in potential
that makes some current happen,
and it's Ohm's Law that says
how much current happens.
OK.
And then the final step of this
framework is the equation A
transpose y equals zero.
And that's -- what is that
saying?
It has a famous name.
It's Kirchoff's Current Law,
KCL, Kirchoff's Current Law,
A transpose y equals zero.
So that when I'm solving,
and when I go back up with this
blackboard and solve A transpose
y equals zero,
it's this pattern of -- that I
want you to see.
That we had rectangular
matrices, but -- and real
applications,
but in those real applications
comes A and A transpose.
So our four subspaces are
exactly the right things to know
about.
All right.
Let's know about that null
space of A transpose.
Wait a minute,
where'd it go?
There it is.
OK.
Null space of A transpose.
We know what its dimension
should be.
Let's find out -- tell me a
vector in it.
Tell me -- now,
so what I asking you?
I'm asking you for five
currents that satisfy Kirchoff's
Current Law.
So we better understand what
that law says.
That, that law,
A transpose y equals zero,
what does that say,
say in the first row of A
transpose?
That says -- the so the first
row of A transpose says minus y1
minus y3 minus y4 is zero.
Where did that equation come
from?
Let me -- I'll redraw the
graph.
Can I redraw the graph here,
so that we -- maybe here,
so that we see again -- there
was node one,
node two, node three,
node four was off here.
That was, that was our graph.
We had currents on those.
We had a current y1 going
there.
We had a current y --
what were the other,
what are those edge numbers?
y4 here and y3 here.
And then a y2 and a y5.
I'm, I'm just copying what was
on the other board so it's ea-
convenient to see it.
What is this equation telling
me, this first equation of
Kirchoff's Current Law?
What does that mean for that
graph?
Well, I see y1,
y3, and y4 as the currents
leaving node one.
So sure enough,
the first equation refers to
node one, and what does it say?
It says that the net flow is
zero.
That, that equation A transpose
y, Kirchoff's Current Law,
is a balance equation,
a conservation law.
Physicists, be overjoyed,
right, by this stuff.
It, it says that in equals out.
And in this case,
the three arrows are all going
out, so it says y1,
y3, and y4 add to zero.
Let's take the next one.
The second row is y1-y2,
and that's all that's in that
row.
And that must have something to
do with node two.
And sure enough,
it says y1=y2,
current in equals current out.
The third one,
y2 plus y3 minus y5 equals
zero.
That certainly will be what's
up at the third node.
y2 coming in,
y3 coming in,
y5 going out has to balance.
And finally,
y4 plus y5 equals zero says
that at this node,
y4 plus y5, the total flow,
is zero.
We don't -- you know,
charge doesn't accumulate at
the nodes.
It travels around.
OK.
Now give me -- I come back now
to the linear algebra question.
What's a vector y that solves
these equations?
Can I figure out what the null
space is for this matrix,
A transpose,
by looking at the graph?
I'm happy if I don't have to do
elimination.
I can do elimination,
we know how to do,
we know how to find the null
space basis.
We can do elimination on this
matrix, and we'll get it into a
good reduced row echelon form,
and the special solutions will
pop right out.
But I would like to -- even to
do it without that.
Let me just ask you first,
if I did elimination on that,
on that, matrix,
what would the last row become?
What would the last row -- if I
do elimination on that matrix,
the last row of R will be all
zeros, right?
Why?
Because the rank is three.
We only going to have three
pivots.
And the fourth row will be all
zeros when we eliminate.
So elimination will tell us
what, what we spotted earlier,
what's the null space -- all
the, all the information,
what are the dependencies.
We'll find those by
elimination, but here in a real
example, we can find them by
thinking.
OK.
Again, my question is,
what is a solution y?
How could current travel around
this network without collecting
any charge at the nodes?
Tell me a y.
OK.
So a basis for the null space
of A transpose.
How many vectors I looking for?
Two.
It's a two dimensional space.
My basis should have two
vectors in it.
Give me one.
One set of currents.
Suppose, let me start it.
Let me start with y1 as one.
OK.
So one unit of -- one amp
travels on edge one with the
arrow.
OK, then what?
What is y2?
It's one also,
right?
And of course what you did was
solve Kirchoff's Current Law
quickly in the second equation.
OK.
Now we've got one amp leaving
node one, coming around to node
three.
What shall we do now?
Well, what shall I take for y3
in other words?
Oh, I've got a choice,
but why not make it what you
said, negative one.
So I have just sent current,
one amp, around that loop.
What shall y4 and y5 be in this
case?
We could take them to be zero.
This satisfies Kirchoff's
Current Law.
We could check it patiently,
that minus y1 minus y3 gives
zero.
We know y1 is y2.
The others, y4 plus y5 is
certainly zero.
Any current around a loop
satisfies -- satisfies the
Current Law.
OK.
Now you know how to get another
one.
Take current around this loop.
So now let y3 be one,
y5 be one, and y4 be minus one.
And so, so we have the first
basis vector sent current around
that loop, the second basis
vector sends current around that
loop.
And I've -- and those are
independent, and I've got two
solutions --
two vectors in the null space
of A transpose,
two solutions to Kirchoff's
Current Law.
Of course you would say what
about sending current around the
big loop.
What about that vector?
One for y1, one for y2,
nothing f- on y3,
one for y5, and minus one for
y4.
What about that?
Is that, is that in the null
space of A transpose?
Sure.
So why don't we now have a
third vector in the basis?
Because it's not independent,
right?
It's not independent.
This vector is the sum of those
two.
If I send current around that
and around that --
then on this edge y3 it's going
to cancel out and I'll have
altogether current around the
whole, the outside loop.
That's what this one is,
but it's a combination of those
two.
Do you see that I've now,
I've identified the null space
of A transpose --
but more than that,
we've solved Kirchoff's Current
Law.
And understood it in terms of
the network.
OK.
So that's the null space of A
transpose.
I guess I -- there's always one
more space to ask you about.
Let's see, I guess I need the
row space of A,
the column space of A
transpose.
So what's N,
what's its dimension?
Yup?
What's the dimension of the row
space of A?
If I look at the original A,
it had five rows.
How many were independent?
Oh, I guess I'm asking you the
rank again, right?
And the answer is three,
right?
Three independent rows.
When I transpose it,
there's three independent
columns.
Are those columns independent,
those three?
The first three columns,
are they the pivot columns of
the matrix?
No.
Those three columns are not
independent.
There's a in fact,
this tells me a relation
between them.
There's a vector in the null
space that says the first column
plus the second column equals
the third column.
They're not independent because
they come from a loop.
So the pivot columns,
the pivot columns of this
matrix will be the first,
the second, not the third,
but the fourth.
One, columns one,
two, and four are OK.
Where are they -- those are the
columns of A transpose,
those correspond to edges.
So there's edge one,
there's edge two,
and there's edge four.
So there's a --
that's like -- is a,
smaller graph.
If I just look at the part of
the graph that I've,
that I've, thick -- used with
thick edges, it has the same
four nodes.
It only has three edges.
And the, those edges correspond
to the independent guys.
And in the graph there -- those
three edges have no loop,
right?
The independent ones are the
ones that don't have a loop.
All the -- dependencies came
from loops.
They were the things in the
null space of A transpose.
If I take three pivot columns,
there are no dependencies among
them, and they form a graph
without a loop,
and I just want to ask you
what's the name for a graph
without a loop?
So a graph without a loop is --
has got not very many edges,
right?
I've got four nodes and it only
has three edges,
and if I put another edge in,
I would have a loop.
So it's this graph with no
loops, and it's the one where
the rows of A are independent.
And what's a graph called that
has no loops?
It's called a tree.
So a tree is the name for a
graph with no loops.
And just to take one last step
here.
Using our formula for
dimension.
dimension, let's look -- once at
this formula.
The dimension of the null space
of A transpose is m-r.
OK.
This is the number of loops,
number of independent loops.
m is the number of edges.
And what is r?
What is r for our -- we'll have
to remember way back.
The rank came -- from looking
at the columns of our matrix.
So what's the rank?
Let's just remember.
Rank was -- you remember there
was one -- we had a one
dimensional --
rank was n minus one,
that's what I'm struggling to
say.
Because there were n columns
coming from the n nodes,
so it's minus,
the number of nodes minus one,
because of that C,
that one one one one vector in
the null space.
The columns were not
independent.
There was one dependency,
so we needed n minus one.
This is a great formula.
This is like the first shall I,
-- write it slightly
differently?
The number of edges -- let me
put things -- have I got it
right?
Number of edges is m,
the number -- r- is m-r,
OK.
So, so I'm getting -- let me
put the number of nodes on the
other side.
So I -- the number of nodes --
I'll move that to the other side
-- minus the number of edges
plus the number of loops is -- I
have minus, minus one is one.
The number of nodes minus the
number of edges plus the number
of loops is one.
These are like zero dimensional
guys.
They're the points on the
graph.
The edges are like one
dimensional things,
they're, they connect nodes.
The loops are like two
dimensional things.
They have, like,
an area.
And this count works for every
graph.
And it's known as Euler's
Formula.
We see Euler again,
that guy never stopped.
OK.
And can we just check -- so
what I saying?
I'm saying that linear algebra
proves Euler's Formula.
Euler's Formula is this great
topology fact about any graph.
I'll draw, let me draw another
graph, let me draw a graph with
more edges and loops.
Let me put in lots of -- OK.
I just drew a graph there.
So what are the,
what are the quantities in that
formula?
How many nodes have I got?
Looks like five.
How many edges have I got?
One two three four five six
seven.
How many loops have I got?
One two three.
And Euler's right,
I always get one.
That, this formula,
is extremely useful in
understanding the relation of
these quantities --
the number of nodes,
the number of edges,
and the number of loops.
OK.
Just complete this lecture by
completing this picture,
this cycle.
So let me come to the -- so
this expresses the equations of
applied math.
This, let me call these
potential differences,
say, E.
So E is A x.
That's the equation for this
step.
The currents come from the
potential differences.
y is C E.
The potential -- the currents
satisfy Kirchoff's Current Law.
Those are the equations of --
with no source terms.
Those are the equations of
electrical circuits of many --
those are like the,
the most basic three equations.
Applied math comes in this
structure.
The only thing I haven't got
yet in the picture is an outside
source to make something happen.
I could add a current source
here, I could,
I could add external currents
going in and out of nodes.
I could add batteries in the
edges.
Those are two ways.
If I add batteries in the
edges, they, they come into
here.
Let me add current sources.
If I add current sources,
those come in here.
So there's a,
there's where current sources
go, because the F is a like a
current coming from outside.
So we have our edges,
we have our graph,
and then I send one amp into
this node and out of this node
--
and that gives me,
a right-hand side in Kirchoff's
Current Law.
And can I -- to complete the
lecture, I'm just going to put
these three equations together.
So I start with x,
my unknown.
I multiply by A.
That gives me the potential
differences.
That was our matrix A that the
whole thing started with.
I multiply by C.
Those are the physical
constants in Ohm's Law.
Now I have y.
I multiply y by A transpose,
and now I have F.
So there is the whole thing.
There's the basic equation of
applied math.
Coming from these three steps,
in which the last step is this
balance equation.
There's always a balance
equation to look for.
These are the -- when I say the
most basic equations of applied
mathematics --
I should say,
in equilibrium.
Time isn't in this problem.
I'm not -- and Newton's Law
isn't acting here.
I'm, I'm looking at the --
equations when everything has
settled down,
how do the currents distribute
in the network.
And of course there are big
codes to solve the -- this is
the basic problem of numerical
linear algebra for systems of
equations, because that's how
they come.
And my final question.
What can you tell me about this
matrix A transpose C A?
Or even A transpose A?
I'll just close with that
question.
What do you know about the
matrix A transpose A?
It is always symmetric,
right.
OK, thank.
So I'll see you Wednesday for a
full review of these chapters,
and Friday you get to tell me.
Thanks.